<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The English orator, or, Rhetorical descants by way of declamation upon some notable themes both historical and philosophical in two parts.</title>
            <author>W. R. (William Richards), 1643-1705.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 246 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 101 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A57224</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1375A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R22197</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12059775</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12059775</idno>
            <idno type="VID">53205</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A57224)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 53205)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 576:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The English orator, or, Rhetorical descants by way of declamation upon some notable themes both historical and philosophical in two parts.</title>
                  <author>W. R. (William Richards), 1643-1705.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 191, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Obadiah Blagrave ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata and advertisement: p. [1] at end.</note>
                  <note>Dedication and preface signed: William Richards.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:53205:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:53205:1"/>
            <p>THE Engliſh Orator OR <hi>Rhetorical Deſcants</hi> By way of DECLAMATION Upon ſome notable THEMES BOTH Hiſtorical and Philoſophical.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In Two Parts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Obadiah Blagrave</hi> at the Sign of the <hi>Bear</hi> in St. <hi>Paul's</hi> Church yard, 1680.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:53205:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:53205:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Worſhipful Sir <hi>Francis Leigh</hi> Knight, of <hi>Wickham</hi> in <hi>Kent.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honour'd Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THe firſt Proſpect of your Perſon, methoughts, preſented me with ſuch a Landskip of Candor and Ingenuity, of ſuch ſweetneſs of Diſpoſition and native Goodneſs, as that I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently began not only to admire the Sc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e of your Accompliſhments, but paſſionately to be raviſht with the Love of them. The ſecret charms of I know not what Excellency (Ethicks her ſelf can't give it a name) that runs through and adorns the whole frame and courſe of your Life and Being, did ſo captivate and affect me, as that I wiſht I might be ſo happy as to enjoy the Mercy of your Worthy Acquaintance; and to live under the influence of ſo much Vertue, I wiſh't I might be bleſt with an opportunity of expreſſing the Religion of that Homage and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice,
<pb facs="tcp:53205:3"/>which I owe to you; and of preſenting you with ſomewhat as a Pledge and Emblem of the profoundeſt Eſteem, and moſt devout Affection I bear towards you: And indeed Providence hath been ſo propitious as to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer my deſires, in occaſionally fixing me ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times near you, and in placing me within the Verge of that Paradiſe, which your Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence Conſecrates where ever it is; ſo that I have often been ennobled, nay almoſt deified in the <hi>Eliſium</hi> of your Company, have become lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by your Converſe, have grown Prudent by your Example, have been maintained at your Table, have been feaſted with Civilities both from your Perſon and Fortune, and have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed the Favours of all your circumſtances and capacities; For which I return you an Eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Thanks. Neither am I unſucceſſeful in my ſecond Prayers, Fortune having put into mine hands an opportunity, whereby I am capacitated to put ſomewhat into yours; I mean this inconſiderable trifle, which I do not Dedicate as a Preſent to requite you, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as a Toy to play withall, and to divert you. I hope you will pardon the Soleciſm, and Impropriety of the Gift, for I muſt confeſs I am ſenſible of mine Errour in Prefacing with ſo ſtately a Frontiſpeice ſo mean an Edifice; I mean in prefixing your name to ſo poor a
<pb facs="tcp:53205:3"/>Pamphlet, your more curious Ingenuity, large Capacity, and univerſal Accompliſhments in more ſolid Learning, I know deſerve a treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Quintenſence and Elixirs of choicer Muſes: I am not ignorant, that knotty Maxims of Policy, ſubtleties of Government, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trigues of State; a miſtery in Divinity, and ſublimer Speculations are more ſuitable Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainments to the Acuteneſs of your Parts, the Swiftneſs of your Apprehenſion and Penetra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of your Judgment; But when I conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that you have advanc't ſo far in all Are and Science, as that the utmoſt of my Studies can't contribute one thought to further your Progreſs. I ſay, ſeeing I cannot inform you, hubmly crave leave with theſe Toys to recreate you. They were the Spawn and Iſſue of ſome ſpare hours, and are fit only for the Entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of idle time; 'tis not handſome nor mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh for me to commend them; only thus much I think I may ſafely ſay, if you are inclin'd to ſleep, their lulling Quality will be <hi>Poppy</hi> to your temples, and may procure a nod as ſoon perhaps, as the greateſt <hi>Narcotick,</hi> which if it does effect, it will do you a kindneſs, in removing you from the noiſe of a tumultuous world, and in relieving you with the eaſe and ſoftneſs of a ſilent ſlumber. I now withdraw from your preſence to prevent the creation of a
<pb facs="tcp:53205:4"/>further trouble. All that I deſire, is a Candid acceptance of what is here tender'd; which if you ſhall graciouſly receive as a meer teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of my gratefull reſpects for all Favours, without any further deſign on your Worth and Goodneſs, I am at the height of mine Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, and have obtained the end of my pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Addreſſes. <hi>I am</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Honour'd Sir</salute> 
               <signed>Your moſt Humbly Devoted Servant <hi>William Richards.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>Helmdon.</dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:53205:4"/>
            <head>THE Preface TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Preſent thee (moſt Courteous Reader!) with a Manual of Thoughts on Miſcellane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Subjects. They were hatcht in the retire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of a Country Cell, and now fly abroad into the world, not ſo much to boaſt the paint of their Plumes and Elegancy of their dreſs, as the newneſs of their garb and habit, wherein they appear; there being nothing extant of this Nature in Engliſh, we being wholly deſtitute of Declama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in our Language. I muſt confeſs there can be no great want, or thirſt of Oratory, as long as <hi>Quintilian</hi> and <hi>Seneca</hi> among the Ancients; <hi>Putean, Ferrarius, Gardiner</hi> and others of a
<pb facs="tcp:53205:5"/>later date, have oblig'd the world with ſuch Eloquent Streams; But yet their Rhetorick flowing in a Latine Channel, all are not capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of drinking in their Current. But this Tractate is calculated for Readers of a lower rank, and yet affords brisk Entertainment for thoſe of an higher. 'Tis written in a modern Style, and is exactly compoſed after the ſame model as uſually harangues of this nature are now adays. The firſt Part are flouriſhes on certain Paſſages, which occur in Hiſtory; ſome of which Fancy hath adorned with her Conceits on both ſides, others on one ſide, ſhe hath left untouch't and naked: The latter are Meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons on ſeveral Queſtions in Ethicks, Politicks and Natural Philoſophy, as I occaſionally pop't upon them, and they have pleaſed my Genius. If what I have garniſht them with, pleaſe your palat, the Kind Acceptance of this firſt diſh, will encourage me to treat you with a ſecond Courſe.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>W. R.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:53205:5"/>
            <head>THE Engliſh Orator.</head>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <div n="1" type="declamation">
                  <head>DECLAM. I. <hi>A certain Damſel reduc'd to want, ſells her Hair to relieve her in her Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>IF no reproach can fully the brightneſs, nor eclipſe the glory of ſhining Vertue; if the calumny that perſecutes a famous Exploit, add to the Praiſe of him that atchiev'd it, Then our Virgin amongſt the diſtracting cares of pinching Poverty, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratulates the cenſure of that action, by which ſhe ſhew'd her ſelf more than Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. 'Twould have made the Modeſty of a Maid to Bluſh, ſo publickly to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:53205:6"/>to the view of the world, but that ſhe is inflam'd with that ſacred Ardor, which is kindled in the Breaſt of pious Matrons, when concern'd and zealous for the injur'd Fame of their traduc'd Innocence.</p>
                  <p>On her own accord ſhe ſues for Judgment, not as if conſcious to her ſelf, ſhe did at all fear, leaſt ſilence ſhould ſpeak her guilty; But that ſhe might publickly wipe off all Aſperſions, and might comfortably enjoy her Accuſation: ſhe had no need of an Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocate to defend the ſale of her comly treſſes, her hard Fortune was plea ſufficient, and ſhe is abundantly protected by her chaſt Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity.</p>
                  <p>This wretched Damſel in this ſad condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion could neither hope for Hatred, nor ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect Envy; ſhe ſuppos'd her miſeries a charm againſt the malignity of the ſevereſt Fortune, and her obſcurity a ſanctuary againſt any harm; and therefore doth at once both wonder, and grieve too, that ſhe is ſummo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to a Tribunal; as if ſhe were encircled with a Crown of Happineſs, or were an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject worthy of Spleen and Malice. This poor Girl implores your pity, both on her ſlender Eſtate and her Baldneſs too; which was not caus'd by ſlothful age, or feeble luſt, but was inflicted upon her by ravenous hunger
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:53205:6"/>and the mercileſs tyranny of cruel deſtiny, ſhe was diſtreſs'd in her infancy, and felt the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor of Fortune in her very cradle; where ſhe ſeem'd at once with the ſame cry both to deprecate her nakedneſs and lament it too.</p>
                  <p>Her miſeries increas'd as ſhe grew in years; and Poverty (as it were) was equally adult with her perſon too. What ſhould this Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin do ſo miſerably involv'd in ſo great Evils? Her extremity render her labour and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry vain and fruitleſs; and ſuch a Lent of faſting had whither'd the Spring of her blooming youth into the Autumnal decays of wrinckled age. After ſhe had a long time ſtriven, and all in vain, with theſe her ſtubborn and obſtinate troubles. At length ſhe finds out ſome little redreſs for all her grievance, and an innocent remedy for her urgent neceſſity; ſhe cuts off her locks to ſupply her wants. And indeed in ſo preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing a calamity, ſhe was glad to find any thing that was vendible, any thing that could refreſh the languors, and ſtrengthen the weakneſs of her feeble limbs, and by a ſhort truce prevent the invaſion of approaching death. If it be lawful with any price to bribe off deſtruction, and with all arts ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable to purchaſe the comforts of preſent life, Then, why is this Damſel cenſur'd for a
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:53205:7"/>little deferring her fatal blow, and for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeming with ſpoils of her own body the delights and Pleaſures of a few days. Although loſs of Hair is an unhandſome defect in the female Sex, yet where is the woman, that ſtudies her dreſs, or regards gallantry amidſt the dubious concerns of an uncertain life, and the expected horrors of almoſt preſent death? Affected neatneſs and curioſity of attire, is quite neglected, when the pale fiend advanceth forward, in a frightful garb of his own terrors darting himſelf in a glance or look. Want of Hair is far more tolerable than want of Bread; and Baldneſs to be preferr'd before Hunger, and the continual languors of a ſtarv'd carkaſs. 'Tis far more pleaſant to have no Hair than to dye by degrees, and to periſh inſenſibly by piece-meal, and tedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly to depart, and (as it were) after repeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Funerals to breath her laſt. Though a naked head in a wench is ſcandalous, yet why ſhould diſgraces vex her? 'Tis Revenge enough to ſee her pale, and to hear the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cents of her mournful groans.</p>
                  <p>Suffer therefore this unhappy Virgin to enjoy the benefit of her baldneſs, and let her live in her own puniſhment. See! The woods are depriv'd of their leaves and orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:53205:7"/>and the <hi>Dryades</hi> ſuffer (as it were) an annual baldneſs for the better increaſe of their inward vigor, and that under the pretence and ſhew of age, they may reſume and flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh in a freſher verdure, and boaſt the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gance and flower of their retriv'd youth; ſhe cares not for Deformity, Infamy, nor her Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion neither, ſo long as hunger (like an Enemy) forrages within making men <hi>Canni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bals</hi> to themſelves, and (O horrible!) devour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the prey of their own members. When Famine had added terror to her eyes, and you might have contemplated her ſtiff joints, and bloodleſs cheeks, you would have ſtood amaz'd at the ſight of this Ghoſt of a carcaſs; eſpecially to have ſeen, amidſt the ugly ſhapes, and figures of death, the diſchevell'd wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonneſs of her looſe treſſes, nouriſht by the horror and dread of Fate, and produc'd by ſquallid Contagion and Putrefaction.</p>
                  <p>We have here an excellent Example of rare Prudence, and an admirable pattern of ſingular Virtue. Behold! an unhappy Laſs amids the Inconveniences of a Cottage, and other hardſhips of an adverſe Fortune deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the blandiſhments, and flatteries of the world; nay more, contemns that, which either Hunger or Want ought to have deſir'd, ſhe ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered that which the women of <hi>Aquileia</hi> had
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:53205:8"/>done before her, who amidſt the ravenings of War, and Famine, pol'd their heads, not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe grief or deſpair, but danger commands them to make halry bowſtrings.</p>
                  <p>Our poor Girl hath ſuffer'd war, hath en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dur'd famin, yet hath return'd with equal Victory: If therefore you will ſtill go on to condemn her baldneſs, why do you not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn her chaſtity too? and cenſure the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blem of the greateſt Modeſty? ſhe could not behold her deformity with a greater diſlike than her attempted Virginity; and a ſollicitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to diſhoneſty was in her Judgement capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal. She ſhaves her head, ſells her hair, leſt her poverty ſhould tempt her to become a proſtitute; and ſo by the damage of her beauty prevents her infamy; Pardon therefore the fall and loſs of thoſe locks, which if kept any longer, had prov'd fatal to her Virtue! Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don that ſhe ſold them, which was not ſo much to prolong her life, as before a Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunal to give the reaſon of that her Action. She humbly implores you, to let her enjoy the innocence of her calamity, and alſo the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts of Poverty, Baldneſs, and Chaſtity.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="declamation">
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:53205:8"/>
                  <head>DECLAM. II. <hi>Againſt the Girl that cut off her Hair to relieve her want.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>I Pray do not think that I being a yong man do willingly accuſe this fair Maid, who beſides is young and tender, and had ſhe not loſt her Hair is a beauty too. There lies a neceſſity upon me of undertaking this un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grateful Province. Behold this wretched young wench every way ſurrounded with the greateſt extremity! 'Tis true indeed, ſhe is ſufficiently embelliſh'd with the endowments of nature, but poorly furniſh't (God wot) with the gifts of Fortune; being far better adorn'd with beauty, than enrich't with an Eſtate; ſhe hath a cheſt indeed, but ſmall and empty. But though Fortune heaps no gold in her coffer, yet Nature hath ſhed it upon her Hair. But ſee! at length this blind Goddeſs ſends her gifts, but I fear on hooks, and ſo baits the Damſel with her deceitful pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents. The ſilly Girl receives with one hand the boons of Fortune, and beſtows with
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:53205:9"/>the other the goods of Nature; ſhe takes the money, and gives her hair.</p>
                  <p>But (alas!) of how little value are theſe dangling treſſes, thoſe ſuperfluous threds of her troubled head, if compared with the om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotence of ſacred gold? 'Twas this opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that deceiv'd the Virgin into ſuch deformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which ſhe had rather richly endure with money, than poorly without it to enjoy her beauty entire: and her charms inviolable; as if one and the ſame could not be fair and needy; and as if the features of a woman were not a richer dowry, than <hi>Attalick</hi> wealth. Beauty doth that in the ſofter ſex, which va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour doth in the ſtronger; and as this doth en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noble the baſe, and advance them to a pitch of dignity and honour, ſo that doth raiſe the mean, and recommend them to the embraces of Kings and Princes. How vile therefore and what a nothing is a little modicum, a parcel of money, if ſtanding in competition with the Divinity of beauty! This unfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate Laſs hath made ſuch a ſwop as <hi>Glaucus</hi> in <hi>Homer,</hi> who chang'd away his gold foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhly for braſs, and may deſervedly be ſtyl'd the very Proverb of ſtupidity.</p>
                  <p>But conſider, (I pray) urgent neceſſity did preſs upon her: The reward of her hands could hardly defend her from the injuries of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:53205:9"/>cold and hunger; labour and diligence was all her poſſeſſion, and her whole revenue. But who diminiſheth that true wealth far to be preferred above <hi>Perſian</hi> riches? But what hurt is there in a ſhaven crown, though there is no money given for the filth and excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of a naſty head? We confeſs our hair to be nothing elſe but the ſcurff and dregs of a cribrous head, ſtretch't and extended into ſlender threds; but the more vile the mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rials, the more admirable and exquiſite the skill and workmanſhip. The excellency of theſe above other locks doth evidently ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear from the very deſires of him that buys them, which were greedy and pecunia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. Behold! how importunate his petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons! How vehement his wiſhes! and how eagerly doth he long for the poſſeſſion of them? For this very reaſon (O beſieg'd Virgin!) becauſe he is ſo inſtant, deny his requeſt; for if fictitious cruck's add ſuch a grace to other heads what glories and pret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſſes muſt theſe ſcatter upon her neck, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing never tranſplanted from their native ſoil, nor ever depriv'd of their natural elegance.</p>
                  <p>On this thy crime do thou thy ſelf paſs ſentence (O moſt indiſcreet Virgin!) Thou canſt not be acquitted by thy ſelf thy Judge. The richer mettal of thy golden hair thou haſt
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:53205:10"/>chang'd, and truck't for viler ſilver, and ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> deliver'd that to the buyer, which might have been a credit and an ornament to the ſeller— Beware therefore for the future of thine own glaſs; For that which even now did pleaſe thee with the lovely reflection of thy flattered Image now affright's thee with the mormo's, and repreſented horrours of thine ugly ſhapes: neither is there any reaſon why thou ſhouldſt expect a milder doom from our tribunal, whoſe candour, ſmiles, and expanded brow, your filthy baldneſs hath terrified and conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into contracted frowns.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="declamation">
                  <head>DECLAM. III. Tiberius <hi>did well, in forbidding the Kindred of thoſe that were Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to Lament and Mourn.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>IF the ſacredneſs of Laws ought to be kept and preſerved inviolable; and if a do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſtick conſpirator is more dangerous than a forreign invader, then wicked ſighs brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:53205:10"/>out for criminals, are to be accus'd as guilty, and mourning weeds preſage as much the fate of the mourner, as the death of him for whom he griev's. Certainly the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour did well conſult the good of his Citizens who forbad and condemn'd both the rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and impiety of thoſe groans and tears that were both utter'd and ſhed at a wicked funeral. That conſpiracy ought to be bury'd in the deepeſt ſilence, which, with a clamo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous grief would recal the ſoul of an expiring Tyrant, repair the decays of waſted ſtrength, and with a new life reſtore freſh and more vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorous treacheries. It had been noble and generous at the death of a Captain, though an enemy, to perform ſuch funeral rites; which his ſouldiers would have celebrated with ſolemn pomp. Thus in vain the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roe of old breath'd his ſoul into his gaſping companion, in vain he embrac't him, clos'd his eyes, and in vain he imbib'd his laſt breath: But when a villain dyes, let his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour fear, nay let his unhappy iſſue too, to ſuck and receive his laſt ſpirit, leſt the wretch ſhould bequeath in the legacy of a ſob his crimes and ſhould pant ſlaughter, and ſo after death live in his kindred ſtill a murderer; as mad dogs by biting and hags by kiſſing inſtill their poyſons, and leave a deadly dart on their
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:53205:11"/>friends lips. Hence often it is that an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent ſon poſſeſſing the ſoul of his damn'd father, inherits his vices and his puniſhments too.</p>
                  <p>The Deities would have us dumb and ſilent who with ſecret darts do ſcatter death, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidding all noiſe, but their own thunder, and ſeeing no body that's guilty dies lamented by his neighbour, we muſt obey Fate; Thus one being ſmitten, the prudent herd conſulting its ſafety, deny's a refuge to the wounded Deer, and willingly comply's with the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pert Archer to prevent the ſlaughter of more ſacrifices.</p>
                  <p>Grief trickling from Parents in ſuch li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beral ſhowers, ſeems to ſuſpect the integrity of the Judge, and to accuſe the magiſtrate of injuſtice too, whilſt he is thought to be cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt, and his power criminal. And indeed, well may ſuch tears affright, and terrify, which do patronize wickedneſs, and it's Authors too. Though they diſtil ſilently, and in their firſt drops diſcover only but feeble angers, but at length, when floods ſhall meet with floods, and Blaſts of ſighs are oppoſed by blaſts, then the deluge of ſorrow ſwells into complaints, and boils, and ferments into impotent revenge. The aſpect of theſe mourners grow fierce and cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:53205:11"/>who execute with their looks, and mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the aſſertors of their own right. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſuch mild ſeverity, and ſo calm a ſtorm, let it ſhame the Citizens to weep more! let them bluſh to grieve for dying treachery, and let not the out-cry of a conclamation, but more pleaſant noiſes attend the herſe! If a doleful mother always pregnant with a vitious brood, ſhould ſtill deplore her nefarious off-ſpring, in vain are priſons, and tribunals; where the Hypocriſie of grief, and counterfeit lamentations corrupt the fidelity and integrity both of Judge and witneſs; and ſo the guilty enjoy their ſuffrages, and ſo numerous Patrons of vice do expiate the crime.</p>
                  <p>If guilt be in ſo great eſteem, let the Guard be armed from a full priſon, and let the weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing City reduced and profligated by a rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious Citizen, feel thoſe treacheries, of which the lamented villains were the Authors! and let it deplore the loſs of its robuſt vigor ſo plainly enfeebled by their ſtrength; Thus the ſwift Hart is griev'd at his horns, when their unprofitable weight does hinder flight, and when the uſeleſs burden of his branch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing head ſhall expoſe him as a prey to the cruel hunter. The condition of the Repub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick was more proſperous, and flouriſhing after the ſlaughter of theſe Citizens; For
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:53205:12"/>whilſt friends do torment, and joyfully pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh malefactors, the old contagion begins to languiſh, and that priſtine fury diſpers'd amongſt many dyes and determines in the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor only: But if turgent ſorrow ſhall im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove the fertility of growing impiety, and the poyſon that's nouriſh't in one member doth not only infect a ſingle man, but cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt alſo the whole alliance, then the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſionate Father in vain laments his conſcious grief, the Mother in vain repents of her un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt ſorrow and that ſhe hath thus polluted her innocent tears, which deſerve to be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh't, not for her own, but only for the guilt of her condemn'd ſon. And thus, whilſt the ſame crime hath made them all equal, and they are as much ally'd by vice, as blood, let the whole family be accus'd, and the whole progeny be condemn'd! let no ſolemn ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours confiſcate with his heritage attend his herſe; no funeral rites grace and adorn his prophane pile! Let not his condemned aſhes enjoy the repoſe of a quiet Urn! Let his carcaſs lye unburied, that as well dead as alive he may ſuffer puniſhment.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="declamation">
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:53205:12"/>
                  <head>DECLAM. IV. <hi>The</hi> Carthaginians <hi>did very ill, in cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifying a Captain unadviſedly waging war, though he returned with Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THough a reverent eſteem is to be ſhewn to Laws, and the ſanctions of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey are not to be deſpiſed, yet 'tis unjuſt (methinks) to condemn to the croſs this Captain, who ſo unwillingly did violate but one of theſe, and that meerly to defend the City, and all things beſides, from the violence and injury of a furious enemy. Law-givers know not what a day may bring forth; their Conſtitutions and Decrees muſt give place a little when occaſion ſhall require, the Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of the General is diſregarded; leſt, if the Magiſtrate ſhould by a Gibbet deterr the Souldiers from conquering againſt their or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, they ſhould ſo much fear capital puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as not to endeavour the ſafety of the Republick. How doth this Captain fluctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:53205:13"/>afflicted with the dubious fate of <hi>Metius,</hi> being on all ſides diſtracted by inſtant death! If he ſhould be conquer'd, he becomes a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice to the inſolence of his enemy; and ſo ruine and deſtruction muſt needs befall him; but if he triumphs, the croſs, a gibbet, and a more ignoble fate attends him. However he had rather try the clemency of noted <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thage,</hi> than expoſe himſelf, his Countrey, to the cruelty of a Victorious, and odious Nation. He hop'd that his good ſucceſs might have eaſily atton'd for the envy of the fact, and that it would not have been ſo ungrateful to <hi>Carthage;</hi> in regard he had been ſo adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tageous to it. He fights therefore and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes, and by the votes of the <hi>Carthaginians</hi> he is adjudged to the croſs. A man certainly moſt worthy of life, who for the publick good made himſelf obnoxious to ſo ſevere a death.</p>
                  <p>But what unjuſt cruelty is this, to hurry a Conquerour ſpared by the tempeſt of war and arms, to a puniſhment more barbarous than his enemies ſword? He that contrary to the Laws, and with ſuſpence of ſucceſs, or unfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunately joins battle, let him endure the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved ſmart of his own raſhneſs; but who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever inflicts penance on a Conqueror, whoſe war both the favour of the Gods, and the event do allow of, he both diſquiets and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſes
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:53205:13"/>Heaven. By what an unhappy kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the fates hath our captain ſurvived the battle, to be reſerv'd a victime for the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minious croſs! He might have fell (being conquer'd) by the revenge of his enemies, without the crime of a guilty Judge. But whilſt by the unjuſt ſuffrages of the Citizens he is puniſh't with a gibbet and diſgrac't too; the life of the Conquerour, and the juſtice of the Country go both to wrack.</p>
                  <p>So falls our Captain, as famous for the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of his excellent valour, as remarkable for the diſgrace of an ungrateful City; who, that he might render <hi>Carthage</hi> victorious, was not ſtartled at the danger, either of field or tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunal, but twice hazarded his life, and had twice conquer'd, if the <hi>Carthaginians</hi> had not been more obdurate than his enemies ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. He dy'd not being overpower'd in bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel, neither through his own miſcarrage or default of Fortune, his puniſhment is aggrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the unworthineſs of it, for he is adjudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by them to death, to whom by his victory he gave life.</p>
                  <p>This great Severity may be thought the greateſt Juſtice; which though it may be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended perhaps by Law, yet not in Equity. What if the Captain being aſſur'd of Victory did not expect the commands of his Country?
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:53205:14"/>An Enemy may be conquered before it can be determined by the Senate, whether a Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral ſhall fight or not. The Fate of this Officer is very deplorable, who might be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell'd by the Laws to be conquer'd, but could not overcome ſecurely againſt them. But the ſenſe of the Law is to be regarded, and not the terms. The <hi>Carthaginians</hi> forbad their Generals to fight againſt the Orders and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions of their Country, becauſe Captains, eſpecially young ones, are inflam'd with a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of Renown and Victory, and oftentimes run upon an engagement raſhly, ſo that the Strength and Proſperity of the Republick is much abated, and the Glory of their Nation obſcur'd by the fatal overthrow of their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feated Army.</p>
                  <p>But our Captain, wiſe and prudent, as well as valiant, knew he ſhould conquer before he ſought; neither is it to be doubted, but that the Law-givers themſelves, if they had been preſent at the Warr, and had underſtood the conveniences of Fighting would have adviſed to them an Encounter. How unjuſt therefore is it to condemn that, which, if preſent, they had approv'd of; and that too after the Victory was won, and Trophies raiſed through the Conduct and Valour of this wiſe Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain!—Certainly there is reaſon to ſuſpect
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:53205:14"/>that the <hi>Carthaginians</hi> did not ſo much take ill the violation of the Law, as they envyed the Honors and Triumphs of the Victor; and therefore cenſur'd him to ſo ſhameful a death. His doom was barbarous and cruel, and if after the dangers of War the Citizens ſhall thus at home threaten the croſs to their victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Captains, they may deſervedly fear, leaſt hereafter they ſhould want men to defend their Countrey.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="declamation">
                  <head>DECLAM. V. <hi>Whether</hi> Codrus <hi>did well in devoting himſelf to deſtruction, and loſing both his Life and Liberty for the ſafety of his Country.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <head type="sub">
                     <hi>Againſt</hi> Codrus.</head>
                  <p>SEeing there is no Happineſs to a people, but what depends on the Counſel and Valour of a prudent Prince, He therefore
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:53205:15"/>that throws away his life for his Countries good, ſeems not ſo much to prevent it's miſery, as to increaſe and haſten its approaching Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine. For after the deceaſe of a valiant Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour who dares not aſſault a people wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and without a head? Who dares not provoke them being deſtitute, and void of Strength? Who hopes not to ſubdue them, and to raiſe Trophies to himſelf from their Spoils, ſeeing they are without Counſel, which is a ſtronger fortreſs aginſt their Enemy, than Bulwarks and Caſtles.</p>
                  <p>The ſudden death of <hi>Codrus</hi> might perhaps remove from his Country ſome preſent cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity; it might perhaps diſperſe an imminent Storm. But (alas!) to what Evils is it left expos'd, now he is gone, who could alone preſerve it who whilſt he liv'd was its only ſafeguard? There is no Law obſerved now the Emperour is dead. The diſtracted Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſheath their ſwords in their own bowels, and by mutuall ſlaughters bring that deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on upon themſelves, which was forbidden by the Oracle to fall upon the <hi>Peleponenſiaus.</hi> No Homage, and Obedience is paid to Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours, the Subject hath ſhaken off the yoke from his neck, and every miſcreant lays un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt claim to that Empire, which was left by the Princes voluntary death — Thus (O <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drus!</hi>)
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:53205:15"/>haſt thou involved others in thine own Ruine, and thy Death hath been more pernicious to thy Country than ever could thy Life be, which was ſo odious (as thou thought'ſt) to the <hi>Athenians.</hi> But yet 'twas ſo dear to the Gods, as that thine Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies were commanded not to deprive thee of it, or to dip their ſwords in thy precious gore. But thou diſdainſt ſo kind a Favour, and by fighting (like the Giants) againſt Heaven, haſt expoſed thy ſelf to an ignominious Death. For <hi>Codrus</hi> did not Heroically in the Feild diſcomfit his Enemy with a threatning look, neither ſhining in Armor, or beſmear'd with Blood, did he breath his laſt, but deludes his Enemy with a diſguiſe in the habit of a poor man, and doth ſpontaneouſly embrace a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generous Death.</p>
                  <p>Seeing he undertook ſuch great things for his Country, he (without doubt) propos'd to himſelf great Rewards; ſuch as ſhould pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe him an eternal name, and tranſmit his Fame to future Ages. But who will lament his immature Fate, whereas the Ruine of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publick is to be more deplored? What Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject will ſing his Encomiums, ſeeing he hath deceivep not only his Enemies, but his Friends too? His Fate is deplorable on both ſides, ſeeing by his death the Garland is won,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:53205:16"/>and the Empire is deſtroyed. Thou waſt inflamed (O <hi>Codrus!</hi>) with too great a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion and Zeal for thy Country, who waſt ſo forgetful of thy Life and Liberty, and dids't ſo contemn the Care of the Gods. If the former courſe of thy Life was juſt, yet now thou haſt committed an heinous Crime, thus by offering violence to Nature, and exerciſing Tyranny over thy ſelf, Let not Nature be thus violated!</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Codrus</hi> hath loſt his golden Liberty, to free his Country from filthy Bondage; hath laid down his Life to give it continuance, and to reſcue it from Death; But how can it ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vive, and live, when he is dead, who by his Valour alone did preſerve and defend it, and who (whilſt in Being) was both the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light and Orna<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ent of the People. He had more prudently conſulted the <hi>Athenians</hi> good, if he had ſtill reign'd, and if the Enemy had not kill'd the Prince, but the People, and brought them to ſo ſad and fatal an end.</p>
                  <p>Thus liv'd this ſtout Heroe, who might law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſupport the ſinking ſtate, might puniſh the pride of his triumphant Enemies, might with his Life and Valour (ſeeing he could purchaſe Victory by his own Blood) have animated and encouraged the conquered <hi>Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians,</hi> and repaied their ſlaughter again with
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:53205:16"/>ruine. For tis not the part of a Valiant Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to yield at the firſt wound, but obſtinate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to purſue flying Victory, and with a perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacious reſolution, ſolicite adverſe and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luctant Fortune; and as it were extort vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently from the Gods the Palm of Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Codrus</hi> by his ſignal Piety to his Country, hath through his Death purchas'd to the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenians</hi> Victory and Safety; But yet he had ſhew'd himſelf more wiſe, and valiant, if eſcaping but one, though unhappy battel, he at length by a more proſperous event of War, had made himſelf Victorious, and his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try too.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="declamation">
                  <head>DECLAM. VI. <hi>Whether</hi> Paulus Emilius <hi>did well, who, utterly deſparing of the Safety of the Republick, ruſh't wilſully into the Battel, and caus'd his own Death.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>AFter ſo unfortunate a management of Affairs, after ſo cruel a ſlaughter of his Souldiers, and the total overthrow of his
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:53205:17"/>whole Army. Can <hi>Aemilius</hi> (do you think) live an ignoble Life? Do you believe I can endure <hi>Hannibal</hi> fluſh'd with Victory, and triumphing over a routed Conſul? Seeing my Souldiers are ſo ambitious of the glory of Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, that when their Strength fails, and their hands are unprofitable, they had rather ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe their heads to the Conquerours weapons than decline a Fight, as if they would hinder Victory, when they cannot conquer: Seeing my Common Souldiers give ſo excellent a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cimen of <hi>Roman</hi> Courage, ſhall <hi>Paulus</hi> their General baſely fly? Seeing my ſtout Cavalry protected me in the Battel, and ſo bravely fell in the hot diſpute, ſhall I baſely ſurvive them, and run to <hi>Rome?</hi> And there (like Women and Children) lament the Ruine of the State which I had ſo illy defended? Shall I on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhed tears for my Countrey, whilſt you faithful Souls pour out no leſs than your laſt Breath? Rather let mine Enemy ſlice me into a thouſand peices, and ſpill my very heart-blood; that the Citizens may know, that I contemn Death with the ſame Courage, as I did formerly their unjuſt Reproaches, and let the Conquerour <hi>Hannibal</hi> underſtand, that we have yielded to him in Fortune only, but not in Valour. I fear not to be cenſur'd Raſh and Furious, and too unadviſed in my
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:53205:17"/>Actions, for what do I deſire that ſeems ſo unreaſonable? Seeing I cannot live without Reproach, and Envy, I only ſeek an honeſt Death.</p>
                  <p>You all know in my former Conſulſhip, when things were better with me than now, how I ſcarce eſcap't with my Life from the Popular Tumult; And what do you think the diſpleaſed People will do in ſo great a Deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Slaughter of their Souldiers? But why do I mention things of ſo long a date? In this preſent Conſulſhip the ungrateful Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens did upbraid with Sloath and Cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardize, though by my Care and Counſel, I diverted this Plague that hung over their heads, and reſcu'd my men from the jaws of their Enemies by detecting their Treacheries. What a man have I ſhewed my ſelf in this Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel, who have fought illy, and (ſeeing I durſt not die) who have fled more baſely? Fancy me leading, like Cattle, the remainder (if there be any left) of my rallied Army, through unwayed Mountains, and Summer Thickets! Fancy us to fly (like Harts) and to be ſtun'd with the noiſe of our cloſe Purſuers! Fancy us entring the City overwhelm'd with griefe, and their Sorrow to ſwell at our Approaches! I am not to be carried there (after the <hi>Roman</hi> manner) in a Triumphant Chariot; And
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:53205:18"/>indeed, I know not the uſe of ſuch a Chariot, unleſs to carry me to the utmoſt limits and bounds of the Earth, whither the name of <hi>Hannibal,</hi> the Report of this Overthrow, and the Execrations of the City cannot reach.</p>
                  <p>Methinks I ſee the Patrons, and the Cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents mixt together, and all in Publick! Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks I ſee the wretched Matrons running on all ſides to the Hallowed Temples, and ſweep the Altars with diſhevel'd Treſſes! We hear nothing but the Howlings and Lamentations of the Citizens; nothing but the complaints of them that weep. In vain they do now im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plore my Aid; now they curſe that unhappy General. Methinks, I hear the enraged Multitude railing againſt me in ſuch language; Give me my Children! Reſtore my Parents! Return my Souldiers, who may defend the walls! All which Clamour is an harſher ſound than noiſe of the treacherous <hi>Carthaginians,</hi> that aſſanlted us in the Rear, than the groans of Souldiers beſet with Enemies, than the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal voice of <hi>Hannibal,</hi> whereby he pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to his Souldiers certain Victory.</p>
                  <p>But though things are grievous, yet if they benefit my Countrey, I can bravely bear them. I could wiſh to live though in Diſgrace and Infamy, if thereby I could any wiſe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage the Republick. But what profit
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:53205:18"/>can accrue to you from the ſingle Valour of one, and he but a private perſon? Where elſe can I have another Army? With what Courage will Souldiers fight under ſo unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py a Captain? Surely they will find a more proſperous General. Why being a Coward do I live ſo long? unleſs it be to ſee another Conſul ſubduing thoſe Enemies that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer'd me, or to ſee the demoliſh't walls of <hi>Rome;</hi> the former will reflect upon his Name, the latter injurious to his Piety; but a glorious death will deliver from the Infamy of both.</p>
                  <p>I will follow you (O my Souldiers!) and with you will I die, and (what pleaſes me moſt) I will dye in the Battel. Neither will I periſh by every obvious and feeble hand. I will break my way through the thickeſt ranks, and through the midſt of mine Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies weapons will I ſmite <hi>Hannibal.</hi> And (my dear Fellow-Souldiers!) I will appeaſe your Ghoſts, either with the Victors gore, or elſe ſacrifice mine own, and ſo, ſhall I eſcape Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumelies, and Reproaches, and ſhall waſh away mine Ignominy with mine own Blood.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="declamation">
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:53205:19"/>
                  <head>DECLAM. VII. <hi>Whether</hi> Tullus Hoſtilius <hi>did well, who firſt taught the</hi> Romans <hi>the Art of War?</hi> Aff.</head>
                  <p>I Am perſwaded you marvel that I being in a Gown, ſhould take upon me the defence of Arms: But I do not perſonate the Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, but act the Orator; and why ſuch won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering at my undertaking? Seeing I am only about to defend that, which both protects me and the Republick too. 'Twas War that lay'd the Foundation of the Commonwealth, and 'twas War that raiſed it to ſuch a pitch of Glory. In vain the Warlick God of <hi>Rome</hi> had in ſtoln Embraces begat <hi>Romulus:</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs the Youth by traduction had his Fathers Spirit. In vain had <hi>Numa</hi> taught them fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Rites, and holy Cercmonies, unleſs <hi>Hoſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius</hi> by his Arms had protected his Religion and ſacred worſhip of the Immortal Deities. <hi>Jupiter</hi> himſelf is of no eſteem without his thunder, and diſarmed <hi>Apollo</hi> appears ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous.</p>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:53205:19"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Rome</hi> the Miſtres of the whole world, meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly flouriſh't by the help of <hi>Mars;</hi> and hath raiſed eternal Monuments and Trophies of Valour; whereas other Nations have lived inglorioſly without Arms. Not the leaſt ſpark of <hi>Roman</hi> Proweſs had appeared, if <hi>Hoſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius</hi> had not inſtituted Martial Diſcipline. 'Tis true, War doth ſometimes rage amongſt harmleſs People, and thoſe muſt needs be ſubdued, who cannot with Arms aſſert their Right. You would not have your Country the Scene of War, but how can you expect a Freedom from the ſame, when every mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the State wages an inteſtine War againſt it ſelf? I mean the mutual conflicts of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agreeing Paſſions; and (if we believe Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy) we had not liv'd unleſs ſprung from the Quarrels of the jarring Elements, neither can we die unleſs diſſolved by the Diſcord of our firſt Principles.</p>
                  <p>Is Martial Diſcipline ingrateful to your ears? And muſt this Art worthy of Eternity, be utterly aboliſh't, without which, <hi>Domitian</hi> could not ſo much as kill a Fly? Perhaps you dread a Warlike Death? as if Souldiers ſo well acquainted with it, did not know how beſt to ſuffer it, as if they did not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand what themſelvers were, who behold Death daily triumphing over dead bodies; ſo
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:53205:20"/>that we may ſay (what ſome of Philoſphy) that the Military Art is the Meditation of Death <hi>Hoſtilius</hi> did not inſtitute it by Mans Advice, but by the Counſel of the Gods. For there was in the world ſuch ſoftneſs of Spirit and effeminacy of Mind, that the Art of War was given from above to prevent the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generacy of the Maſculine Sex. <hi>Jupiter</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf had had a Squob upon the earth as well as <hi>Vulcan,</hi> unleſs <hi>Mars</hi> and <hi>Victoria</hi> had come to aſſiſt him againſt the Giants. And do you not yet eſteem <hi>Gradivus</hi> for a Deity? Is his a fictitious God-head, when Emperours his Adorers are eſteemed Deities? Do you thus requite him? If this be the caſe? Away (ye Philoſophers!) with your Heroical Vertue! Away with thy ſacred Buckler (O <hi>Rome!</hi>) dropt from above as a proof of its Divinity! Away with the feigned Gods of the Poets! and with <hi>Jupiter</hi> himſelf! Let Heaven fall!</p>
                  <p>But I fear, leſt, if I am too tedious, the Tribune will inflict upon me a Military Mulct. I have ſounded a Retract: And if you think I have not defended <hi>Hoſtilius</hi> well enough (like an Orator) with my Tongue, I am ready to fight for him (like a Souldier) with my Sword.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="declamation">
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:53205:20"/>
                  <head>DECLAM. VIII. <hi>Whether</hi> Horatius <hi>is guilty of Death, who killed his Siſter for weeping at the ſight of the Spoils he took from her</hi> Paramour? Aff.</head>
                  <p>CEaſe to wonder that I dare appear againſt and accuſe <hi>Horatius,</hi> whom the <hi>Romans</hi> have acquitted; and unworthily Crowned with triumphant Laurel! Behold! the man beſmeared with his Brothers blood, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not content with one Impiety, he goes on to propogate unexpiable crimes. Thou wretched Villain! Whither did thy Fury hurry thee, thus to revenge the tears of thy Siſter dropt at the herſe of her deceas'd Sweet-heart, thus, not to ſuffer her to enjoy her Lover nor to lament him neither? It had been more becoming thy ſelf a <hi>Roman,</hi> to grieve that he happen'd to be an Enemy, and that 'twas thy misfortune to ſhed his Blood, and that thy reſpect to thy Country had ſo ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed thy Kindneſs to thy Family and Siſter. Love and Mildneſs are natural to Women;
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:53205:21"/>and therefore not to be removed with Sword and Violence. Thou waſt content not with the Victory obtained over the <hi>Curiatii,</hi> but thou venteſt thy rage upon Female Innocence, and levels thy Malice at thine own Siſter.</p>
                  <p>O Horrid Wickedneſs! worthy the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of future ages. For who but this <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratius</hi> (like a fierce Lyon from his prey) would have returned from the ſlaughter of his murdered Brother, and not yet glutted with Blood, would ſheath his Sword in a womans Bowels? What have ye done (O <hi>Romans!</hi>) in acquitting a perſon both guilty of Parra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide, and Ingratitude too? How can you en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure that ſuch a miſcreant ſhould live within the Conſines of your Empire? Thou (O im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious <hi>Rome!</hi>) who haſt filled the World with War and Ruine, and contemneſt the Deities with reproachful threats; Thou (I ſay) at length art juſtly puniſh't, and deſervedly ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers the thunder of the Gods, and the Frowns of Heaven. Thy Foundation was lay'd in gore, and thy Deeds are Bloody, and thy Off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring Vitious and debaucht. Why doſt thou glory in ſuch lewd Actions? And why doſt thou not puniſh this Murderer amongſt the moſt flagitious Malefactors? If we ſhould ranſack the Corners of the whole world, we ſhall never find an Example, that can paralel
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:53205:21"/>the Ingratitude, and the ſavage Barbarity of cruel <hi>Horatius;</hi> who offering his vanquiſht Enemies, to his Angry, and injured Country, hath committed an heinous Fact, and hath fully'd his name with perpetual Infamy, in ſpilling the Blood of his Siſter for a ſacrifice to his Fury. <hi>Nero</hi> and <hi>Caligula</hi> thoſe mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous Parricides of that age deſerve not ſo much the names of Apes, and Vipers, as he to be branded with Eternal Ingratitude.</p>
                  <p>If (according to the ſaying of that noble <hi>Roman</hi>) it is more honourable to ſave one Citizen from death than to ſlay a thouſand Enemies, of what horrid Villany then is he guilty, who after a ſignal Victory hath inhu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manly deſtroyed a poor woman, and toolt away the Life of one, for whom he had done well, if he had reſign'd his own? What if full of Fury, he came laden with the Spoils of his conquer'd Enemy? What if his Sword was ſtill dy'd with the tincture of their Blood, yet the Inhumanity and Brutiſhneſs of the Action deſerv's no mercy? Should he travel the Univerſe, he would ſcarcely find a Patron of his wickedneſs.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="declamation">
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:53205:22"/>
                  <head>DECLAM. IX. Horatius <hi>vindicated.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>I Wonder with what face ye <hi>Romans</hi> dare condemn <hi>Horatius,</hi> who reſcu'd even now from Fire and Sword not only your Republick but your Lives too, who hath ſnatcht them from the jaws of death, and ſafely preſerved them. Ingrateful <hi>Rome!</hi> How he hath deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved ſo ill at thine hands, as thou ſhouldſt thus deſtroy him? 'Tis a bloody Crime to kill him, to whom thou art more obliged than to thy Father <hi>Romulus;</hi> For he only drew the bare model of the City, but the other ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured it when Populous with Inhabitants, when crowded with People, and ſurely 'tis better not to be, than to be a Slave.</p>
                  <p>But why is he come to this? what fault is there in him, beſides his Indulgence (if that be a Crime) to his dear Siſter? who was the only cauſe, that ſhe ſhould enjoy, being dead in the ſhades below, that Sweet-heart, whom ſhe could not obtain alive on Earth above. But if he did it out of meer Revenge,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:53205:22"/>then this is as commendable as the former Action, and there is more of Glory, more of <hi>Horatius</hi> in this, than there is in that; For his noble Spirit ſcorned that a <hi>Roman</hi> Lady, and his Kinſwoman too, ſhould with impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per tears, and unſeaſonable grief ſo ſervilely lament the death of his Enemy. He would not have the very Sex to want its Praiſe; and ſo great was his Zeal and Affection to his Country, as that he would not ſpare his offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Siſter. But if none of all her Vertues, and Deſerts can wipe off the guilt, or make an Atonement for this Crime; yet pardon (I beſeech you) her for her Fathers ſake<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Pity and behold him with much Clemency; he will ſcarce ſurvive after this great Diſgrace, and thus you'l kill two Noble <hi>Romans</hi> with one blow.</p>
                  <p>But conſider I pray. His provocation to the Fact extenuates the Guilt: For ſeeing your ſelves, your Fortunes, and all that you have you owe to his Valour, that unhappy Woman by her impertinent grief, ſeems to prefer the ſafety of the Enemy, before her Fathers, or her Countries welfare; and appears to be troubled at nothing elſe, but that the Third did not periſh with the two other Brothers. <hi>Rome</hi> may ſhortly want another preſerver, for the <hi>Albanes</hi> are a free People, never under
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:53205:23"/>Subjection, and therefore 'tis doubtful, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they'l keep their League, and endure your Government, utterly diſregarding their own Liberty: And then <hi>Horatius</hi> may be as uſeful, as he was before; and that Army which ſent back their Legions untouch't, and triumphant to <hi>Rome,</hi> may again moſt wonderfully defend you, and ſtrike a terrour into all your Enemies: For without doubt where ever is this other Genius of our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth there will be the Fates of the <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bans.</hi> For our valiant Captain hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed their Forces with his own hand.</p>
                  <p>But now if a Fathers Prayers and a Fathers Tears, if a Victory purchaſed by himſelf alone; If Innocence and the Danger of an enſuing War cannot waſh off, and Expiate this Crime; Go on then with your raſh Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment! Puniſh with death this execellent Citizen! Condemn (if you pleaſe) ſtout <hi>Horatius;</hi> but conſider withall your Strength is weakned, your Sinews are cut, and that <hi>Rome</hi> will fall with it's brave Captaine.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="declamation">
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:53205:23"/>
                  <head>DECLAM. X. Zopyrus <hi>cunningly commanded his body to be torn, and wounded, that he might betray, by the Stratagem, the City of</hi> Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilon <hi>to King</hi> Darius.</head>
                  <head type="sub">
                     <hi>For</hi> Zopyrus.</head>
                  <p>THough it may ſeem unjuſt to lay down our Lives for the publick good, becauſe repugnant to Nature, and inconſiſtent with the Cowardice of timerous men; yet there is nothing certainly more noble and glorious, than after the Vertuous courſe of an honeſt Life to reſign our breath, and all for the Safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of our King, and Country. Now this <hi>Zopyrus</hi> that ſo injur'd his body to betray the City, is as commendable as he, who falls a ſacrifice for the Kindomes glory; For he did not die with Infamy and Diſgrace, but lived not only to the Honour of his Country, but to the Reproach of his Enemies, and to his own credit and reputation. If the welfare
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:53205:24"/>of the Publick had requir'd his Life, he would have laid aſide Mortality, and have put off his body as willingly and as readily, as he had deformed it. And thus <hi>Zopyrus</hi> devotes himſelf to ruine for the ſafety of his Country. And how much better is it to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face the Beauty, to tear the Limbs, and to rage with Cruelty on the parts of his Body, than to melt down his Strength and exhauſt his Spirits by Softneſs and Luxury, and ſo to ruinate the whole Structure.</p>
                  <p>Who more worthy than <hi>Zopyrus?</hi> Who more to be belov'd? who to adorn his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try with Peace and Glory, hath repreſented himſelf an ugly Spectacle. Whoſoever diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praiſes him doth in effect commend the Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous, and Slothful, and hints this as his Diſgrace, that he had profuſely ſpoiled the Sweetneſs of his Aſpect, the Charms of his Face, and waſted prodigally his very Blood for his Country, and ſhews he had rather the Deſolation of the Publick, than the Ruine and Deſtruction of one private Feature. He hath ſurvived long enough, who hath liv'd to the Publick; and his dayes are not to be accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſhort, who is regiſtred in the Monuments of Immortal Fame.</p>
                  <p>'Tis an unworthy Age that preferrs Beauty before Valour, and that is much diſpleaſed
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:53205:24"/>that the Country owes its Defence to Scarrs and Wounds. Behold <hi>Zopyrus</hi> graſping Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry with his own hands! See the demoliſht Walls! the burnt Houſes, and the whole City of <hi>Babylon</hi> lying waſt and raz'd! and thoſe things that were in vain attempted by the Strength of thouſands, are now effected by the Arm and Policy of one Man! Go on brave Captain with thy undaunted Valour! Deſpiſe the reproaches of malevolent tongues! And big with Renown, the Reward of thy Deſerts, be thou a Monument of Valour, and an unimitable Pattern to ſucceeding Ages!</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="declamation">
                  <head>DECLAM. XI. <hi>Againſt</hi> Zopyrus.</head>
                  <p>IF <hi>Zopyrus</hi> had well weighed and conſidered of thoſe exquiſite pains, which he ſo mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerably ſuffered in his tortur'd Body, certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly he would never have exerciſed ſuch Cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty on his innocent Members, and by an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy Stratagem, have wounded his Enemy
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:53205:25"/>through his own Bowels. He had better have killed himſelf outright, than thus to beſmear himſelf infamouſly with Blood, and to inflict upon himſelf thoſe dolorous Torments, which make him weary of his life, and to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vet death.</p>
                  <p>Though he was ſo ſturdy as a little to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure the ſharp pennance of his ſlaſhed limbs, yet he unwillingly ſuffered that ugly Defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, which made him horrible to others, and a wretched Spectacle to his own ſelf. The ſquallid Complexion of his crimſon Face was ſo far from pleaſing, that it terrifi'd <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius;</hi> and if he affrighted the King, for whoſe Glory and Honor he endur'd the Pennance, how much more lothſom was he to others, who may juſtly doubt whether he be a man or Fury? For the loſs of his Lips, Noſe, and Ears make him rather reſemble the Picture of a Monſter, than the Shape of a man; For his cheeks are beſmeared with a ghaſtly die, his eyes are glutted with the Streams of his own Blood; and he that ſhould triumph and boaſt in ſhedding his Enemies, by an unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Error, ſpills, and wallows in his own gore.</p>
                  <p>But now he deſervedly feels the ſmart of thoſe Puniſhments he inflicted upon himſelf; he affects not the ſweetneſs of refreſhing
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:53205:25"/>odours: but is ſad and melancholy amidſt the ſcents and breath of perfumed Roſes; his ears are ſtopt, and hears not the voice of charming Eloquence; his mouth is crammed, and utters no Oratory, but remains ſilent; ſo that eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one doth injure, and affront <hi>Zopyrus,</hi> and vex his ſores with new wounds.</p>
                  <p>Thy Caſe is ſad <hi>Zopyrus!</hi> what is there that can delight thee in the whole world? All men hate thee, and all fear thee: wherefore think thy ſelf ſcorned and odious, and ſee (if thou haſt got any eyes) thy maimed Limbs, and lament the Defects of thy crippled Body: But this is thy only comfort, thy neceſſity (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to thy deſerts) of ſuffering theſe things. But now, if the want of theſe Members make him ſo dreadful a Spectacle in the ſight of others, how frightful and cruel muſt he ſeem to his own ſelf! For who would lick his own Blood? who but a mad man, would with voluntary ſtripes chaſtiſe himſelf? In this he appears more bloody than a Butcher, who, though he ſlays the beaſt, yet ſpares him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; But he after he had wreak'd his Spight, and rage on his Enemies, he executes his Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny upon his own ſelf, and that not ſo much out of a Concern or Affection for the Publick, as to diſcover his Cruelty and Madneſs, for which he is rather to be puniſht
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:53205:26"/>than commended. And what reaſon is there, why he ſhould not ſuffer, unleſs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he cannot endure enough? For his members already have been ſo forely handled, that no cuts, and ſlaſhes, no pungency can be added to his former dolors; unleſs all his Pains be wholly ſwallowed up by the ſting of death; wherefore without doubt, he had never committed ſo heinous a Fact, unleſs encouraged by the hope of a proſperous For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune. But we do not ſee that <hi>Darius</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanc't him; and indeed neither did he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve Promotion; for he might have ſhewed his Zeal and his Courage for his King and his Country many other ways, and thoſe more proper for, or becoming a man. But that which increaſes the Abſurdity of the Action was, he ſtain'd his hands in needleſs Blood, which neither the time nor neceſſity did require of him; for neither thy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try nor thy ſelf <hi>(Zopyrus!)</hi> were in any danger; and <hi>Darius,</hi> without thine aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance, could have either contemn'd <hi>Babylon,</hi> or elſe have conquered it. What if the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty had been overcome? What if thy <hi>Perſia</hi> had been laid waſt? Thou couldſt not have died more miſerably, than thou didſt now; For thou haſt ſo hackt and hew'd thy manlike Face, and ſo baſely ſpoiled thy hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:53205:26"/>Limbs, that I queſtion whether the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my could have mangled thee more. To con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, I prethee <hi>(Zopyrus!)</hi> be ſenſible, by thy loſs, of thy great Folly, and wiſh for (though too late) and prefer thy Safety be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a Victory.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="declamation">
                  <head>DECLAM. XII. Brutus <hi>perceiving that his Sons endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd the Reſtauration of Kings among the</hi> Romans, <hi>drag'd them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Forum, and before the whole Aſſembly caus'd them to be ſcourged with Rods, and afterwards cut off their Heads.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <head type="sub">
                     <hi>For</hi> Brutus.</head>
                  <p>SEeing the firſt Age of <hi>Rome</hi> was ſo miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably ſpent under the cruel Tyranny of ſeven Kings, and becauſe the City in its In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy was ſo oppreſt as to be ready to expire
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:53205:27"/>in its very Cradle, I'le be hang'd, if ever the <hi>Romans</hi> are Lords of the Earth, or if the City be ever Empreſs of the whole World, I dare warrant that the Scepter ſhall never any more be ſway'd by Tyrants, and that extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſht Monarchy ſhall never be reviv'd, ſo as to involve us again in another Bondage. The people of <hi>Rome</hi> have found by Experience that Kings are not only proud by Name, but by Nature too; and that they have infring'd the Liberties, and Priviledges of the Publick; and that though they were valiant, yet they did not ſo much protect by their Courage as deſtroy their Subjects. I cannot relate without Dread and Horror, how often <hi>Tarquin</hi> hath drawn his Sword againſt the City, how often he hath more rag'd in Peace, than in times of Warr, that he might ſee the gaſpings, and diſtorted looks of dying men; that he might hear the ſighs and groans, and the ſad com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints of the miſerable.</p>
                  <p>Whoſoever wiſhes a new Succeſſion to this laſt of Kings, he is worthy to ſuffer all manner of Thraldom, he is ſit to be the firſt Inſtance of his Cruelty; and let him endure a Tyrant in his very Father. If ſuch Princes as theſe are fit to rule, let your old diſtemper return again; if you delight in new Fury, and in a freſh diſeaſe, then let Kings be reſtored
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:53205:27"/>again. But if a Conſular Government ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel a Kingly, which doth not only puniſh the Murderers of the Citizens, but takes care for, and defends the Liberty of the City, then let Monarchy die with <hi>Tarquin;</hi> and let not one Tyrant rule with a milder Government, but let more Nobles conſult and act for the good of the Publick: let them defend the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty as well from Domeſtick Confuſions, as Forreign Invaſions; and ſeeingboth the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuls have Power and Command over one City, and that but a little one, let them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer the Nations over which they preſide; let them make their Enemies and Captives be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come their Citizens, and all the Provinces of <hi>Italy</hi> to become <hi>Roman.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>A ſingle Monarch being hardly enough for one Scepter never by Conqueſt enlarg'd his Dominions, but ſuſpecting the Fidelity of his People, he is wont to rule in Poverty, and Want, by reaſon of his oppreſſion, whereby he uſes to defend his Territories; and he weakens his Subjects to prevent their revenge. Various Slaughters ſuffered not <hi>Rome</hi> to grow to the ſtate of Manhood; nor was it ſafe for the Kings that the <hi>Romans</hi> ſhould wax old, leſt any by their Deſerts ſhould aim at the Kingdom; ſo that Puniſhments and Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments were inflicted to ſuppreſs the growth
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:53205:28"/>of flouriſhing Vertue. Thus the People un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a <hi>Roman</hi> King obeyed a Tyrant: no man lived ſecurely, but whoſoever was ſuſpected, though harmleſs, was condemn'd to death, and whoſoever lamented the Innocent, was puniſht as Guilty.</p>
                  <p>But now the Conſuls emulating each others Vertue, make Laws for themſelves, as well as for the People; and defend with their own the <hi>Roman</hi> Liberty. One can't ſo much oppreſs, but the other is as ready to redreſs their Grievance: neither can they vex the Republick with private Animoſity; but they muſt turn their Fury upon their own ſelves. And thus the haughty Lyon affrights with a noiſe the common Herd, and preys only upon little Flocks, but when he hath in view ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Lion, he is ſtruck dumb, and ſilent; and they both diſdain the neglected Cattle, but both emulous and jealous of each others Honour, and neither brooking the equality of a Rival, do engage mutually, and terrifie no more the deſpiſed droves, but exert their Fury upon, and ſeek to devour their own ſelves.</p>
                  <p>If this Conſular Government pleaſe the Senate, then theſe <hi>Roman</hi> Youths may not by Force ſubvert it without Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. They ſeem to undermine the City,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:53205:28"/>to affect the Kingdom, and to revoke themſelves inſtead of Kings. Theſe Youn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers certainly aſpire too high, who take up arms againſt the Fathers, Conſuls, and eſtabliſhed Laws of <hi>Rome.</hi> Profeſſed Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, that dare do any thing, never ſtrike at the Form of Government. Every Nation may (as it pleaſeth) Diſpoſe of its people and may reſtrain them by what ties it liſteth; and Cities at Emnity do not give Laws to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, nor do they foment civil Broils among their Citizens or embroil their Citizens in ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil wats.</p>
                  <p>Seeing therefore the Government of the Conſuls is either to be eſtabliſht by the death of the Conſpirators, or to be abrogated for the future by a free Remiſſion, the moſt juſt <hi>Brutus</hi> did juſtly condemn his Sons for the Liberties of his Countrey, and for the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges of <hi>Rome;</hi> And that he might not ſurvive a childleſs Parent, he the Aſſertor and Father of the Laws hath tranſlated into his own Family, and hath adopted the Citizens in the room of his Sons.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="declamation">
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:53205:29"/>
                  <head>DECLAM. XIII.</head>
                  <head type="sub">
                     <hi>Againſt</hi> Brutus.</head>
                  <p>AFter the Foundation of the Empire lay'd in Blood, and ſuch a continual ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of horrid Cruelty (as if it was juſt, that as <hi>Rome</hi> in her Infancy conſecrated her future Grandeur by ſo a Barbarous a Crime, ſo ſhe ſhould defend her Safety by repeated Slaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and Patricidial Murders maintaining thereby the limits of her Power) I ſay, after the frequent Violations of the Laws of Nature, and the exile and baniſhment of proſcribed Humanity, or Preſcription of exiled and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carded Humanity; 'Tis no wonder that <hi>Brutus</hi> ſhould exert his rage on his own fleſh, and more Cruel than <hi>Indians</hi> (who only de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour their dead Friends) ſhould wreak his Fury upon his own Bowells. He ſlays his own ſons, thoſe dear Pledges of himſelf, becauſe he would not favour the private ties of Affinity: But let him ſatisfie his Fury ſo ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagely, and that he may be a ſafe-guard to <hi>Rome,</hi> let him be fierce and inhumane.</p>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:53205:29"/>
                  <p>Ceaſe (ye <hi>Romans</hi>) by the help of the Gods to reduce and ſubdue forreign Nations, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Rome</hi> by her ſhedding blood, and by her flagitious Crimes, hath given a ſpecimen of her future Impiety; and <hi>Brutus</hi> the Aſſertor, and Patron of <hi>Rome,</hi> having left his Enemies, proſecutes with Hatred his own Sons, and triumphing at home in a bloody Victory, is become a Conquerour within his own houſe. Let not the Deities hope any more for their wonted Flames, nor for the ſolemn Pomp of former Victims, ſeeing <hi>Brutus</hi> ſpared not his very Houſhold Gods; whilſt he equally for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gets both his Piety, and his Sons; by the death of his off-ſpring he ſhews himſelf to be but a cruel Parent, by whoſe blood he hath purchaſed an ill gotten Liberty— After ſuch great Specimens of an ambitious Spirit, and Crimes ſucceſsfully committed againſt the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publick, he now attempts a greater wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and that ſuch an one, which cannot be expiated by any Sacrifice. For having got the Empire, and by the death of the Kings, having obtained his deſire, he does now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging to wanton in Cruelty, and being backt with Power, doth more violently rage. His Sons, that reſiſt his growing Tyranny, he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutes with a cruel affection and ſtrikes them through with darts of Love, and (like a
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:53205:30"/>ſwelling deluge checkt by violence) he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vades them preſently with a double force, and lets them fall as victims, for the defence, and ſafeguard of the new Empire.</p>
                  <p>Moſt unhappy Young Men! whoſe Valour alone hath made them miſerable! who have done nothing worthy of death, unleſs it be Capital, to reſiſt the unjuſt Pride of their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and to defend <hi>Rome</hi> from the Treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of <hi>Brutus.</hi> Things are come now to that paſs, that there is need both of the Pious and Valiant to reſtore the Republick; For what could they do elſe? if they had not of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended againſt <hi>Brutus,</hi> they had ſinned (which had been worſe) againſt the Gods and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey too. A crime is to be choſen, about which they did not long deliberate. The vai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner name of a Father could not affright them, nor the reverence of a Parent deter them; For let him be no longer a Father of Children, if he will be no more a Parent of his Countrey. The Young Men had a natural Veneration for Majeſty, and therefore reſpect and honor the Kings, and defend their Prerogatives to their laſt breath.</p>
                  <p>The City was ſo oppreſs'd with Cruelty, and ſo bloody with the ſlaughter of murdered Citizens, that the Gods themſelves could hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly releive it without expoſing themſelves to
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:53205:30"/>death and danger. But <hi>Brutus</hi> haſtens to his Sons with the greateſt Zeal, and at once doth uſe both Prayers and Threats, he ſooths them up with winning Inſinuations, he accoſts them with language as ſoft as deceitful. He ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects unto them the Honour, Glory, and Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lurements of Empire, the great Pleaſure, and Priviledge of Governing: But our Young Men oppoſe, and embrace not this wheedling Courtſhip, whoſe Fidelity is not to be ſhaken, either by Price or Pleaſure, no not by death it ſelf, and therefore the cruel Father advances himſelf to the higheſt pitch of Fury and Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety, and by the diſmal Tragedy of his Sons, ſacrifices to the Liberty of his Country; that thoſe whom he could not provoke by his Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition and Tyranny, he might at leaſt over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come by Death and Envy: Thus whilſt he hath beheaded his Sons, and endeavors to ſpill his own blood, he doth not only loſe the Reputation of being Humane, but buries his name in ſilence and oblivion. He deprives himſelf of the comfort of Poſterity, and of that Immortality which is for ever propaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by a dear off-ſpring.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="declamation">
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:53205:31"/>
                  <head>DECLAM. XIV. <hi>When a certain City was daily haraſs'd by continual War, the Citizens at length decreed among themſelves to demoliſh the golden Statue of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, to coin money for their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, and maintenance.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <head type="sub">For the Citizens.</head>
                  <p>IF you know not the greatneſs of Imperial Majeſty, and how much to be defended by the Lives and Eſtates of Loyal Subjects; I ſay, if you do not any otherwiſe underſtand it, yet from hence you may learn, namely, that the Glory of the whole Empire depends upon the Safety of the Emperour, and as of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten as War ſhall require, Subjects (like Bulls to <hi>Jove</hi>) muſt fall victims to their Prince: Then certainly tis no ſuch great matter to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend a little Gold (otherwiſe unprofitable unleſs in War) for the Honor of the King, for the defence of the City, Palace, nay of
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:53205:31"/>Majeſtie too. Nothing could be thought on more noble and more redounding to the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the Emperour, or give a greater Proof of a Deitie, than that Golden Statue pull'd down and demoliſht in the defence of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. If the Imperial Image could ſo protect the weak Citizens, and (by I know not what Charm) ſhews that it can effect ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what that is Auguſt and Magnificent, if the Royal Eſſigies could aſſright Enemies, could ſtretch out its Fatall Arms, and kill thoſe with the Cruelty of a Look, whom it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not wound with its extended hands, I ſay, if the meer Figure could do this, what ſhall we think then of the real perſon, whoſe Statue could drive away his approaching Enemies? Let it therefore be domoliſht, and by its fall, let it prove that there is nothing belongs to an Emperour, but what is Divine.</p>
                  <p>We read that the Statue of <hi>Scipio</hi> did pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect the <hi>Italians</hi> from the <hi>Carthaginians;</hi> and that his Reliques and Aſhes were as uſeful to <hi>Rome,</hi> as the living General. We know that an Enchantreſs can wound a man meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by waxen Images; and at once can hurt the Original and the Copy too; can ſtrike the Image, and hit by Sympathy the Man too; ſo that, tis not ſo great a matter for the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial Statue to effect theſe things, ſeeing
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:53205:32"/>waxen Puppets have ſomething of Life in them, and become Arbiters of Life and Death. Behold the miſery of the poor City! Contemplate the ſad Looks, hollow Cheeks, the paleneſs of the Inhabitants at the thoughts, either of preſent Danger, or fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful expectation of future Death! Both the Subjects and the Statue are all like to periſh, and like to be involv'd in the ſame ruine. But is it not beſt to preſerve them to ſecure the Citizens, the walls of the Emperour, and laſtly, to protect the Emperour himſelf, and all by the deſtruction of one Statue? For 'tis eaſie after a Conqueſt, to erect, and raiſe new Images, and new Statues, and thoſe greater; and with the Relicks of this gold, after Fights and Overthrows, to make an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Image and conſecrate it to <hi>Caeſar.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Let the golden Statue and the ſacred Image be quite defac'd, that it may be reſtored and raiſed more Auguſt and Divine: we do not envy the Emperour that piece of Divinity, as to be abſent, unarmed, inviſible, and yet by this Art to be preſent at his Battels, to ſtir up the feeble Citizens, whereby he ſhews him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf not ſo much to be an Emperour, as a God.</p>
                  <p>Though 'tis an heinous crime to violate any thing, that (for their noble exploits) is
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:53205:32"/>conſecrated and devoted to the memory of our Anceſtors, yet ſeeing neither the Peace of Countries can be enjoyed without Arms, nor Arms be procured without Pay, it may not ſeem a wonder, if we endeavour by our honeſt Ingenuity, to free our ſelves from for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Invaſion, and reſtore our ſelves to our fotmer Liberty, and ancient Glory. Inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuous Spirits are aſhamed to be put under, and to ſubmit their neeks to the Tyranny of a Yoke, and to become Tributaries to thoſe whom we have freed from ruine and the jaws of Death; therefore we thought it good, rewards adding Courage to Souldiers to ſcrape off the gold from the Imperial Statues, and to coin it into money, and that not to defend our ſelves only, but the Gods too: For we were reduced to that extremity, that unleſs we had laid out our money and care for the Safety of the Countrey, we had certainly periſhed and been deſtroyed by them; The Temples had been rob'd of their Gods, and the Deities been depriv'd of their Temples too; they had condemn'd us to hard and miſerable Bondage, and that which went neareſt to us, they would have ſhackled our Hands with unwonted chains. But by this our Trick, we have prevented our Enemies from ſacking <hi>Rome,</hi> and have triumpht over
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:53205:33"/>thoſe who would have conquered us, and that which makes us more Noble and Happy, we have not flincht from our firſt Enterpriſe, but have ſtoutly reſiſted their fierce On-ſets, and have ſubdued our cruel Enemies, and that with our Ancient, and truly <hi>Roman</hi> Valour; and have put their necks impatient of Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage under our yoke, and (the Gods favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring our Cauſe) we have wholly routed them, and reduc'd them.</p>
                  <p>Behold our Enemies enrag'd with grief, do liment and howl at their miſerable Fate! and curſe our Valour, and good Fortune too! Behold on the contrary us walking in State and Pomp! we are received with pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick acclamations, and the Gods have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratulated our freſh Victory, and thank us, for preſerving them untoucht and ſafe! with what Solemnity will our Triumph be cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated in <hi>Pompey's</hi> Theater? with what joy and ſhoutings are Trophies erected in Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of our Victory? with what care is the Gold and Silver reſtored to their reſpective Statues? and the People of <hi>Rome</hi> are ſo far from derogating from, or eclipſing their Splendor, that they take care to preſerve them and to adorn and gild them with grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Curioſity.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Rome</hi> being ſecure from and having loſt its
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:53205:33"/>Rivals, and the Gods being free from all Fear, let us not withdraw from Tumults, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take our ſelves to eaſe and quiet! Let the City enjoy her former Beauty, and Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificence; and let the <hi>Roman</hi> People diſplay their wonted Glory! Let the Souldiers boaſt of their wounds and ſcars, and let them eſteem them their moſt honourable Badges, and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments of their Bodies.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="15" type="declamation">
                  <head>DECLAM XV. <hi>Againſt the Citizens.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>REligion is preſerved inviolable among all Nations, and there is no Villany ſo extreme, no Impiety ſo cruel, as to allow of, and favour horrid Sacriledge. A very Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my himſelf (though never ſo much incens'd) would ſcarce ſuffer the ſacred Temples, and the Monuments of our Anceſtors to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaned and ſpoiled. But (ye <hi>Romans!</hi>) ye have laid aſide all Conſcience and Religion in ſo baſely demoliſhing the Repreſentative of the Emperour, which you ought to have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:53205:34"/>with all your Strength, and with as great care as the Prince himſelf. Beſides there was no need of committing ſo great a Crime, for the Deſolations of War threatning Poverty, and the grim Aſpect of approaching Death, ought to have animated them and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed their Courage in the Defence of their Liberty and Country, and of their own ſafety, and of their Princes too.</p>
                  <p>O moſt earthly and ſordid Souls! who breaking the Laws, and contemning and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſing both Gods and Men, have thus villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouſly prophaned moſt ſacred Majeſty (little leſs to be adored than a Deity it ſelf) ſo that the Gods are unſafe, and <hi>Jove</hi> juſtly fears, leſt you vile Miſcreants (like <hi>Dyoniſius</hi> the Tyrant) ſhould preſume to pull his golden Beard. If you could no otherwiſe have defeated your Enemies Army, you had bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter have embrac'd an honeſt Death, than to endure a Life ſo ſcandalous, and ſtain'd with ſo horrid a Crime; it had been better to have been oppreſt with Poverty and Bondage, than ſo ignominiouſly to live; and to purchaſe your Liberty at the price of your Innocency. What ſacrifice can atone for this fact? Ye have (O ye <hi>Romans!)</hi> by throwing down the Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Emperour, made an attempt on his ſacred Perſon, and ſo are guilty of High-Treaſon.</p>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:53205:34"/>
                  <p>We do too much indulge the Parricides in ſuffering them to be openly and publickly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended, whom the Gods would have puniſhe and ſlain too; For the appeaſing of whoſe Anger the whole Religion of the City can ſcarce ſuffice: Becauſe if we rightly conſider their Loſſes, we ſhall find ſomewhat which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides War, and a Siege, we ought to deplore; ſomewhat that is ſad and Tragical, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not at all be aſcribed to an Enemy; For behold here are Citizens, who have added this im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious Cruelty to all our miſeries, that we ſeem meerly to be ſupported by the Benefit of our Sacriledge, and midſt the Terrours and Hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips of War and Hunger, to dare to abuſe the Emperour, <hi>i. e.</hi> to prophane, violate, and contemn the Gods themſelves. If an Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my had done this we had hop'd for a Victime, and would have made them by their Fall to have expiated and aton'd for their Guilt. But now with what Hope? with the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance of what Deity can we take up Arms? for we have loſt our Courage, becauſe our In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocence, and (which is more) our Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour too. Our Enemies rejoice, and begin their Triumph from our Crimes. The wicked Citizens boaſt as if they had defeated Hunger and their Enemies by their horrid Sacriledge; and indeed ſo they have; for the Heinouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:53205:35"/>of the Fact had ſcar'd them with i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Horrour, and put them to Flight, unleſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> its Blackneſs had recalled them and move<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> them to Revenge, and ſo made them wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> a double Fury fall upon the Sacrilegious and exert their Rage upon them. If de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair ſhould make us Conquer, yet we ſhould bluſh to enter the City, and be aſhamed to viſit thoſe ſacred Temples, whoſe Holineſs, we have polluted with our unhallowed hands.</p>
                  <p>Behold how theſe Pious Inhabitants have preſerved their unhappy City! They have go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> their ſuſtenance by Sacriledge, by which we are fed for ſacrifice, though a whole City is not Victim enough for ſuch a Guilt, where the Gods, the Emperour, nay our Enemies are to be aton'd, and ſatisfied. We do not complain of trivial matters; nor are we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with a ſingle Grief; but we lament the Condition of the whole City, which theſe Villanous Parricides have diſtracted, waſted, and ſpoiled in the Emperour: For after they had defiled themſelves with this black Crime, they propagated the Contagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Vulgar, that every one might bear the proper Guilt of his own Sacriledge: It grieves us to think how with a ravenous mouth we devoured the diſmal Gates, and
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:53205:35"/>how greedily we ſwallowed even the horrid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mpiety. We ow to the Citizens that we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ive, that we can courageouſly behold the hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of the Fact, and ſo great an Inſtance of Cruelty. You thank them for reſtoring your decay'd Strength, for arming you with your Emperour, and making that a Prey to the Enemy, which they themſelves ador'd whilſt in the Temple. They have ſpoiled the tute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Deity, more venerable than Hunger; they have ſpoil'd the Emperour, more Auguſt than the Image. They have ſpoil'd that, which ſtanding, we might have liv'd innocently, even in the ruine of the City. If a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querour had entred, we might have been ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure; For the ſacred Majeſty of ſuch a Statue would either have extorted Religion from them, or if they have none, 'twill teach them ſome. But our Grief hath overcome our Hopes, and we have defil'd our miſeries, and (which is the laſt that belongs to the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable) we have loſt Pity.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="16" type="declamation">
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:53205:36"/>
                  <head>DECLAM. XVI. Manlius Torquatus <hi>to maintain the Diſcipline of his Camp, killed his own Son.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <head type="sub">
                     <hi>For</hi> Manlius.</head>
                  <p>I Am not Ignorant with what Prejudice I ſtand here before you in the behalf of <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius;</hi> For I fear that theſe ſad, and harſh Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands will be very ungrateful to your tender ears, which yet are wholſome for my Son, who either by Fate, or through Shame of declining Battel, was driven into the body of his thickeſt Enemies, and (as it happen'd) prov'd Victor: But he, whom no Law or Edict either of Father or Conſul could keep from raſhly breaking his rank and order, is to be reſtrained by the Sword. Let not Martial Diſcipline be corrupted by one ill Example leſt the whole Army ſuffer through Default of one.</p>
                  <p>Our <hi>Manlius</hi> aim'd at ſomething to be done, more Auguſt and Glorious than the ſoft Effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minacies
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:53205:36"/>of fond Parents; His Paſſion was more ſtrong and ſevere than to defend and patronize his Bowels, his Off-ſpring in ſo great a Wickedneſs. 'Tis Inhuman and horrid to hate his Iſſue, but yet to ſpare ſuch a Son is worſe than Hatred: the Law and Republick can't be ſo ſatisfied; Let the Son ſuffer for his raſhneſs, rather than the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth rue for the wicked Indulgence of his Father. What People did ever more religiouſly preſerve Martial Diſcipline than the <hi>Romans?</hi> To whom warfare was far more ancient than Parents or Children; whoſe well order'd Troops have advanc't them from nothing to the Dominion of the whole world; neither can the <hi>Roman</hi> Glory be Eclipſed, nor the wide Empire of the Victorious, Shrink or Decay, unleſs this ſtrong tye, or Union of diſtant Colonies be diſſolv'd by Effeminacy, Luſt or Luxury; whilſt with a well diſciplin'd Army (like a well fortified City) they did repel the On-ſet of their invading Enemies, they always returned with Triumphant Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gles; But whilſt the Son of <hi>Manlius,</hi> breaking his ranks, obtains the Victory, he departs only not conquered.</p>
                  <p>You have here (moſt equal Judges) <hi>Manlius</hi> acting the part, not ſo much of a ſtout and valiant General, as of a ſolicitous, and careful
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:53205:37"/>Parent, nor more commendable for his Juſtice than his ſingular Clemency, who even conſulted the good of the Republick though 'twas to his own damage. He thought it far better to be the Lord of the Country, than to be called the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of ſo ſtubborn a Son; neither did he ſtudy only the good of his Country, but of himſelf too; and whilſt he puniſht his Son with death for declining the Commands of his Father, he preferr'd an honeſt Reputation before an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famous Off-ſpring; and ſeeing he could not beget an Heir equal to his Parent, he would have none ſurvive that is unlike ſo great a Captain.</p>
                  <p>But <hi>Torquatus</hi> lives ſtill, and as long as Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Diſcipline, and Laws of Camps do flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, <hi>Manlius</hi> the Patron of Arms will ſurvive and never fall or decline, but with the very Standards: ſeeing he ſmote with the Ax his only Son, he hath vindicated his name from devouring obſcurity. Thus he hath prolonged his Life by dying, and ſurviving himſelf, hath 'een by mortality made himſelf Immortal; And ſo aged Valour withſtanding the Teeth of Time and Rottenneſs, hath tranſmitted him to Poſterity without an Heir.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="17" type="declamation">
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:53205:37"/>
                  <head>DECLAM. XVII. <hi>Whether it is lawful to uſe</hi> Perſian <hi>Pomp in the midſt of War?</hi> Aff.</head>
                  <p>VVHy ſhould I doubt, I know no reaſon but that only ſeems unlawful (<hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian</hi>-like) to grow rich. We adore a Penu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and a hard Fortune, and lament the loſs of a golden Age, not ſo much becauſe we are Vicious, as becauſe we are Beggars; yea our minds are ſo impoveriſht (neceſſity cauſes ſuch a degeneracy) that we cannot conceive the Splendor of the <hi>Perſian</hi> Equipage. It becomes the Lords of the Earth thus richly to fight; That Magniſicence is honeſt, and thoſe Ornaments glorious, which are only the rewards of Sweat and Valour. <hi>Perſicus</hi> deſcrib'd with his Sword the whole Univerſe, and commenc'd <hi>Geographer</hi> by his own Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries; he underſtood <hi>Bactria</hi> from a Cloak, and the <hi>Sogdiani</hi> from an Helmet; his Steed hath been laden with Spoils of ſeveral Nations, and why then ſhould he not proudly prance, who hath dar'd to fight for his Harneſs, and Trap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pings,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:53205:38"/>and who will level the Mountains, and lay flat with the ground his Enemies too, that he might vex his creſt with their weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Jewels?</p>
                  <p>That Pomp doth juſtly excuſe Pride, and is neither vain, nor ridiculous, which is the reward of ancient Valour, and is a ſpur to new. Thoſe who are afraid of Ghoſts and Goblins, who can't undauntedly contemn the Fates, nor dare provoke death: Let them combate in ſquallid weeds, and mournful dreſs: But thoſe that are of an approv'd Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, and who draw Fortune after them bound in chains, to whom tis the ſame to war and triumph, why is it not lawful for them to breath perfumes, to ſhine with Oils and Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomes, and to enjoy the Teſtivity of a crown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed brow, and to uſe in War all the Pompous Luxury that attends a Victory?</p>
                  <p>Let the rude vulgar contemn that which is noble and gallant, as if Robes of Kings and Triumphal Garments muſt declare the Mind to be Proud and Soft: we have often ſeen Vertue (I know not by what unhappineſs) half clad in tattered weeds, and ſcarcely co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd without a Figure: But as if vile rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment were a Vertue it ſelf, it will be a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach to the deſerving to be richly attir'd; neither is he thought worthy of Praiſe, who
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:53205:38"/>dies for his Countrey, if he ſacrifice himſelf with well ordered Hair, and if by chance an importunate Hero ſhould with a trim aſpect put to flight his Enemies, the auſtere Laws would condemn him as though ſtill drunk with Victory. When <hi>Rome</hi> was reduc't to ſo great extremity as wholly to deſpair of its ſinking Empire, when the Sinews of War began to crack, and the Strength of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publick began to languiſh, and <hi>Roman</hi> Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour could atchieve no more, the Senators did not take Sanctuary in Forts and Garriſons, nor did fly to Arms, but adorn'd themſelves with their Robes and Purple; whoſe Senato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian Pomp repreſenting the Sages as ſo many Gods, did ſtrike ſuch a reverence into the amazed Enemy, that ceaſing to reſiſt, and aw'd with the Religion of the ſolemn Specta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle they began to fear, retreat, and worſhip. What need we care? If adverſe Fortune be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fals us, we ſhall die in the ſame gallantry, wherein we fought, and to the Angry Deities fall crown'd ſacrifices: But if our ſucceſs be proſperous, that will give credit and reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and recommend the Honeſty, Vertue of our Magnificence, and will vindicate the lawfulneſs of our cenſured Glory.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="18" type="declamation">
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:53205:39"/>
                  <head>DECLAM. XVIII. <hi>Whether</hi> Philoſtratus <hi>did well, who, to make Death Familiar, lived in a Tomb ſeven years?</hi>
                  </head>
                  <head type="sub">
                     <hi>Againſt</hi> Philoſtratus.</head>
                  <p>WHen I contemplate nothing but the noi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome ruines of dead Men, and am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſant only amongſt Vaults and Sepulchers, I ſeem already ſentenced, and adjudged to death, having no other company in my ſqua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid ſolitute, but the Society of Monuments and learned Marbles. I am encompaſſed on every ſide with gaping Tombs, but they are not vocal; for amongſt the Hiſtories and Epitaphs of famous Heroes, you will find a ſilence as deep, as the diſmal Cell wherein they are cloiſtered. Here you may ſee the Urn of a Commander adorned with Poetry, and Lawrel too; but as ſpeechleſs as the heaps of his Enemies over which he tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphed; There you may read inſcriptions
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:53205:39"/>as durable as the ſtone on which they are writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, and which are ſacred to the memory of a voluble Orator, whoſe mouth now is fuller of duſt, than tis of Eloquence; and he that even now was begirt with a ring of living Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirers, now ſtands ſurrounded with the dumb Attendance of breathleſs Images.</p>
                  <p>It is reported that the Statue of <hi>Memnon,</hi> ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted by the raies of the riſing Sun, became vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, as if the dead Image was Ambitious to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim the approach of ſo great a Deity, and as if that Muſical God that found out Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, had been the Author, and Inventor of ſounds too. But we need not the Influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of a propitious Heaven, here you may behold a Monument never ſaluted or ſeen by the Sun, and within it a Philoſopher (like a certain Oracle) uttering ſpeeches darker than the Cavern wherein he lies: For our <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſtratus</hi> inhabits at once both his Study and Sepulcher too: He reads melancholy volumes that treat of death, and meditates of certain I know not what trivial notions, and invokes the Fiend with as fervent Zeal, as the war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Poet his beloved Muſe. But oh! <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſtratus!</hi> we have heard ſome times that the Muſes can inſpire, but never knew before that death could dictate. Away with thoſe ſolemn thoughts about your latter end! Fly
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:53205:40"/>ſwifter than Fate from the Putrid rumes of filthy Carcaſes, and keep thy ſelf as ſafe from theſe as thou wouldſt from Death! For within the narrow confinement of this ſordid Cave, there is nothing lives, beſides thee and worms: The Air is infected with Stench and Rottenneſs, and the place is infeſted with nought but Horror; with the defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Shapes of Ghoſts and Goblins.</p>
                  <p>'Tis true, we read of the Veſtal Virgins, that being once deflowr'd they were interred alive, and were condemned to the perpetual darkneſs of a diſmal Den; and ſo extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſht at once both the Flame of their Life and Lamp too. But if thou <hi>(Philoſtratus!)</hi> lieſt hid any longer in the Cloiſters of thy Tomb, we will ſuppoſe thee as criminal as the Guilty Nuns, and think the Auſterity of thy Life to be not ſo much thy choice, as thy Pennance. What Pleaſure lies hid in the obſcurity of a charnel Houſe? Wanton Lovers affect the night, that they may act in darkneſs; But behold! all things are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit for laſcivious Embraces, all as cold as the Marble under which they lie; no kiſſes to be gathered, but from mouldred Lips, or from the Fragments that are left by glutted Worms.</p>
                  <p>Behold thy Companions in thy gloomy
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:53205:40"/>Cave! Here are the Legs, and Armes; the Ribs and Thighs of thy ſcattered Anceſtors, as void of Life as they are of Fleſh; There lies a Head, which rob'd of its Beauty and Brains too, is a lively Image of that death thou adoreſt; behold the ſockets of their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſht eyes! See the ruines of a nibled noſe, as if devouring <hi>Venus</hi> had been preying up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the dead, as well as the riots, and feaſts on the living.</p>
                  <p>What heinous crime haſt thou committed, that thou alone thouldſt live amidſt the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of rotten Carcaſes; and inflict upon thy ſelf that Puniſhment, which the greateſt Tyrants do on their worſt Enemies <hi>i. e.</hi> join thy ſelf alive to dead Bodies? But thou (O <hi>Nero!</hi>) in the mean time deſerveſt Prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, as great as the Univerſe, which thou ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt, who after a cowardly and ingrateful Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volt of thy Souldiers, and their Reproaches, more intolerable than their Crime, didſt deny to go quick into the Earth, and waſt content to reſt under a little ſpot, who hadſt the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of the whole globe: It becomes thee who haſt ſubdued the world under thy Feet, to die ſtanding, and thou, who didſt contemn in thy looks and language the Bowels of thy dear <hi>Agrippina,</hi> wouldſt eaſily deſpiſe the viler Entrails of thy common Mother.</p>
                  <pb n="72" facs="tcp:53205:41"/>
                  <p>'Tis the Part of a Valiant, and Heroick Spirit, even againſt Fate it ſelf, to level at thoſe, who ſit triumphantly, out of the reach of darts, in the Victorious Chariot, and to fear no more deaths blunter darts, than the keener ſteel of their Enemies. Vain are the Terrours of that petulant Fate, which in this only differs from a ſmooth Chameleon, that the latter is ſupported by the Attraction of Air, the former by the ſurreption of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers breath: There is no reaſon therefore, <hi>(Philoſtratus!)</hi> to ſpend ſeven years in a Tomb, the better to overcome a momentary death. The Deſtinies are Siſters, and weak in Sex, and infirm too; and their Inſtruments are ſofter, than the wool they ſpin; what! does a Diſtaff, a Thread, and Sciſſars affright thee? Theſe are the Toies, not of Men, but Women; and are as harmleſs, as the ſoft ſmooth Fingers, by which they are managed, Phiſitians tell us, that decayed Nature is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired again in the ſpace of ſeven years, and that men are oftner clad with new Fleſh, than new Garments; which if it be true, we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve thou livedſt <hi>(Philoſtratus!)</hi> not that thou mightſt die, but that thou mightſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trieve thy Youth, and that the whole bulk of thy Body (like the Hairs and Nails of other men) might be revived, and flouriſh with
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:53205:41"/>new Life. But beware, leſt whilſt thou lurk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt in this gloomy ſhade, the Fates ſhould think thee already dead, and ſo ſhouldſt loſe the expected approach of the deſired Deſtinies, becauſe already buried.</p>
                  <p>Seeing therefore, Thou haſt ſuch an earneſt deſire to know death, leave this dormitory, and betake thy ſelf to <hi>Mars</hi>'s Field; and there thou maiſt ſee the Souldiers brandiſhing a Sword and Death in the ſame hand, which as ſwift as arrows, peirces the breaſt of ſtout Champions, and purpled with gore, Victoriouſly triumphs over proſtrate Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives! Think and meditate on divine <hi>Bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> who with a careleſs Gallantry diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with Spectres, as with his familiar Friends. But if theſe Martial Camps, more dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful with Horrour, than Throngs of Men, do not pleaſe thee; F! to the mournful, yet laſcivious tents of <hi>Venus,</hi> and there behold Virgins (like Baſilisks) kill with the artil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lery of their Looks, ſhooting from their eyes glances keener than the ſhafts of their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; For a deep furrow of a contracted Brow ſtrikes a greater Terrour than thy Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulcher, and one tirannical Averſion of a diſdainful Eye, ſcatters Darkneſs as blind as the God of Love. There you may hear fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs groans equalling the Torments of a neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:53205:42"/>Paſſion; and ſuch bluſtering ſighs, as if they would blow out thoſe Flames, which they ſo violently fan; There you may ſee tears flow from a diſconſolate Lover in ſuch a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luge, as if they would extinguiſh thoſe fires, which firſt cauſed them. Behold the Heart and Entrails ſo ſcrocht and burnt, that you would think their Breaſts not ſo much the Fence or Guard, as the Urn of their Bowels.</p>
                  <p>In theſe places, that Fate, which thou ſo deſireſt, thou maiſt with the ſame labour both ſeek, and enjoy, and (like buried Lamps) maiſt find in the open air that death, which thou couldſt not obtain in thy cloſer grave. This we think <hi>(Philoſtratus!)</hi> to be a Prodigy greater than thy Life, that whereas the names of others do ſtill ſurvive becauſe they are in Tombs, thine lives becauſe thou waſt a Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher; and that Immortality, which others acquire by courting Fame, thou haſt puchas't by deſiring death.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="19" type="declamation">
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:53205:42"/>
                  <head>DECLAM. XIX. <hi>Whether</hi> Cimon <hi>did well, who for the more ſumptuous Interment of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſold both his Liberty and Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf too.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>'TWas wiſely ordained by our Anceſtors, that as men, whilſt alive, ſhould be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured with the Tribute of obſervance and reſpect, ſo when dead, ſhould be attended with the Ceremonies of a decent Funeral. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly a very commendable, and a moſt hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Cuſtom, whereby Men excel other Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mals, who know no other Rites of Burial, than the Solemnity of being devour'd by other Beaſts, and who have no other Tombs, than the living Sepulchers of their Fellow Creatures. But Humane Nature abhors the Brutiſhneſs of ſuch Obſequies; for a ſavage Conquerour ſeeing the field beſtrewed with arms and ſcattered limbs, bedews his garland and ſheds tears at the thoughts of his bloody Victory, and indulges his Enemies the civil pomp of an handſome Interment. Death
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:53205:43"/>puts a period to the moſt barbarous Cruelty, which never raves beyond the Fatal Stroke. <hi>Caeſar</hi> wept at the Herſe and pitied the Fate of ſlain <hi>Pompey,</hi> whom when alive he perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted with the greateſt Fury, and with all the Methods and Arts of Ruine.</p>
                  <p>How unhumane is that Countrey, which ſuffers even Strangers to lie unburied! How much more therefore ought we to Honour with a Sepulcher a Citizen a Kinſman! But how great an impiety to leave a Parent expos'd to the open air! He is unworthy of his own life, that celebrates not with coſt his Fathers death: Can a Son be exceſſive in kindneſs ſo to his Parent? for whom not only his Wealth and Liberty, but let him expend his very Life too. He can give nothing to him, but what he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived from him. Is he only obliged to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence his Parents, whilſt alive? Muſt he contemn and ſpurn at them, when dead? whom Death among the Antients did ſeem to conſecrate, and whoſe Monuments were had in great Veneration. This our Heir therefore, whoſe Breaſt was inflamed with a Pious Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor towards his Father, will not have him lie without a Sepulcher, and ſcorns that he ſhould have no other Grave but a Priſon, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore for the Magnificence of his Funeral, he ſells his Liberty and himſelf too.</p>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:53205:43"/>
                  <p>We have here a rare Example of unuſual Piety, and of a Filial Care! <hi>Cimon</hi> ſhew'd himſelf a loving Son to his Father, when alive, and a Pious one, when he was dead. He impoſed voluntarily on himſelf the Yoke of Slavery, that his Father might have a Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and loſt his Freedome, that he might enjoy the Priviledge of the dead: He thought with himſelf, if his Father ſhould want a Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulcher, his name would quickly find one, and the Glory thereof be ſoon buried in Oblivion. Degenerous Poſterity would loſe the Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of ſo exellent Vertue, unleſs his Memory was committed to the faithful Cuſtody of Eternal Marble, upon which his noble Exploits being engraven, would give duration to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and to his Tomb too. He conſulted both his own Fame and the Honour of his Father, who adorn'd his Herſe with ſuch Solemnity. What renown hath he purchaſed, who by his own Liberty hath ſet free his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned Father, and that he ſhould not want a guilded Tomb, He himſelf was the price of the noble Sepulcher.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="20" type="declamation">
                  <pb n="78" facs="tcp:53205:44"/>
                  <head>DECLAM. XX. Cardan <hi>a Philoſopher, and an Astrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, having foretold the day of his Death, to fulfil his Prediction, and to ſave his credit, he starved himſelf with Hunger.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>UNhappy <hi>Cardan!</hi> whoſe Reputation is either hazarded, or his Life expoſed to Danger! The greatneſs of thy Spirit cannot brook the want of the one, nor humane Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture endure the loſs of the other. But oh the Vanity of that Name, which Wickedneſs and Impiety do alone perpetuate, and whoſe everlaſting Memory derives its Immortality from a death attended with ſo much Infamy! But pardon me moſt learned Aſhes, and moſt unhappy Relicks! We dare not ſummon ſo great a Ghoſt, nor accuſe the deceaſed of ſuch a Crime. Thou haſt obeyed the Imperious Motions of the Heavens, and the cruel ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of the harder Fates. <hi>Cardan's</hi> Art is greater than <hi>Cardan;</hi> and cannot be eluded
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:53205:44"/>by the Endeavours of Miſterious Philoſophy. But what? He that can maſter his Affections and nearer charms, which ſcorch't and cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivated other Mortals, doth he now yield to the diſtant, and ſtragling Stars? Thoſe Stars (I ſay) which, (unleſs antiquity be deceiv'd) are much inferior to our Humane Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and are compell'd by it? How much more happily by the Flight of Birds, or En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trails of Beaſts, might he have foretold the Event of things, and the hidden Treacheries and ſecret Stratagems of his Enemies!</p>
                  <p>There are ſome things the Gods envy the knowledge of to Mankind, and would have them chaſtly buried, and to lie hid in their firſt cauſes; leaſt they ſhould be prophaned and violated by too bold a reſearch; ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing it to be the greateſt piece of Learning to underſtand the revolution of Times and Feſtivals, wherein it may appeaſe the diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Deities, and humbly offer Incenſe to the Coeleſtial Empire. How much prying Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals have been puniſh't, and chaſtized for their too much Curioſity, the waters made infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous by a premature and unexpected Fate, and <hi>Veſuvius</hi> celebrated for the Death of <hi>Pliny,</hi> do abundantly declare. But if it be a fault to dive and ſearch into the firſt Principles and Motions of things; If it be criminal to fly
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:53205:45"/>to the utmoſt Sphears, and to know more than vulgar Capacities, why was man endowed with reaſon? why doth that Particle of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Air animate a Being, that moulders and languiſheth with Sloth, and Negligence, but that it climbs up to the Stars, and viſits the ſeat of its firſt Original? Why is the Face of Nature not always the ſame, but various, ſometimes famous for the clearneſs of its ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, and ſometimes venerable for its miſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious workings? Why is it thus? but that it may exerciſe the activity of the vigilant Soul, and that there may be more matter for its con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation? She is not ſatisfied (like the Body) with the delicacies of a treatment, nor with all the Luxury of the Fruitful Seas, or Teeming Earth. She delights not (like that) in ſuch narrow Confinements, who feels not the bounds of an embracing Ocean, but rowes about into unknown tracts with a boundleſs Freedom. How doth ſhe ſoar aloft, big with ſcorn of this Inferiour World? Not wearied with the difficulties of its crag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged ways, how doth it imitate the inceſſant motion of the firſt Heaven?</p>
                  <p>Moſt cruel Toil! we reach the Heavens with our Folly; and neglecting thoſe things, which are the only ſupport of the more ſolid Felicity of our Lives, we are diſtracted with
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:53205:45"/>the Images and Shadows of vainer Phan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſms. To theſe we pay our more frequent devotions, and to theſe we offer our daily Homage, till tir'd at length with the ungrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Journey, like the waves, a long time toſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with tedious Storms, we are wearied and languiſh, and are quite ſpent into Peace and Calmneſs. We are more affected with the narrow precincts of a little Village, more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted with illiterate Eaſe, and a private Retirement, than with our former pale En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours, and with our traverſing the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe, when with a ſacrilegious and bold In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry we wandered further than <hi>Hercules</hi> Pillars, and went beyond the bounds as well of Modeſty, as Nature.</p>
                  <p>From no other Fountain flowed our <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dans</hi> premature death, haſtened, to wit, by pertinacious Induſtry, and an indefatigable Soul; which although Fatal to its Maſter, yet grateful Poſterity will never mention without the higheſt Encomiums; and though far from Superſtition, it raiſe no Altars to his Merits, yet will enroll him amongſt Heroes, and advance him to the higheſt pitch of Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals Ambition. Let others reproach his ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Fate, and abrupt Funeral, <hi>Cardan</hi> dies through no other, but his own wickedneſs; and in vain had he deſir'd in the Inhumane
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:53205:46"/>
                     <hi>Gete,</hi> or <hi>Venetian</hi> aſſaſſine, a more cruel mind to aſcertain his Prediction; neither could he have found one more kindly cruel, as to free the Philoſopher from infamous ſui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide; and Poſterity would not have pardon'd the Crime, if committed by any other hand beſide his own, which though it did moſt unhappily obey his Maſter in his Death, yet hath made amends for the Injury by his lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Pen.</p>
                  <p>But oh! the various Fluctuations of the Soul! This miſerable man knows not what rock to cling to; at the ſame moment, he doth both at once determine, and yet doubt to die. This Procraſtination of his Deſtiny, argues a timerouſneſs not becoming <hi>Cardan,</hi> and he had died more gloriouſly ſtab'd with a Sword, than ſtarv'd by Famine. But this may be ſaid in Favour of the Deceaſed, that he yielded up the Ghoſt with an undaunted Courage; and whilſt others oppreſſed with Penury, and grinding Neceſſity, breath out a faint and languid Spirit, he neglects his ſuſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and yields to Fate. He underwent not the Deſtiny of <hi>Petrius,</hi> and Renowned <hi>Cato,</hi> who enjoyed the Felicity of a ſudden End, but ſatisfied the cruel Command of his Governour, whilſt he determined to periſh gently by little and little, and not ſurrendring
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:53205:46"/>to the Fates, but after a long ſiege, he truly perceives himſelf to die—And leaſt he ſhould be unhappy in his Death, Let him enjoy for me a ſilent Urn and peaceable Aſhes! Let the Stars be propitious, whoſe influence he aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted even with his Life and Blood! Nor let the Arts be ſilent of him, who was their great Patron and Protector.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="21" type="declamation">
                  <head>DECLAM. XXI. Alexander, <hi>being ſaluted the Son of</hi> Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter Hammon, <hi>and thereupon arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gating to Himſelf Divine Worſhip, is accuſed of Pride by his Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <head type="sub">He defends himſelf.</head>
                  <p>SEeing I have expoſed my ſelf (O ye <hi>Macedonians!</hi>) to ſo many dangers in your behalf, ſeeing I have preſerved you ſafe from the Injuries and Violence both of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:53205:47"/>and Enemies, at <hi>Granicum, Cilicia</hi> and <hi>Arbela,</hi> ſeeing I have ſtoutly maintain'd the Honour and Glory of the renowned <hi>Mace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons,</hi> and have added, by my Victories, the ſubdu'd world to your Empire; I had thought, after ſuch Divine Teſtimonies of my Courage you would have ſubſcribed to mine Opinion, and would have affectionately embrac'd me like ſome ſacred Buckler, that had dropt from Heaven. But to Crown me with Divine Honours, I perceive, is not agreeable to your Cuſtoms; you therefore belch out your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches againſt me, devote me to the ſhades, though every one of my Atchievements ſpeak me not ſo much a Man as a God; A Deity (I ſay) in regard I never had a repulſe, nay Fortune her ſelf, though obſtinate, durſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver contradict me.</p>
                  <p>How often have I, undaunted, rendered my ſelf obnoxious to certain Perils? and with an Invincible Courage, have (in ſpite of the Fates) reſtor'd the tottering, chance of War? That I have triumph't over that ſickle God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſs, that I have trampled under feet the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venous Deſtinies, and that I am the only Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch of the Univerſe, the Gods and you do well enough underſtand; that <hi>Jupiter Hammon</hi> hath rewarded my Deſerts with Immortality, and acknowledged me his Son, you ſufficiently
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:53205:47"/>know, and tis needleſs to tell you; why do you not therefore, with bended knees, adore as a Deity my Divine Majeſty? why do you not believe <hi>Hammon,</hi> whoſe credit to this very day remains inviolable? Do Oracles utter Lies? Do you think me unworthy of the Society of the Gods? What? have not my conquering Arms advanc't me above the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary pitch of Mankind? Have they not made me equal to <hi>Hercules</hi> and <hi>Bacchus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Obſerve, (O ye ungrateful <hi>Macedonians!</hi>) Is it nothing that I have trodden ſo much ſnow, that I have paſſed over ſo many impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Rivers, and travell'd over ſo many fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen mountains, which (if you believe Fame) have daunted <hi>Hercules,</hi> who had not Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage enough to attempt them? I forbear to mention Victories and Triumphs; I ſpeak not of ſubdued Kingdoms and Empires, which were not ſo much as known by him, much leſs ſubverted by his proweſs. I have raz'd <hi>Thebes</hi> without War or Blood, and my very Name hath ſtruck ſuch a Terrour into <hi>Greece,</hi> that it offered me a golden Crown of Victory, and hath choſen me her Captain. My ſtupen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dous Glory will not be confin'd within the narrow limits of the <hi>Macedonian</hi> Kingdom, but revolving in my mind the whole Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe, to make way for my future greatneſs, I
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:53205:48"/>have landed a few men in <hi>Aſia,</hi> and at <hi>Grani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus</hi> have quell'd my moſt dreadful Enemy with a great ſlaughter; have reduc't <hi>Lidia, Ionia,</hi> and <hi>Phrygia,</hi> and made them ſubmit to my Power.</p>
                  <p>Finally, having overcome and broken through all oppoſition, I came to <hi>Iſſus,</hi> where with repeated Victories, I diſcomfited <hi>Darius</hi> the Potent King of <hi>Perſia</hi> with his numerous Army. Afterward it came into my mind, or I recounted how many ſlain I ſent in one day to the ſhades below, inſomuch that <hi>Charon</hi> confeſſed that his own boat was not ſufficient, but that there was need of a whole navy of Ships for Tranſportation. And to omit my atchievements at <hi>Tyre,</hi> and <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bela,</hi> and an infinite more in other places, I arrived a Conqueror at the <hi>Indian</hi> Ocean, and made that a bound both at once to my conqueſts and the whole world; and put to ſlight their wounded Elephants, and made King <hi>Parus</hi> my miſerable Captive. Paſſing the River <hi>Tanais,</hi> I have deſtroyed the fierce <hi>Seythians</hi> with a great ſlaughter: and the rock <hi>Aornon,</hi> whoſe craggy difficulty forc'd <hi>Hercules</hi> from a ſiege, I alone have attempted, have climb'd it and conquered, and have rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed my Trophies and Eternal monuments be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the bounds of Father <hi>Bacchus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:53205:48"/>
                  <p>Finally, returning from <hi>Memphis,</hi> the whole world being at Peace, I made mine addreſſe according to the Cuſtom of my Country to the Oracle of <hi>Jupiter Hamon,</hi> where I was joyfully received, and with the gratulations of the whole company of Prieſts; nay, <hi>Jove</hi> himſelf, the Father both of Men and Gods, deſcended from his ſtud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Throne of Emrald, and ſaluted me as I approach't him; and after much comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment exchanged on both ſides, He adopted me to be his Son, and commanded you to adore your King, and to worſhip him with Divine Honours.</p>
                  <p>But you neither hearken to his Commands, nor will believe that I am enrolled among the Gods. And your Envy doth daily more increaſe againſt me, becauſe I hate not <hi>Jove,</hi> by whoſe Oracle I am pronounced a God. Are the anſwers of the Deities in my Power? He profered me the Name of a Son. I wiſh you would believe me a God, that ſo you might atone and appeaſe the diſpleaſed Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and reward your King with Immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and Glory; by whoſe warlike Proweſs triumphant <hi>Greece</hi> hath been raiſed to the higheſt pitch of Felicity — But though now you think it much to bow your Heads to my Deity, yet I fancy when I ſhall be tranſlated
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:53205:49"/>to Heaven you will not deny me Divine Honor, and as ſoon as you perceive your baſe Ingratitude, whom now you hate, being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent with you, you will lament and grieve for, when I am ſnatch't from you, and will perform due Honour, and Reverence to my Ghoſt and Aſhes.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="22" type="declamation">
                  <head>DECLAM XXII. — <hi>For Fear of Death, 'Tis madneſs to reſign our Breath.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>He is neither Patient nor Valiant, who amidſt the Tumult and Fury of War, cares not to die by the Sword of his Enemy, but covets to fall by his own Hand, he is to himſelf an Enemy, and to his Enemy a Friend; he is kind to them, and to himſelf a Tyrant. If when proſperous ſucceſs, ſhall crown our Endeavours, Life is ſo much eſteem'd midſt the pomp of Victory, that there is ſcarce mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for our Triumph, or time to admire, or adore our ſelves; Methinks 'tis ſtrange, after one frown of Adverſe Fortune, one blow of
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:53205:49"/>an incenſed Enemy, ſo to be weary of our Breath, as not only to avoid and ſhun our Adverſary, but to run from our lives as a more cruel Enemy.</p>
                  <p>By doing thus, we both aſtoniſh Nature and Heaven too; who are not only Rebels to our ſelves, but ingrateful to it, and are Uſurpers too. For if we take away our lives with thoſe darts, which Nature has given for the defence of them, we make her to act in vain, and violate the ſacred Inſtitutions, and Laws of the Deſtinies. 'Tis not Glory, nor Valour; Honour nor Proweſs to yield to ſo eaſie a Death, and whilſt we ſpill our Blood againſt the Deities not enough propitious, we ſeek to revenge our ſelves of Heaven, and not of our Enemy. This Villany, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficious Fame will tranſmit to Poſterity. Such a crime argues Degeneracy of Spirit; and 'tis not Valour but Fear overcomes us; ſo that our Bodies can hardly endure ſavage Tiranny, becauſe our Souls are weak and ſtupid. Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Valour muſt be as hard as Adamant, and have a Breaſt an Anvil to all miſeries, which (like the invincible Palm-tree) muſt trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phantly riſe againſt all Preſſures.</p>
                  <p>Far be it that our Enemy ſhould glory in our overthrow without a wound or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict! Far be it that his Sword (like the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilisk)
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:53205:50"/>ſhould ſhoot forth Death on a mee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Spectator! Nothing can be deſired worſe than Death: but now if Death be a reward, we muſt break our way through our Enemies Breaſts, and becauſe there is not room for Flight on Earth, we will purſue our Foe (as <hi>Brutus</hi> the Adulterer) to the Shades be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low. But perhaps he is not ſo furious as to be a Tormentor rather than a Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: But if nothing can quench his thirſt, but a draught of Blood, we muſt imitate the Example of the <hi>Roman</hi> Senate, not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire Death, or fear it. When our Enemies ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach, having adorn'd our ſelves with Pomp and Splendor, let us expire in ſtate: And if we can ſuffer the Fatal ſtroke with an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunted Spirit, let us not for ſhame be afraid of Enemy or Bondage, as if more cruel than Death. Let us not free our ſelves from priſon by our own wounds, we will not pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe ſo inglorious a Refuge at ſuch a rate; nor ſo obſcurely deſcend to the Ghoſts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low; we will rather wholly be involv'd in chains. A Souldier ſhall load our Ambitious hands with ſuch Bracelets. 'Tis no diſgrace for ſuch great Bodies to be lead Captive. We are of more worth than to become a trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant Feaſt for the Furies. We will not ſubmit our ſelves to a Martial, but bow our necks
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:53205:50"/>to a Marriage yoke, deſiring to lie impriſon'd in more noble Embraces. We bluſh not (being ſubdued) to be carried Appendages to the proud Chariot. We will not imitate <hi>Demoſthenes,</hi> or <hi>Varus:</hi> Far be it from us to follow ſuch degenerous Commanders. But thou <hi>Claeſia!</hi> the wonder and glory of <hi>Rome:</hi> ſhalt be our pattern, we will croſs (like thee) not only over <hi>Acheron,</hi> but our Country Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. For amidſt ſtorms and tempeſtuous Troubles, Valour breaks forth with a brigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Luſtre; ſo that if Heaven, Earth, and Air, ſhould conſpire againſt us, we will ſtand unaffrighted at ſuch great ruine. Such Proweſs if it cannot invite, yet ſhall ſcare our Enemies into Kindneſs and Clemency. If they will not commiſerate our ſad con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, let them be more ſparing of their brandiſh't weapons, But if they are aſham'd to put them into a dry Scabbard, and have a mind to lodge their Artillery in the qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of our pierced Breaſts, let us fly enrag'd to the Infernal Lake, that not only our Foes, but Furies themſelves may be ſtruck with Fear and Conſternation. What Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal Glory will accrue by this? we are as Famous in our Death, as Valiant in our Life. And although we are dead, yet perpetual Trophies ſhall preſerve us alive;
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:53205:51"/>and though no one will lament and bemoan our ſo unhappy Fate, yet Poſterity will pay everlaſting Homage and Eternal Veneration to our Tomb and Sepulcher.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="23" type="declamation">
                  <head>DECLAM. XXIII. 'Tis better to travel abroad, than to tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry at home.</head>
                  <p>I Bluſh to ſee ſuch a ring of Philoſophers, and ſo many pale Students always plod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and poring upon their Books. We ought ſurely to engage our ſelves in a more profitable Employ, and not to be confin'd in a narrower Study, than the whole World. He is truly a Scholar, who is vers'd in the Volumn of the Univerſe, as who doth not ſo much read of Nature, as contemplate, and ſtudy Nature her ſelf. Thoſe are but low and mean Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, who breath at home, and cling ſo faſt to their Native Soil. The Diviner Soul, mindful of its Extraction, and Birth above, imitates Heaven, and delights in motion. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:53205:51"/>the Stars, how they wheel about with unwearied Courſes! How doth the Sea fluctuate with a reſtleſs wave? and (un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs <hi>Copernicus</hi> had a whimſy) the Earth turns round, and is troubled with a Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigo.</p>
                  <p>And do we not yet travel? Behold the Aſpect of every thing invites you abroad! eſpecially that verdant <hi>Tempe,</hi> and the em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broidered <hi>Eliſium</hi> of the new-born Spring! And who is he, unleſs condemn'd to the ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle in chimny corner, that will not run to the joyful Nativity of the Infant-year, and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie his ſenſes with the blooming Blandiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the pleaſant Fields? What diſgrace doth attend the Houſhold Deities? But if you take a voiage from home, here you are ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the proud height of <hi>Alpes</hi> and <hi>Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramids,</hi> there you meet with the prodigious Fabrick of a burly <hi>Coloſſe;</hi> on this ſide a Landskip adorn'd with Cities, on that a Proſpect ſhaded with Groves; one very ſide ſurrounded with new worlds, and encompaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with the Luxury of divers objects; ſo that your divided Senſes turn doubtful Sceptricks, being diſtracted with the variety of freſh Spectacles, and regiſter the remembrance of their paſt Pleaſure. From whence proceed your Famous Wits? From whence ariſes
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:53205:52"/>Dignity, and Honour? Who was ever emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent or advanc't from ſmoke? or who was ever made immortal by a Domeſtick <hi>Jove?</hi> with whom, whoſoever through Sloth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſes and dwells, the Glory of his Fame will daily fade, his Sanguine Cheerfulneſs will be Phlegin and Dulneſs, his brisker Heats will cool and die, his Vigor Faint, his Life is Death, and his Name buried in ſilence and oblivion.</p>
                  <p>How many have there been (as experience tells us) who have come into the world dull, and ſtupid, and condemn'd by Nature to the prophane Rabble, whom an ingenious ſearch into Forreign Parts (<hi>Prometheus</hi>-like) hath animated and enlivened with new Fires, and hath (as it were) made and framed them of new mould, hath refined them into Stars, and made them glorious Luminaries to diſpel the darkneſs of the cloudy Age? Again, how many are there of quicker parts, who though coaeval with <hi>Neſtor</hi> within their private walls, yet have at length expired Fools and Ideots.</p>
                  <p>And what? Do we not travel yet? Why are we enlightned with two eyes? Why are we fork't, and branch't into two legs? what did Nature mean to diſtinguiſh man into ſo many Senſes, and almoſt crown'd him with
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:53205:52"/>Immortality? Why did ſhe fix the mountains, pour out the Sea? Why did ſhe embelliſh and beſpangle the world with ſuch Star-like Spectacles? 'Tis ſtrange! What was her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent? Far be it, that we ſhould thus defraud our Nature and Genius, that ſuch Divinity ſhould lurk and be concealed in a Chimny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corner, and ſhould die, and expire in a cloud of Smoke! Every thing in the world is an Emblem of Travel: For what elſe are the Motions of the Stars, the Flights of Clouds, the Career of the Sun, and the Courſe of the Moon, the Fall of Waters, the gliding of Rivers, the Frisking of Beaſts and Swim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of Fiſhes, in woods and ſtreams; I ſay, what elſe are all theſe, but repreſentations of travel, and a waifaring Life? But to come a litter cloſer: ſeeing theſe kind Invitations do but little move you, we will ſlatter you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to travel with more winning inſinuations, and ſhall give you a Proſpect of that pleaſing Variety, of thoſe raviſhing Delights, which feed the Curioſity of an inquiſitive Traveller; and they are ſuch, which captivate the wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring Senſes with ſuch powerful charms, that whom they cannot perſwade, by a gentle violence, they will draw abroad.</p>
                  <p>Here (believe me) are to be ſeen ſuch allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring objects, which will even tire the multitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinous
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:53205:53"/>ſight, and the viſive faculty of all-eyed <hi>Argus;</hi> which once being veiwed, make us ready to wiſh to be perpetual Spectators with an alternate eye. There are odors which feed you with their breath: here dainties, which you cannot ſo much as look on with idle Lips, on every ſide do occur ſuch potent delights, ſuch prevalent entertainments, that a Sceptick cannot queſtion their command they have over us.</p>
                  <p>But now ſuch is the unhappy condition of home-bred Clowns, that nothing is the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of their Senſes, but what is ordinary and familiar; They ſee nothing ſtrange and rare; what they do to day, that they do to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, and every day; and what they ſee now, doth accur alwayes; Let us not therefore, as if unlawful to exceed the bounds of our Native Soil, end our days on the ſame ſpot, whereon we began them, and ſo expect death under the ſame Climat, wherein we received our life. What matter is it what ground we tread? what Air we breath in, or in what Region we behold the Sun. That publick Exchequer of Light doth ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his Treaſure to all alike; it every where glides the ſame Heaven; we are in all places refreſh't by the ſame Air, and whereſoever our Souls are ſolicited and treated by new
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:53205:53"/>Spectacles, they can only diſcover divers Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuations, but not another Earth: Let us not therefore, as if born and condemned to one corner of the Globe, breath our laſt, within the ſame walls we received our firſt; for he that lies hid at home does not live but is bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried in his houſe, whoſe cloſet is his Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, upon which you may inſcribe this Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taph, <hi>(hic ſitus eſt)</hi> here he is laid. But (thou moſt noble Youth!) whom Arts have inſpired with a freer Genius, who art as wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to traverſe the world as well with thy feet, as to rove about it in thy active mind; Fly! Begon! thou canſt not be ſafer in thine own houſe! Fancy the Univerſe to be thy <hi>Lycaeum,</hi> and the ſeveral Regions the Authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick manuſcripts of the old ſtagyrite, all which having run over, thou wilt at length become a true ſtagyrite. Viſit the amphibious Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces of the <hi>Dutch</hi> Otters, thoſe Citizens of the Sea, who are leſs acquainted with their own, than with other Nations, and who have a Countrey where they have no Land. Or if thou hadſt rather, go ſee and conſult the <hi>Britains</hi> ſeperated and divorced from the whole world, whom you will find encom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs'd with the embraces of the Sea, which is not ſo much their Priſon as Defence, who are not its Captives, but Lords over it; For
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:53205:54"/>there is no tract of the Earth untrodden by the <hi>Britain,</hi> no creek of the Ocean, but he has ſailed in it. There is nothing diſtant or hard to him; there is nothing, but what he hath either overcome or ſeen; hath meaſur'd by his travels, <hi>France,</hi> and <hi>Italy; Spain</hi> and <hi>Germany; Aſia</hi> and <hi>Africa,</hi> and hath taken a journey to unknown Parts. Some have ſo curiouſly pried into the Northern Regions, as that they have left the Sun and Light behind them, and have followed ſo far the directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and conduct of the Polar-Star, till 'twas no longer their Guide, but a Companion in their Progreſs. Others not leſs ſcorch't with heat, than theſe were benumb'd with cold, have advanc't ſo far into Southern Climates, as to have ſeen the chambers of the riſing Sun, and view'd the cradle of the Infant-morn; where kinder <hi>Phaebus</hi> ſheds not his raies on the Heavens only, but munificently gildes the Earth too, in whoſe boſome you may find mountains of gold without a fiction, and ſuch heaps of jewels, which are only vile through their great Plenty. Let us not therefore alwayes devote our ſelves to the idle Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, nor dote on the Sophiſms of knot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Sciences; Let us not, cloyſtered in our Studies, perpetually be enſlav'd to the Libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Arts; ſeeing the utmoſt pitch of our En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:53205:54"/>and Sweat are ſubtle Niceties, emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Notions, ſolemn Trifles, and learned No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>things. Let us no longer ſo curiouſly ſearch after their abſtracted ſubtleties, nor hunt any more after their fugitive inventions; But lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aſide all laborious contemplations, let us meaſure in our progreſs the dimenſions of the globe! let us reach its bounds, and wander as far as the remoteſt <hi>Antipodes!</hi> let our eyes rove with their wanton glances, let our noſes imbibe the fragrant breath of refreſhing odours; and let us treat our palats with the magnificent Feſtivity of rich <hi>Viands!</hi> let the whole troop or brigade of our Senſes travel; and we being ſurrounded with a guard of their pleaſures, here let us view the ſweet perfumes of <hi>Tmolus,</hi> there go ſee the ſcents of <hi>Theſſalian</hi> Fields! Now let us go viſit the golden ſtrand of yellow <hi>Tagus,</hi> and the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious ſtreams of rich <hi>Pactolus;</hi> anon enjoy the raviſhing Felicities of happy <hi>Arabia,</hi> and the delicious Prodigalities of the luxurious <hi>Indies!</hi> nay, have at the wanton Treaſures of the whole Univerſe, which if I ſhould at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt to deſcribe to you in bare words, 'twould be as great a Soleciſm, as to make an Oration to your eyes, or to declaim and harangue to your noſes; I ſhall therefore wave the travel of our Senſes, and ſhall omit that fertil preg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancy
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:53205:55"/>ſo big with Delights, which are wont to raviſh thoſe noble Centinels of our Souls, I mean our Senſes, whenſoever they travel.</p>
                  <p>And what do you ſay now? do theſe things ſpeak but coldly? we will urge the matter home, and preſs it further. Go too! prepare your ſelves, and behold the dangers of a domeſtick Education.</p>
                  <p>What do men do within their private Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitations? they ſit ſtill; Oh ſad! How often do we ſee thoſe home-bred Ruſticks buried in Sloth, and wallowing in Intemperance! How frequently drown'd in a deluge of Liquors, who overwhelmed in <hi>Lethe,</hi> do breath out their immoderate Souls in a mortal dream! whereas the lively and moving Spirits, do by their Sobriety obtain of the Deſtinies a lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger thred, who indulging their Senſes a pleaſant variety of grateful objects, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come eminent and conſpicuous, famous and illuſtrious, and (to ſpeak more gloriouſly) mortal Deities, famous and conſpicuous? why ſuch you may find amongſt the Houſe-hold Gods; For they have their wonders and ſpectacles worthy your ſight; For what elſe are thoſe luxurious ſpend-Thrifts, who make themſelves old, even before their youth, who waſt their Patrimony in unlawful loves, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes quarelling for new Miſſes; who in
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:53205:55"/>their Minority are ripe for Hell, and provoke and invite unwilling death before their time.</p>
                  <p>Let us rejoice, and triumph! let us elevate our Spirits! Forſake the chimny-corner, aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don Sloth! let us riſe, walk, and be travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling! Our will commands us; Pleaſure deſires us; our hands and feet importune us; at home dangers affright us, abroad ſpectacles invite us. Rejoice, and triumph!</p>
                  <p>Hath nature chain'd us to one clod? Hath it condemn'd us to one corner? ſhall we lead our lives within the narrow precincts of a few miles? ſhall we grow old in the confines of one cottage? where we lived, ſhall we there die? I bear about me but ſix ounces of duſt, which I owe to our common mother (for the Chymiſtry of <hi>Cardan</hi> found no more in the aſhes of a calcin'd body) and what matter is it, where my Tabernacle is diſſolved, and where I pay ſo ſmall a debt? at home through Luxu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and delights we grow effeminate, and are melted and diſſolved through domeſtick ſoft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
                  <p>Let us away then to the frozen pool; and let us admire orbicular ſurrounding amphi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theatrical ſhadowes of the remote <hi>Amphiſcii!</hi> The acute Mathematicians meaſure the Earth with grains, and weigh it with ounces; they will tell you the number of the duſt of the
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:53205:56"/>Earth, and compute the quantity of the drops of the Sea: the vaſtneſs of the former, and the wideneſs of the latter they will contract and crowd into the narrow compaſs of little maps; where the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Empire is compri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed in a blot, and the large <hi>Danow</hi> repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented by the ſlenderneſs of a thin line. Would you hold and graſp Nature abridg'd in the compaſs of your hand? why <hi>Hondius</hi> hath fram'd moſt exactly ſuch artificial worlds, that you may compaſs the Univerſe with the length of your fingers, and go beyond <hi>Drake</hi> with your extended Palm.</p>
                  <p>But what do men at home? they drink and ſwill: Here the gluttony of <hi>Apicius,</hi> there the ſoftneſs of <hi>Sardanapalus:</hi> here prodigal wretches conſume and waſt their dwindled Fortunes, there Gormondizers bury their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimonies in the gulph of Luxury; here beard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs youth devoted to <hi>Bacchus,</hi> there riper age martyrs to <hi>Venus;</hi> ſome born in a richer dirt, and more prodigal ſoil, are enſlaved to the Fortune of an uncertain die! others more co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous, and adoring gold, fleece the poor, and defraud the needy, and with winged ſpeed, fly to the commiſſion of all Evil.</p>
                  <p>And do not all theſe things previal yet? behold the notable Example of great <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der!</hi> from whence (moſt worthy Heroe!)
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:53205:56"/>hadſt thou thy wit and parts? what <hi>Pallas</hi> (as I may ſay) I want a word) did Parnaſſate thy Soul with ſuch Learning and Vertue? what was it plac'd thee, being greater than all Encomium, and enrolled thee among the Gods? did not thy viewing in travel, Cities and Countries? let me ask ye (O ye famous worthies, <hi>Hercules, Cato, Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cero, Plato</hi> and <hi>Caeſar!</hi>) how did ye become ſo glorious? though you are dead, yet your Example ſpeaks: 'twas your Familiarity with forreign Parts, that tranſmits your renown to ſucceeding Ages. I could cite infinite others both of former and preſent times: but I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not omit the never dying, or deathleſs memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> whoſe happy Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginity fruitful in Dominions (though not in Children) hath Chriſten'd Regions with her Name and Religion; hath planted Colonies in a new world, and hath removed <hi>England</hi> into the diſtant Continent. What ſhall I ſay of him, whom I will not call the Envy, but the wonder and amazement as well of Ancient as Modern Conquerors; who, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion to the Sun, hath compaſſed the world with that daily travellor; who hath laid open and diſcovered the hinges of the Univerſe, and to whom we are ſo much indebted for the
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:53205:57"/>knowledge of Nature, as to the famous Stagy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, its chiefeſt Secretary.</p>
                  <p>But to conclude, and that our Oration need not want authority, behold! it boaſts of Kings and Nobles; amongſt whom let us fix upon our Famous <hi>Charles</hi> of bleſſed me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, who was both a Guide and Example to forreign travel, who though much admired by his own Countrey, yet returned more conſpicuous by his <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Accompliſhments, and Forreign Acquilitions.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="24" type="declamation">
                  <head>DECLAM. XXIV. <hi>Againſt travelling abroad, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THere is nothing which we cannot both ſooner and ſafer acquire by the motion of our eye at home, than by the weary ſteps of our feet abroad. How many rare inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious perſons hath a forreign Sky unhappily transformed into beaſtly monſter? They have returned only with humane aſpect, and like the Olympick <hi>Joves</hi> mentioned in the
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:53205:57"/>Poet, have appeared glorious with their gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den heads, but are mean and fordid with their dirty bodies; like <hi>Coloſſaean</hi> Images they raviſh without with the pleaſant Hypocriſie of char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming colours, but within terrifie and affright with the ugly ſhape of an Ape or Serpent. They are more nice and effeminate than <hi>Sar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danapalus,</hi> who are ſoftned by Venery into putrefaction; whoſe exceſs and debauchery hath non-pluſs'd <hi>Bacchus,</hi> and hath drank dry even the God of Tipple. There is no un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard of Villany, which they have not either done or thought of. Behold! what aking heads? what ſwoln, puft up, <hi>Boreas</hi>-like, cheeks! what dull and heavy eyes! what tottering feet! how often do they diſgorge up their Souls amidſt their intemperate cups? and are buried with the Solemnities of drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken <hi>Bromius?</hi> 'Twas travel that brought us this vice, and the <hi>Dutch</hi> good-fellow-ſhip hath taught us Drunkenneſs.</p>
                  <p>Whence comes it that our Femaſculine Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons, our <hi>Engliſh Syrens</hi> are ſo ingenuous for Pride, who place not an hair without advice, but call a Court for the diſpoſing of every lock, who diſpence not a nod without Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, whoſe eyes glance not without an Edict, and whoſe feet do move in exact meaſure. How do they counterfeit Nature; who ſo drench
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:53205:58"/>their looks in oils, and waſhings, that they loſe their faces and complections in their gally-pots; they ſo glitter in their filks, and are ſo critically attired in ſo exact a dreſs, as if they would break the eyes of every Specta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor. From whence ſuch petulant, and ſparkling eyes? Certainly Pride taught this vice of travelling, and we may thank haugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty <hi>Italy</hi> for theſe prodigies and crimes againſt Nature. How often do we feel <hi>France</hi> in our bones? and how often find <hi>Paris</hi> on our bodies, which ſometimes doth op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs with a faſhion, and ſometimes pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh.</p>
                  <p>Let every one breath in the Air, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he was born! and let him not with wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſteps ſeek thoſe things under another Sun, which he enjoys under his own! our <hi>Lares</hi> tell us there is nothing more pernicious to good manners, than diſtant viſits of forreign Cities: there is none but brings home or commends ſome vice or other. Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors ſeldome return with the ſame humors they exported abroad; they barter faſhions, and are laden home with exotick cuſtoms. <hi>Cato</hi> and <hi>Laelius</hi> can ſcarce keep themſelves from being corrupted and debauch't; againſt whom the moſt ununiform rabble have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared <hi>Circaean</hi> cups to extoxicate them.</p>
                  <pb n="107" facs="tcp:53205:58"/>
                  <p>A juſt man, <hi>tenax propoſiti,</hi> worſhips and adores his domeſtick <hi>Joves;</hi> and, if we are wiſe, let us love, our Muſes, and go no further than this our <hi>Parnaſſus!</hi> 'tis wiſdome to keep in our preſent Manſion: for what is more unworthy a prudent man than to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure patiently the duſt and Sun, for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny years in the acquiſition of that, which one ſingle Paragraph, one ſingle Page will teach him in one hour.</p>
                  <p>The Schools are open, and Library pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick: here you read with tears of the rub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſh and aſhes of ruined <hi>Troy,</hi> of <hi>Priamus</hi> wanting a funeral Pile. Here you may read in claſſick Hiſtory of <hi>Mauſolaums</hi> and <hi>Pyramids;</hi> of <hi>Coloſſus,</hi> and <hi>Hercules</hi> Pillars, and whatſoever is celebrated by the voice of Fame.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:53205:59"/>
               <head>THE Second Part.</head>
               <div n="1" type="declamation">
                  <head>DECLAM. I. <hi>Whether Vertues are implanted in man by Nature?</hi> Affirm'd.</head>
                  <p>WHen we wander with our eyes through the dubious varieties of diſtracting Nature, and when we behold the roof of the world ſo richly beſpangled with poſies of Stars, that flame above, and the floor of the ſame, ſo luxuriouſly deck't with <hi>Aſteriſms</hi> of Flowers that twinckle beneath, or when we ſee as it were the flowry Pavement of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven beſtrew'd with Stars, and the Starry Fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mament of the Earth ſtudded with Flowers,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:53205:59"/>when we view the Univerſe on this ſide bright, and arraied in Flame; on that ſide dark, and veild with Shade; here gilded with the radiancy of a glorious Sun; there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ullied with the horror of an Eclipſing Cloud; I ſay when we have a Proſpect of theſe things, nothing is the object of our ſight, but won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and ſuch prodigies that ſurpaſs all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Invention. And as we admire the Landskip of the bigger world, ſo are we ſtricken with an equal amazement at the ſight of the leſs, I mean the ſtupendous Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick of mortal man. See! with what a lofty Perſon and Majeſtick Stature doth he ſhoot upward, whereas groveling Animals are prone downwards! what Skill and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaniſm doth his very Model declare? what excellent contrivance is legible in his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>texture? what curioſity of Art doth the leaſt Atom boaſt! with what a grace doth Beauty, that Empreſs of his fore-head, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand and ſway? how are his cheeks en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamed with the bluſhing Oriency of a purple die? What ſparklings in his eyes! what roſes in his lips! what driven Snow adorns his neck? what comlineſs and feature lie ſcattered midſt the excellent proportions of every Limb? Laſtly, what raies of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity do ſhine from his head?</p>
                  <pb n="110" facs="tcp:53205:60"/>
                  <p>If we contemplate the Elegancy of this Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick, and the moſt accurate Induſtry of Nature in this Structure; if we conſider the Pillan of this Royal Palace, and the Buttereſſes that ſupport the vaſt bulk of this proud Edefice if we obſerve the Courts without and the Cloſets within, the perplexed Labyrinths and intricate Mazes of winding Arteries, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> marvelous Luxuriency into ſprouting nerves when we reflect (I ſay) on theſe things we muſt needs be aſtoniſh't, and cannot but exclaim with <hi>Zoroaſter</hi> of old, O man the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle of daring Nature! Admiration it ſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> is delighted with this Spectacle, and Nature her ſelf is intoxicated with her own work.</p>
                  <p>And as ſhe hath bleſt the Body with ſuch excellencies, ſo might ſhe have furniſh't the Soul with the like Endowments, in reſpect of whom, Heaven it ſelf is worthleſs, and to whom the whole world gives place, and veils its bonnet: but the Immortal Gods have deny'd Nature ſo great a Boon, leaſt too im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudently ſhe ſhould boaſt that ſhe is born a Goddeſs. If ſuch a conſtellation of Vertues ſhould club at the Nativity of a poor Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal, certainly Man muſt be reckoned, if not in the ſame rank with, yet in the next form to the Eternal Deities, from whom they differ (according to <hi>Pliny</hi>) in Immortality only.</p>
                  <pb n="111" facs="tcp:53205:60"/>
                  <p>But however, let us not vilifie and diſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage the gifts of Nature, who hath been very bountiful and obliging to us; the hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtil'd into us the Principles of Goodneſs, and hath put it into our power (if we will) to be Vertuous. The Callous Farmer plows up a grave in his Mother Earth, and buries his Corn in the Bowels of our common Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent; but if the ingrateful Soil ſhall devour the Seed, and deny a Reſurrection, or an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected Harveſt, the fault is not in the Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band-man, but in the barren ground. Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hath ſcattered in us ſeeds of Vertues, but if there ſhall follow no crop 'tis not Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, but we are unprofitable. But if it had pleaſed the Immortal Gods to have crowned men with Vertue, without Labour, then there had been reaſon why Nature ſhould be blamed, and not man, and we might have juſtly complained, that ſhe is ſo cruel a Step-mother as to bring us into the world polluted with Vice and utterly deſtitute of all Vertue; but ſeeing Heaven ſells all things to Mortals for Sweat and Labour, and Vertues are the products of Study and Induſtry, and not the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> of meer Nature: men have no reaſon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> that ſhe is ſo hard and cruel. In all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> there are ſome glimmering hopes, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ing they die with age, it is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:53205:61"/>therefore Nature was not defective, but that care was wanting. Let us not accuſe Nature of Impotency, who though pregnant with Vertue, yet brings it not forth, for that is beyond her Strength and Power, nor (which is a more juſt complaint) let us in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict her of Impiety, who is always a cheriſher of Mankind.</p>
                  <p>'Tis true, one man excels another in the acuteneſs of his Faculties, yet our common Parent hath not ſo diſinherited any man of Ingenuity, as to leave him deſtiture of all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Accompliſhments. Some ſhe hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced ripe for knowledge, who (<hi>Papirius</hi> like) are capable in minority of Court Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploiments; but others muſt be anvill'd, and as it were be manufactured by Diſcipline to be made fit for Improvements. She hath not (as the <hi>Stoicks</hi> fondly dream) ſo clear'd the paſſage to Vertue, as that a man may ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive to it without Labour. Some certain colours a fleece eaſily imbibes, others (unleſs incorporated as it were into its very ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance) it will hardly receive; thus humane Souls ſometimes unfledg'd, and in their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy, haſten to be endowed with Maxims of Prudence, and ſometimes arrive to Dotage before they can attain to Knowledg. An happy Education, and early Inſtruction will
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:53205:61"/>much conduce to the faſhioning of our Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and the morning of our daies bluſhing with the tincture of wiſe Precepts, will have a good inſluence in the ordering our Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, for they ſooner reach the top, who ſweating in the aſcent, are elevated by the ſtrength of ſupporting hands; But however, the way that leads to Wiſdome and Vertue, is not block't up from any man; beſides, that Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of working, which Nature hath implanted in every man, like an indulgent Parent, ſhe hath bleſt Mortals with another Faculty, which diſpoſes to the Exertion of that Power, which ſome call <hi>Potentia ſecunda;</hi> but I rather name it an Inclination or Genius; for we uſually ſay that every man of his own Nature and Genius is prone and hath a propenſity to this or that. Such Diſpoſitions and Genius's are inbred in us, but lame and imperfect, yet ſo, as that by Execiſe and Induſtry they may be much improved; Nature hath not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed ſuch narrow limits to mans advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but that he may riſe from one degree of Eminency and be inſtalled in another, ſo that a common Souldier may have the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment of a General, and private men may ſoar to the Dignity of Kings and Emperours; thus the Soul is not confin'd within ſuch ſtrait bounds, as to remain alwayes the ſame ſhe
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:53205:62"/>is by Nature, but may refine her Being, and enlarge her ſelf by Study and Induſtry. The Genius therefore, and diſpoſition of every man muſt be tenderly cheriſh't, and be cultivated by Art, that Vertue may bloſſom from the firſt Principles, and Elements of Nature. A Souldier armed with Courage, and actuated with the Spirit of Valour and Gallantry, whoſe undaunted Breaſt knows no retreat, if his ſtout Bravery be ſharpen'd by conflicts, and is daily converſant in the ſtorms of War, he muſt needs be Victorious, and a man of conduct, he muſt needs underſtand the Strata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gems of his Adverſary, and at his Pleaſure re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns with Spils from his Enemy; but if at the ſight of Battalions, his Magnimity ſhall dwindle into Sloth and Cowardiſe, he adorns his Flight, but not the War; and deſtroyes with fear the natural briskneſs of his ſteely temper, which Labour and Hardſhip had fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented into Stoutneſs and Heroick Reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Thus the ſeeds and ſparks of Vertue that lie buried in our Souls, unleſs actuated and enliven'd by Study and Induſtry, will cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly wither and vaniſh into nothing; but if manur'd by Labour they will daily ſprout and ſhoot up into maturity. Though Vertue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive ſome imperfect bluſhes and hints from Nature, yet 'tis perfected by Documents, and
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:53205:62"/>ſage Inſtructions. All our Counſels and Endeavours tend only to repair the ruines of Nature, all Art and Diſcipline would ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply its defects; for Inſtructions would be ſuperfluous, if Nature were ſufficient. Duſt and Sun are the forerunners, and the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face to the Palm of Victory. The beſt things are beſieged with the greateſt difficulties, and as not Riches, ſo neither do Vertues pop up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Slothful and Idle. They grow on a Precipice, and whoſoever will gather them, with much Sweat and Panting muſt reach after them.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="declamation">
                  <head>DECLAM. II. <hi>Whether Nobility is Natural or Heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary, and propagated by Traduction to Poſterity?</hi> Denied.</head>
                  <p>WHat? honour a native ornament? I pray tell me, what have Mortals e're received from Nature beſides to Live and to Die? 'Tis true, ſhe hath given them a
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:53205:63"/>ductile Being, to be ſpun and wire-drawn into a few years, hath granted them a little daw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and morn of Life, but (alas!) it will quickly determine in a twilight, and night of Death. What? do our Peers owe their Titles to Nativities, and their Badges to the Midwifery of a filly woman? can ſacred Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, the enſign of their Honor, be fitted and adapted to a poor Infant? is it enough to ennoble one to have been born into the world, to have cried, and to have ſeen one day? what therefore doth it avail a man to orerun the world, and to meaſure it with the Geography of his Arms and Triumphs, and to pant and breath out his great Soul midſt the thickeſt of his Enemies, if Nobility be natural, and not to be aſcribed to the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of Vertue? as if <hi>Alexander</hi> was not ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable enough by his univerſal Conqueſt without being the Brat of his fire <hi>Philip;</hi> and as if it was more credit to <hi>Hereules</hi> to be <hi>Jupiters</hi> Baſtard, and to be the off-ſpring of the womb of impure <hi>Alemena,</hi> than to have underwent ſuch famous and renowned La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours.</p>
                  <p>Why ſuch diligence in the tedious exerciſe of ſevere Vertue? why ſuch waiting and atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance on the pale Muſes? who will not laugh at <hi>Cato's</hi> Stoiciſm, at the lamp of <hi>Epicietus?</hi>
                     <pb n="117" facs="tcp:53205:63"/>who will not deride the whole learned world, is Nobility ſprung from Nature? and is not the Product of Wit, of Parts, of Vertue and good manners? let a mans converſation be Vitious and his life profligate; let his Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectuals be ſtupid even to a Prodigie and a Proverb; let nothing be handſome and come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in his Body; nothing Mercurial, and aiery in his Soul, yet Nobility ſhall be liſted among crimes, where to live and to be, is enough to dub one honourable without converſation and living well; where Extraction, and not Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; where Blood, and not Vertue, creates a Gentleman.</p>
                  <p>But what is this Gentile Blood? tell me I pray you, whoſe Anceſtors are ſuppoſed to have inſtill'd into your veins a more noble gore. All Blood is of the ſame colour; and if ſome doth boaſt a purer die, 'tis not Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity but Health and Conſtitution that gave the tincture. The Phiſician in <hi>Phleboto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my</hi> cannot diſtinguiſh betwixt the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Stream, and the Plebeian Flood. What? Is the Blood a juice of an higher rank? and are the other Humors inferiour and common? why do you not eſteem ingenious Melancholy? Martial Choler, and light Flegme? If Honor is in the Blood, what is more refin'd than the Liquor that flowes in vulgar veins? on whoſe
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:53205:64"/>skins dwells the whiteneſs of driven Snow, on whoſe cheeks ſits the Vermilion of a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt bluſh, and through whoſe whole bodies is ſpread a Sanguine Complexion. In the Field of <hi>Mars,</hi> the King and the Subject, the General and common Souldier fall with an equal Fate, but with different Glory, ſhall I think the latter ſpilt more ignoble Blood for his Countrey, than did the former? he is a wretch, who eſteems not the leaſt ounce as dear to himſelf, as doth the great <hi>Caeſar.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But admit, that Nobility doth lodge in the Blood, yet it is but a little that flows within the narrow channels of our Veins and Arteries. But this Gentile Pluriſie ſeems at length to ſink, and what? is there any thing beſides Blood and Spirit that can conduce to Nobility? not Illuſtrious Titles, which are eaſily comprized in a few letters, and can ſoon be pronounced by a little breath; not much money, for he is not <hi>Eques,</hi> whoſoever is <hi>Auratus;</hi> not magnificent Structures, for we are covered with the roof of Heaven and with infinite Stars; nor the tedious Genealogy of an ancient Family; For trace thy Pedigree beyond <hi>Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caleon</hi> and the <hi>Arcades,</hi> and take in the <hi>Ariſtote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lean</hi> Eternity of the world to boot, proceed <hi>ad infinitum</hi> in the Series of thy Anceſtry, at length thine antiquated and obſolete Nobility
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:53205:64"/>will be drained to its dregs and to the leaſt drop of Gentile Blood. An ingenuous Nature is aſhamed to rake for Honour in the Urns and Aſhes of his Fore-Fathers. 'Twas not Hereditary Dignity of his Stock and Lineage that adorned <hi>Tully;</hi> he roſe from nothing, whom if any ſhould diſenrol from the liſt of Heroes, he deſerves not only the Fury of my Speech, but the Satyrs and Scorpions of his <hi>Roman</hi> Eloquence.</p>
                  <p>What a ſmall matter is it to be born of Nobles? worms and flies, the vileſt Inſects, that are either the errours or ſpot of wanton Nature, claim an Alliance to the glorious Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, and derive their Pedigree from the Sun and Stars. Nobility ſtreaming to a long Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity (like waters, wandring too far from their Source) degenerate from the worth of their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Anceſtors, do (as it were) fall quite from the purity of their Chryſtal Spring.</p>
                  <p>But whom, do you think, I eſteem Noble? certainly him that is ingenuouſly born, and as ingenuouſly bred, that is tinctur'd with Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and temper'd with Vertue: him, who is the golden boy of ſmiling Fortune, that widely differs from the bragging rabble, which by no other title can pretend to Nobility, <hi>quam Natura Coccino et Caſtoreo.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="declamation">
                  <pb n="120" facs="tcp:53205:65"/>
                  <head>DECLAM. III. <hi>Whether to live with a Friend is a thing much to be deſired?</hi> No.</head>
                  <p>BE gone (O my Friends) I deſire not ſo much your ſight as abſence, and had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther enjoy your room than company. I am willing ſometimes to be divorced from you, neither do I covet alwayes to live with you; for friendſhip that is alwayes converſant in my preſence becomes almoſt hatred, grows ſlender, diſdainful, and is very haughty. You cannot be ignorant, what Flames of contention are uſually kindled, and attend that Amity, which is ſupported and maintained by mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al aſpect, and how often tis offended with tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vial things. Thoſe whom we have paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately loved, and whoſe ſweet Society have importunately deſir'd, as not only Friends but Brothers and Children, and (if there be any thing more dear) the very Deity it ſelf of Friendſhip, even theſe (I ſay) we wiſh to be abſent, if they hinder our Studies and obſtruct our buſineſs; O what fervent Zeal is there to be found in Love? what
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:53205:65"/>jars in Wedlock! what ſighs and tears, what complaints and ſuſpicions 'twixt jealous <hi>Paramours!</hi> what civil Wars, I will not ſay betwixt Maſters and Servants, betwixt Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and Siſters, Children and Parents, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents and Children! what Indignation is ſtirred in them againſt their Off-ſpring, who whilſt they deſire to be good, look on them as bad; and ſo do as it were after a manner hate them, whilſt they do moſt affectionately love them. Come we now to the ſacred name of Friendſhip, which being derived from Love cannot be conceived to exiſt or be without that Paſſion. But what diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence in the lives and actions of Friends though they agree in their Ends? how do they claſh in their Opinions, Advices, and Counſels! what conflicts about Religion and ſacred things? whereas in abſence no conteſts and bickerings, no gall and bitterneſs, nothing pungent and afflicting, beſides deſires, and yet theſe longings have a reliſh of Sweetneſs and Delight.</p>
                  <p>Tell me (O my <hi>Pamphilus</hi>) why amongſt the many wiſhes of men, the chiefeſt of their deſires is the fruition of their Friend, why do they covet his Society under the ſame roof? is it becauſe diſtance of place makes Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip languiſh and is remoteneſs the bane of all
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:53205:66"/>Fidelity? doth the aſpect of thy Friend ſhed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> complacency and a quietneſs into thy Soul? and art thou but half thy ſelf in his abſence? but if a Friend may be poſſeſs'd not only na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally, but civilly too; how can abſence hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him from ſitting and walking, from rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and jeſting, from ſeriouſly diſcourſing and converſing with thee? ſometimes a Friend is not diſcern'd, but when he is abſent. A glu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of Friendſhip is nauſeous and inſipid, but a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> appetite after it gives a reliſh to its taſt; wherefore if the great Maſters of Love pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe an intermiſſion of enjoyment as very expedient for <hi>Paramours,</hi> whoſe whole plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure is in preſence, why is not an <hi>interregnun</hi> of fruition as convenient for Friends, in whoſe Vertue all delight is plac'd, and is not any way incommoded by abſence, in regard it is every where preſent. I know not whether <hi>Epicurus</hi> was at <hi>Athens,</hi> or elſe where, when writing to his Friend, he bid him do all things as if <hi>Epicurus</hi> ſaw him. But certainly <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naeus</hi> was in <hi>Campania,</hi> when ſpeaking to his <hi>Lucilius,</hi> living in <hi>Sicily</hi> by letters, he exhorts him to ſtudy, ſup, and to walk with him, which things he could not perform, unleſs he act them on the Scene of Fancy without the help and miniſtery of Coporal Organs. But perhaps thine eyes anxiouſly deſire thy
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:53205:66"/>Friend when abſent: 'tis true, ſomewhat is withdrawn from thy ſight by abſence, but nothing from thy mind; no nor from thine eyes neither, if it be a true, firm, and well eſtabliſh't Union.</p>
                  <p>For <hi>Cicero</hi> in an Epiſtle to his Friend <hi>Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus</hi> ſighting in <hi>France</hi> under the Command of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> tells us that he ſaw him not only in his mind, but with his eyes too; which if it be ſo, tell me (my good Fellow!) why canſt thou not both hear thine abſent Friend and ſee him too? unleſs your ſight is more quick and ready at a laſcivious caſt, than at a Vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous glance, and you eſteem ſound more ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable, than chaſt Love, which no diſtance or force can obſtruct or hinder— If we ſhould behold nothing, but what is directly before us and confronts our ſight, and only preſent objects ſhould delight and pleaſe us, then our viſion muſt needs be narrow, and all our En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joiments very ſcanty; then farewel all joys of mental operations, and the complacency that we find in ſevere Speculations.</p>
                  <p>Do not therefore rack thy ſelf with the thoughts of thine abſend Friend! do not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent his departure heinouſly! he that hath learn't to bear the death of his Friend, will never be concern'd, or flinch at his abſence. If thou only conſidereſt of this in Friendſhip, that
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:53205:67"/>its Foundation is perpetual, firm and ſtable, then Death it ſelf can take nothing from thee. Haſt thou never heard how <hi>Laelius</hi> in <hi>Tully</hi> comforted himſelf? how doth his dear <hi>Scipir</hi> live with him? how doth the Fame and Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of his deceaſed Friend ſurvive and flouriſh, and ſhall never be blotted out of the regiſter of his memory? do not therefore yield to thy deſires, but embrace thy Friend in Idea and Contemplation, whom neither Death nor Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence can take from thee! lament not the departure of thy ſweet Aſſociate; for this bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter abſence will ſweeren, and render more Inſcious his deſir'd preſence.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="declamation">
                  <head>DECLAM. IV. <hi>Whether Friendſhip is the burden of Vertue?</hi> No.</head>
                  <p>I Cannot think Love to be ſo degenerous a Paſſion as to ſpring only from ſervile Blood. What are thoſe Friendſhips and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſſes, thoſe delicate Blandiſhments and ſoft
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:53205:67"/>Sportings? what are thoſe chaſt Graces, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>etious Delights, and pleaſant hours it uſually affords? I'le be hang'd if Love be nothing but a ſweet Servitude. What Dialogues and Embraces? what Gifts and preſents? what acceptable Pledges of reciprocal Affections? and what? are all theſe only the mutual of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices of Bondage and Slavery? certainly we rather may exclaim, O the delicious tenor of a joyful Life! O infinite Bliſs and Happineſs! I ſhould be apt to think <hi>Jove</hi> himſelf Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chondriack and Melancholy, and not ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently happy in his raviſhing <hi>Eliſium,</hi> if he ſhould alwayes be contemplative, and not ſometimes recreate himſelf and dally in the Society of Gods and Goddeſſes. The moſt affectionate breaſts of the moſt Amorous Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles do ſometimes boil and ferment with an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and are infeſted with the ſtorms of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind Brawls. The Chryſtal Serenity of the ſmiling Heavens is darkned with the tears of a frowning Skie; and the brightneſs of the Sun is benighted with the horrour of obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Clouds: thus Friendſhip may be eclip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, but not extinguiſht, may ſink into a ſwoon and fall away, but not quite into an Apoſtacie and utterly die. He is a moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licate Lover, who cannot endure the froth of raging Language, which when the eſtua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:53205:68"/>of the blood growes calm, and abates, vaniſheth with the choler that firſt caus'd it. The commands of my Friend I obey, his advice I follow, his perſwaſions I yield to, his affections I prove, his jeſts I laugh at, and care not a fig for his anger, and yet I do nothing whereby I may be thought to ſerve him, but rather to love him; nothing by the Fatal neceſſity and conſtraint of bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, but by Friendly Counſel, and the ſwee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Sympathy of moſt obliging Lovers. I fear not the frowns of the angry Heavens, not a deluge of waters, nor Hurrican's of winds, no nor death it ſelf, if Friendſhip re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire it: for to love is ſo far from being baſe and ſervile, that it is a thing moſt excellent, generous and noble. It is but a ſmall mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to breath out ones Soul (that indiviſible Particle of Divinity and little gaſp of vital Air) and to ſhed a few ounces of Blood in the behalf of a mans Friend: in the mean time let the Envious wretch be rackt and tortur'd, till he ſob from his Skeleton his blew Ghoſt, ſcarce worthy of theſe ſhades to which 'tis damn'd; I ſay, let him ſmart with anguiſh, to whom to love, is not ſo much a ſlavery as a torment, pain and miſery! let proud Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals ſwell with loftineſs, let them huff and be ſupercilious, who trample on all that are
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:53205:68"/>beneath their Orb, and with whom to love is mean and ſordid! let the moroſe Ancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret be eternally damn'd to the ſolitude of his Cell, to whom Friendſhip is not ſervile but ſuperfluous, and who thinks to love is the only property of wanton women.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="declamation">
                  <head>DECLAM. V. <hi>Whether we may gueſs at a Mans Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners by his garb and habit?</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>FArwell all joys! and whatſoever pleaſures the Soul found in ſecrets, be gon and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh! for our privacies now are proſtitute and common, and thoſe things which were only manifeſt to Mathematicians and Aſtrologers, are now publiſht to every one by informing geſtures, and the Rabble may be now of our Privy Counſel. Every limb is become vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, and not only falſe conſtruction and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>congruity of words, but a Soleciſm in our clothes is to be feared too. O vain and foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh dread! doth Nature ſo deſpiſe her work, as that when ſhe gave men Malice, ſhe would
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:53205:69"/>not give them a ſecret too? and ſeeing ſhe hath made our Errors natural, and impos'd upon us a neceſſity of offending, what? doth ſhe ſo much imitate <hi>Juno's</hi> Tyranny, as to commit us to the rout, more glaz'd with eyes than centocular <hi>Argus?</hi> Certainly ſhe conſults better the good of Mankind, and hath not ſo far gratifi'd <hi>Momus</hi> in his deſign, as that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is tranſacted in the inmoſt receſſes and retirements of the Soul, ſhould be publickly legible on the frontiſpeice of the Face. I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal to the delicate and ſoft <hi>Alcibiades's</hi> of this age, whoſe ſmoother brow, and unruffled aſpect, the learned civility of whoſe clothes and garments, have always pleaded for the tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mults of the mind, and for the unruly crowd of their impetuous affections. I ſhould aſcribe his faults to the neceſſity of Fate, who diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covers them to the world by his gate and meen. Let every man chooſe what geſtures he pleaſe to be his Advocate; and there is ſcarce any one ſo wretchedly guilty, as to want the defence, and Apology of his Body. The Elegance of <hi>Greece</hi> hath commended the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Barbariſms of monſtrous <hi>Africa;</hi> and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing various humors are oftentimes couch'd, and lie hid under the ſame ſhape and viſage, the Judgment of Spectators muſt needs be uncertain, and the Station of Spies be
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:53205:69"/>treacherous and deceitful. How have the Fires of Love rag'd and prey'd on mens breaſts within, and yet that burning <hi>Aetna</hi> hath made no change or breach on the face without; ſo that <hi>Cupids</hi> flames (like ſubtle lightning) have diſſolved the mettle and hath left the Scabbard whole and inviolable! how often hath the wantonneſs of <hi>Venus</hi> been ſporting in the veins, when the Severity of <hi>Mars</hi> hath ſate on the brow, whoſe objurgatory looks have been ſo tetrical, as that they perſonate <hi>Cato,</hi> though <hi>Maudlin</hi> drunk. Thoſe excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Creatures, which (like ſo many Pictures) Nature hath drawn for the diverſion of Man, that ugly Viper hath animated them to their ruine, and thoſe charms, that flatter into ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of a delicate <hi>Hellen,</hi> cheats with the enjoyment of a lewd <hi>Lucretia.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Who would expect ſuch rare jewels from <hi>Aeſop</hi> or a Gold-finder? or who looks for Majeſty from <hi>Veſpaſium?</hi> they vizard them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in countenances unlike themſelves, ſo that you diſcover, or read nothing in the face but what is vulgar; for their Souls not regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Nobility of their Extraction, dwell in counterfeit Manſions below their Dignity, as <hi>Galba's</hi> Ingenuity had but a bad lodging. The Soul doth ſo withdraw it ſelf from the ſight of men, and enjoys the ſecrecy of ſo pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:53205:70"/>a retirement, as that no wit can torture it into the confeſſion of its Nature, which is a miſtery, and a riddle that lies hid from all Men. What therefore? is it condemned to ſolitude! ſhould it never lay open, and diſplay it ſelf; there have been geſtures, and poſtures of Body, whereby the mind was wont (as it were) to ſpeak and to ſhew it ſelf, and to ſhine (as it were) with certain raies, and to render it ſelf conſpicuous to the eyes of others: But (O ſad!) they were all ſo counterfeit and feigned, that after the diſguiſes of ſuch fictitious looks, and ſo many vizors of lying aſpects, who but a <hi>Priamus,</hi> or a man prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal of his Faith can believe any more? one acts a Mimick, another a Player. All men imitate and perſonate all things; and thoſe geſtures which were only promoted by Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures dictates, are now inculcated, and taught by the rules of Art. We have prov'd our ſelves the genuine off-ſpring of our true Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and are capable of a Metamorphoſis; ſo that if an <hi>Alemena</hi> be to be won, we are preſently <hi>Amphitruo'd,</hi> who cannot imitate a Philoſopher in the words of <hi>Hercules?</hi> who cannot make his breaſt as immoveable as a Rock? and his Soul as Stoical as any Picture? What <hi>Socratick</hi> Catamite, and filthy Miſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant cannot bluſh at the name of fulſome
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:53205:70"/>Vice? and cannot devoutly defend the cauſe of diſtreſſed and exil'd Vertue, ſo as to be thought a cheriſher and patron of Goodneſs; and not only the charmes and beauty of love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Vertue, and the calmer ſmoothneſs of gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Manners, but (like turning Scenes) can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent the deformities of ugly Vice, and the rougher turbulencies of unruly Affections; can at their pleaſure be tranſported with Love or Anger, Joy or Hatred, and whatſoever Paſſions are created by Nature, the ſame they can per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonate and feign by Flattery. How often do we meet with humble Servants, and yet the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of our Family is not yet increas'd? how do they invade us with inſinuations of ſapple crin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, with elaborate Phraſe, and with the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtations of almoſt a ſwearing countenance, ſo that nothing leſs can be expected than a trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion of themſelvees into our very boſoms, and a cloſe mixture and marriage of our Souls. Behold the Paraſite! how he ſtruts abroad! who being well furniſh't with his garbs, expoſes to ſale his various poſtures, and with ſome importunity demands what is't you'd have? If his Friend weep, he ſheds a tear; if he ſays he is hot, he preſently ſweats; he mingles his ſmiles with his laughter, and trembles and ſhakes with his fears. Not the twins of <hi>Hippo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi> are more alike. They are alwayes mov'd
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:53205:71"/>by the ſame Paſſions, and (like certain jewels) oftentimes languiſh with each others diſeaſe. They are ſick and well in the jucture. He is very obſequious to every nod, and reflects (like a looking glaſs) and repreſents to thee the image of thine own ſelf. Thus his tears ſtand Centinel, and his geſtures (if comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded) are ready upon the guard to make a Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Perhaps in minority, when the Soul liv'd under a Democracie of Paſſions, nor had ſworn allegiance to the Government of Reaſon, then reſtleſs commotions and an inundation of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centiouſneſs overflow'd all things; But now Reaſon is in the throne, and hath obtained the Empire, ſuch Liberty and Exorbitance will ſoon vaniſh; the Affections are ſubdued, and Nature her ſelf is almoſt become a trophie; both looks and geſtures are charm'd to a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyance with all occaſions; neither can we ſooner be transform'd by <hi>Circe,</hi> than by Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. Whatſoever whirlwinds do bluſter in the Soul, whatſoever ſtorms do roar, yet the mouth breaths a <hi>Zephyrus</hi> and ſofter gales, and if reaſon require it, an enrag'd Soul will not ſo much even as threaten a damage. I appeal to thoſe unhappy wretches, whom the pleaſant cruelty of their Prince (like the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous calm of a flattering Sea) as often as it would involve the miſerable in deſtruction,
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:53205:71"/>compels the unhappy to feign themſelves bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and to hide the clowdineſs of their Souls and their ſorrows within, with ſerenity of their aſpects and joy without. Thus ſick and ſad, as if they had eaten <hi>Sardoan</hi> roots, they laugh on the confines and threſhold of death; and ſo every man defends himſelf by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracie of his countenance, and at <hi>Rome</hi> they owe to their faces their life and ſafety.</p>
                  <p>'Tis happily contriv'd by Nature, that the whole bulk of our affections can be ſuppreſt by reaſon, that we can check them when we pleaſe, and ſometimes (as we liſt) may looſen their reins; and may reſtrain ſome within the limits of our breaſt, and diſcover thoſe on our foreheads, which the occaſion ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire. If we ſhould commit our ſelves whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to their guidance, and altogether be obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to their commands, into what Precipices would they hurl us: they would certainly betray us into all dangers, and whilſt they fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly rage like ſo many <hi>Aeoli</hi> (thoſe Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of the air) they would utterly take from us the Sea and the Earth, nay and Heaven too. But the delicate Matrons of this age have prudently been aware of this Evil, who call a Committee about the accurate diſpoſing of each ſingle hair, and diſpence not a nod with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Counſel, they ſuffer not the petulancy of a
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:53205:72"/>rowling eye, unleſs made authentick and war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranted by a publick Edict; nor do they budge a foot without meaſcure; they counterfeit Nature, and are ſo beſmear'd and plaiſtered with Ointment and Pomatum, that the face ſeeks for it ſelf and cannot find it. Let them be guilty of what fault they will, I am ſure they grow not pale at any crime; but are fortifi'd (as it were) with a brazen wall, and remain imperious even to the eyes of <hi>Linx.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Neither is the paſſage more eaſie into a Courtiers breaſt, who doth ſo wholly devote himſelf to the humor of the times, as that he almoſt forgets his proper Genius: 'tis not Nature and Inclination but Cuſtome that ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſts his apparel and geſture; both <hi>Tyrium</hi> and <hi>Trojan</hi> are clad alike without any diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and when they walk they move ſo with the ſame Soul, that you would think them poppets. But there is a vain ſort of men of a ſevere brow, who condemn theſe perſons of Folly, and brand the whole Court with the ſame Infamy; and indeed juſtly, if we liv'd in <hi>Plato's</hi> Common-wealth, or under <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>topian</hi> Government; But we muſt conſult, the age, and our preſent cuſtomes. No man ſafely ſtrives againſt the ſtream, and he doth too haughtily deſpiſe the preſent times, who ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:53205:72"/>with a bluſh, and is aſhamed to be mad. He may depart the world, whoſe Vertues would keep him from its Cuſtoms and Faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
                  <p>Who will hereafter declare his gueſs? who will ſuffer his Judgment to be deceiv'd again? now diſſimulation triumphs, and hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered and poſſeſſeth the whole world. Now every one counterfeits what geſture he pleaſes, every one wears what habit he will, and there are many ignorant Souls in a learned habit, and many (as I may ſay) ungownd minds in that long robe. Who will not therefore al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes confeſs his ignorance? who will not bluſh to own that he knows any thing? by a certain Law we know not theſe things, and ſeeing we are forbidden by Nature to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, 'tis not ſo much our crime to be ignorant as 'tis our duty; neither is it ſo much obedience, as neceſſity.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="declamation">
                  <pb n="136" facs="tcp:53205:73"/>
                  <head>DECLAM. VI. <hi>Whether</hi> Ariſtotle <hi>did well in cenſuring that ſaying of</hi> Bias <hi>the Philoſopher [Love as if you was about to Hate]</hi> No.</head>
                  <p>IF the Friendſhip of the Peripateticks was as ſafe and ſecure, as 'tis pleaſant and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightful, I am perſwaded 'twould be as much in publick like other Vertues, as 'tis now private and ſolitary; for what Felicity doth it create to humane Souls? behold! the ſame deſires and humors do lodg only in different breaſts! an acceſſory Conſciouſneſs to every ſecret, and dialogues interwoven with min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled Souls, do raviſh and delight with ſuch bewitching tranſports, as that not only the weak and ſilly, but even men prudent and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere are captivated by its charm.</p>
                  <p>But there are ſo many coverts and retire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in humane breaſts, and 'tis ſo unſafe a thing to confide in any man, that I know not whether the Friendſhip of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting of the innocent ſimplicity of a mutual
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:53205:73"/>Paſſion, and of an univerſal exchange of all Affections, I ſay I know not whether 'tis ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther an Infirmity, than a Vertue, and not ſo much our comfort as our ruine; for we that live in <hi>Tiberius's</hi> dayes muſt Chriſten diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulation with the name of Vertue, and ſo to act the parts of Friendſhip, as not utterly to forget our Prudence. For there are ſome that have a ſubtle knack in counterfeiting Vice and feigning Vertue, that have a diſpoſition changeable into every Affection, and ſmooth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſliding into the Souls of men, endeavour to pry out and find their guilt; and in this they abuſe the name of Friendſhip, that they are alwaies fear'd, but never lov'd.</p>
                  <p>There are others, who are never more to be dreaded, than when they laugh, who never lay aſide the diſguiſe of Severity, but when 'tis expedient; whoſe clowdy browes never clear up into a ſerenity of ſmiles, unleſs they can gain by ſuch calm Sunſhine; wherefore leaſt our Innocency ſhould be trap'd in ſuch ſnares, it may be very convenient to think of a ſtorm in the midſt of a calm, and to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the advice of the ſage Philoſopher, who bids us [Love ſo as if we were about to Hate] men ſlowly complain of thoſe things, which have befa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n them through their own default, and Folly is attended with this evil, it alwayes
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:53205:74"/>upbraids; therefore leaſt Temerity with its [I had not thought] ſhould rather be a Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, than an Enjoiment, and more grieve than comfort us; I fancy it the wiſeſt, and the ſafeſt piece of Dotage ſo to temper our Love, as to ſavour more of Judgement, than Affection, and ſo to deal and canton our per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to others, as to reſerve a portion for our own ſelves, whether we conſider men them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, or the danger of the thing it ſelf. 'Tis ſcarce ſo pleaſant to find a Friend, as 'tis mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable to be deceiv'd in him. If we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>template the ſeveral ages of men, we ſhall find that Minority and Rawneſs excludes Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren from the Solemnity of ſo ſacred a league, and not ſo much Peeviſhneſs and Moroſity, as Covetouſneſs debars and keeps off the Aged; they mind nothing but wealth, they negoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate in Friendſhip and gain by their traffick, and love not any man, but when it coſts them nothing. I would willingly admit men in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the moſt inward retirements and receſſes of Friendſhip, if they would either love more or be leſs wiſe; for as Affection abates as the Judgment increaſes, thus youthful heats cool at maturity; and though the fervor and violence of their Paſſions ſuffer young men to enter into the embraces of Friendſhip, yet heady Raſhneſs and an unweary diſpenſation of their
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:53205:74"/>Affections, will drive them from thoſe ſacred <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>les, and things acted with heat and violence are not ſo firm and ſtable, as thoſe, that are done with deliberation of a mature Judgement: <hi>Juvenile</hi> Affections have ſhorter periods, whoſe impetuous boilings will eaſily ferment them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into a ſudden calm; they are for the moſt part charm'd with the likeneſs of Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, and are rather jocund among themſelves than paſſionate, as <hi>Geminus</hi> and <hi>Sejanus</hi> were mutual Friends in Luxury and Softneſs.</p>
                  <p>Thus are mens ages beſieg'd on all ſides with theſe difficulties, and if we ſhall further conſider the manners of men, which they have fram'd to themſelves, we ſhall eaſily perceive there is a great neceſſity of believing our ſelves, and of not confiding in any body elſe.</p>
                  <p>The firſt ſort of men that occurr are thoſe, who as oft as we meet with them, riſe up up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their legs, and by the pleaſantneſs of their geſtures are diſſolved and melted almoſt into kiſſes and embraces; they are ready to skip out of themſelves, neither complain they of Injuries received from thoſe they love. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing fitter for Society, than theſe men, if we were born for nothing, but to ſleep and revel. They have ſomewhat of a jovial Gaie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, an allowable Innocence in him, who is permitted either to play the fool, or mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man;
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:53205:75"/>for he muſt be either the one or the other, who doth ſo laviſhly congratulate, and is ſo profuſe in his fawnings.</p>
                  <p>But there are others in the ſecond place, who have more ſober Affections, and have a kindneſs for all, proportioning themſelves to every one by weight and meaſure: their diſcourſe is obliging, and their deportment inſinuating, neither their aſpect Satyrical, nor language ſevere; they ſpeak Panegyricks, and dare not diſcharge a jeſt even againſt the moſt enormous crime. Nothing fitter for civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities than ſuch Natures, they are obſequious to every man, and being averſe to quarrelling are Enemies to no one; they never ſport or toy with their Wits, but are ſo ſolicitous and careful about their Gall, that they are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together void of, and are without Salt — But give me a Friend with whom I may diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>play the Urbanities of a jocund humor, and beguile the tediouſneſs of the hours with the pinquunt facetiouſneſs of ſmart Jeſts: but how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever in regard they are harmleſs, ſuch diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions may pleaſe whether amongſt Friends or Enemies; but becauſe they ſtudy to deſerve and careſſe ſo coldly; as that they neither love nor are beloved, and as they have moſt delicate ears, ſo the unhappy event of one cruel joke, will ſcare them out of Company.</p>
                  <pb n="141" facs="tcp:53205:75"/>
                  <p>There is a third ſort of people, who vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarily exclude themſelves from the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cincts of Friendſhip, whilſt they only ſpeak for fear of others, and if they accoſt any one, ſeem rather to commit theft, than to weave <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Dialogue: they diſcourſe ſoftly Hiſtory and Annals, and whiſper Edicts and Acts of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and (like <hi>Cinna</hi> in the <hi>Epigram</hi>) they commend the Prince in your ear, they praiſe the invention of letters, and the acri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monious moiſture of tart Citron, and (if poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible) without voice, or Books, would rather ſhew what they would have, than ſpeak it: and theſe are ſo ſuſpicious, that they are ſcarce ſecure even from themſelves; becauſe truth loves to be ſeen and ſeeks no corners, I am apt to believe therefore that there is no ſound Affection in ſuch private tempers; they are ſilly waſps of mankind, who from every Company ſuck poyſon.</p>
                  <p>There are oppoſite to theſe other Perſons, who are as free and open, as they were pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate and reſerv'd men of a chryſtal and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent breaſt, who have cribrous ſides, and are full of chinks, from whom whatſoever is put in, either through the eaſineſs of Nature, or ſoftneſs of Humor, doth leak out. Who or what theſe perſons are, not <hi>Apollo</hi> himſelf, with his whole quire of Muſes can declare
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:53205:76"/>unto us; they have an <hi>Extempore</hi> way of living, neither do they perform thoſe things they thought on, but thoſe, which they have popt on; and act not ſo much by conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration as chance, and if they offend, 'tis rather out of weakneſs than choice, out of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmity rather than Judgment: and (like <hi>Fabius</hi> in <hi>Livy</hi>) are rather inconſtant in good than diligent in evil. And as they are wild and talkative, ſo they often diſcover ſome grains of ſalt, ſome Specimens of Ingenuity, which are rather the Products of the Madneſs of their Brain, than of the Acuteneſs and Eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of their Wits. Somewhat of kin to theſe are thoſe, who are inſpired with Eloquence only at Feaſts and taverns, who never cleer up into laughter, but when they ſup abroad. Theſe ſeem to be born on purpoſe for <hi>Satur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalia?</hi> they ſpend their time in much Feſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity, but withall they live in jolly Gluttony. No man begins a ſtory more happily, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends the treatment more laviſhly. What news? he receives at the gates original Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors, neither need any one tell him the por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents of a Comet, or in what breaſt the <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard</hi> will ſheath his ſword: But if theſe perſons are driven out of the road of their common diſcourſe, then their fluency engendered at other mens trenchers forſakes and leaves them,
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:53205:76"/>and then they begin to be tedious, who on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly maintain their tongues in obedience to their bellies; and now amidſt ſuch infinite variety of Humors and Tempers, who dare unbutton his Breaſt, and unboſome his Soul, and lay himſelf naked to the conſcience of every man? who would not be cenſur'd and accus'd for Temerity, whom the Perfidiouſneſs of others ſhould thus unwarily overwhelm? though fortunate and happy Love hath bleſſed thee with a Friend free from theſe Evils ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to Mortals, one in thy Opinion fit for the miſteries and ſecrecies of private Counſels, yet thou knowſt not what a day may bring forth: there are viciſſitudes in Love, Truces and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, Wars and Peace, and though the wounds of offended Majeſty may be ſometimes healed; yet they ſo cloſe as to leave a ſcar behind them, as a monument of the Injury; ſo that there may ſtill remain a jarring Harmony, and grudges more dangerous, than open Animo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities. A fracture in a joint will hardly be ſet, and abreach in an Union ſo cloſe and intimate will be ſcarcely ſoder'd. Fraternal hatred is becom a Proverb, and 'tis a Maxime, that moſt implacable Emnities are betwixt thoſe of a blood.</p>
                  <p>Thus you ſee tis not ſafe to be too much a companion, but ſometimes deſtructive; for who
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:53205:77"/>is there that underſtands men, and who is a ſagacious diver into humane Souls? I ſay amidſt the inſinuating careſſes and blandiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Lovers, as exchang'd hands, mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Embraces, and reciprocal Sighs, Proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Oaths, who dare, I ſay, rather pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe or aſſure himſelf of Fidelity, than deceit and ſnares? certainly more innocent and harmleſs Souls have been often circumvented by ſpecious pretences and appearances of Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, and ſuch impoſtures are ſo much the more rife, by how much the more ſecurely they can cheat and cozen. Who would have thought any Treachery lurk't under that vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard of Friendſhip between <hi>Firmius Catus</hi> and his dear <hi>Libo,</hi> who was his Aſſociate in Luxu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Debt and Luſt too? who would have ſuſpected Falſhood in the Familiarity between <hi>Lactiaris</hi> and <hi>Sabinus?</hi> Love and Affection the moſt ſimple things in the world are both enſnar'd, and <hi>Libo</hi> and <hi>Sejanus</hi> are deſtroyed by thoſe from whom they expected the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Safety. Wicked <hi>Latiares</hi> occur every where, who after the greateſt Profeſſion of the ſincereſt Love do entrap Mortals in their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wary diſcourſes; they are the worſt kind of Enemies, for whom we cannot be prepared in War, and againſt whom we cannot be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure in Peace; <hi>vomica &amp; carcinomata humani
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:53205:77"/>generis</hi> born only for the publick evil, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to ſail in <hi>Trajans</hi> boat, being Piacular victims of inteſtine Wars, Slaughters, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolations, and ſeeing they are hated as much by them, whom they proſit, as by thoſe whom they accuſe, let them ſuffer puniſhment with the ſame pain, they procure it. Men can never be cautious enough at all times; and I fear a man can never be ſuſpicious enough about their Examples, from whoſe end there can never be faithful ſecurity.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="declamation">
                  <head>DECLAM. VII. <hi>Whether the decay and Periods of Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pires are to be aſcrib'd to Fate?</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>WHat? when Fortune ſuſpends the gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of the world, does it then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to ſhake and totter? Is the Univerſe Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern'd by the Fortuitous turnings and teme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarious courſes of blind chance? 'tis unſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable impiety that diſturbs and tortures <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picurus</hi> his Ghoſt; we follow not the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:53205:78"/>of the Heavens, neither do we lead our lives according to the Government of the Stars. All things are eſtabliſh't in certain Periods, and we are all rul'd by the preor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain'd Counſels of impendent Fates. Behold! the Funerals and remaining Aſhes of the chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt Monarchies! a purple'd Emperor crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into the narrowneſs of a little Urn! ſee! the poſthumor rubbiſh of mouldred Cities, and the noiſome carcaſes of numerous Armies! one hour will ſacrifice a thouſand <hi>Myriads</hi> to the ſhades below. See! this is the ratified decree of the ſtubborn Deſtinies.</p>
                  <p>He that in the volumes of the Heavens hath read the Nativities of Kingdoms, and hath conſulted the Stars, midwifeing it at the Birth of an Infant Empire, I ſay, ſuch a man may by a certain Augury foretel the Fatal Period of a dying Nation as well as if he had ſtudied the diſmal Annals of the cruel Fates, or as if the Gods had inform'd him by the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſy of their Agent, I mean their Mercury. When a Comet ſlames with its direful beams, and when the Deities have ſet up their fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Torches, who ſuſpects not the death of a King at hand? ſurely they kindle thoſe bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing Lamps to diſcover the untrodden way of Princes to Bliſs, or rather they are Feſtival Lights, Solemn Bon-fires, made by the Gods
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:53205:78"/>to congratulate their Inſtalment into their pleaſant Paradice.</p>
                  <p>There is nothing in the world more auguſt than Majeſty; 'tis a perſonated Deity, and is inſcrib'd with Divinity. How ſacred is that head that ſupports a Crown! how holy that Perſon that's attir'd with reverend and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt Purple? yet thoſe that celebrate mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificent Nativities, and more ſolemn Obſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quies, tell us, that even <hi>Caeſars</hi> themſelves are born and die as we do; Nature hath made them of nobler mould, but yet one ſpark of a Feaver, one dram of Poiſon will ſoon di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpatch them from the Elements, and ſend them on an Errand into another world. How ſlippery is the top of fickle Fortune! how ſteep and declining is Honours Precipice? how whirling and unſteady are the Pinnacles and Battlements of Potent Empires! The haughty Sun that now culminates in the <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nith</hi> with his whole Orb of Light, after a few minutes declines towards his weſtern Grave; and the Lamps of Heaven are all kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to inflame the magnificence of his Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral; and thus the conſtitutions of Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pires are brittle and uncertain. An ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious cloud through the propitious ſerenity of a ſmiling day, aſpires aloft, and climbs the air, which being diſquieted and toſt by
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:53205:79"/>the ruder winds, melts into tears, and weeps it ſelf down into the lower Region; and ſuch is the downſal of the greateſt Dignity.</p>
                  <p>Fancy <hi>Alexander</hi> the Lord of the Earth, and the univerſal Monarch of all Nature; I ſay, Fancy him on a Throne begirt with a ring of numerous Guards; Fancy the whole race of mankind to be liſted into one <hi>Mace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donian</hi> Army! and then I pray, what ruſtick Deity can be ſo uncivil as to dethrone the King, to uncrown his brow without incur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the guilt of horrid Treaſon? yet after all this Pomp, after a few years he yields to Fate, at the diſſolution of whoſe Empire, are born many petty Principalities, as the Stars do ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear and riſe at the Suns Funeral. Why ſhould I mention the Tragical Cataſtrophe's of expiring Kingdoms. The whole Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe haſtens and inclines to the Weſt, and we, whom Nature hath reſerv'd to the laſt twilight of the ſetting world, I ſay, we muſt undergo the extream viciſſitudes of all things, when the Univerſal contexture ſhall be all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ravell'd, and the ſeries of time ſhall have run to its laſt ſand. I wonder at the quietneſs of Students in ſo great a whirlwind and hurry of Buſineſs, who deſpiſe the Vanities and Trifles of Wealth and Honours, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire not ſo much as what the world is do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing without their Studies.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="declamation">
                  <pb n="149" facs="tcp:53205:79"/>
                  <head>DECLAM. VIII. <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity doth preſerve a City.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>SO Divine are the advantages, ſo charming the Beauties, and ſo prevalent the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and Force of Unity, that 'tis the very Life and Soul, the very Flame and Spirit that actuates, that gives briskneſs to every thing. If all Strife was condemn'd to the ſhades below, and this kinder Deity would converſe with men here in this light above, I know not what golden ages, what pleaſant <hi>Eliſium's</hi> 'twould procure to Mortals, nay (to ſpeak more boldly) an Eternal world, but as the Philoſopher tells us, if the Sun ſhould be bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried in an Eclipſe, and be exiled from his Orb, the day would be extinguiſh't, and die into darkneſs, and the obſcure Globe of the wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed Moon would flie and vaniſh into winds and ſhowers: and thus, if concord ſhould be baniſh't from this Sublunary Scene, and Friendſhip oſtraciſm'd out of this inferiour world, and the golden chain of Unity ſhould be unlink't and broken; how ſoon would this beauteous contexture be all unravelled
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:53205:80"/>into its firſt Chaos, the unpropt Heavens would want an <hi>Atlas;</hi> Kingdoms would moulder into duſt and rubbiſh; and Princes vaniſh into air and ſhades; there would be either no Empires at all, or very vain ones like heads in Pictures without brains. In vain would the Heavens ſlatter themſelves with the hopes of a long duration of inviolable Stars and uncorrupted ages, if they did not harmoniouſly accord within themſelves, and all diſcord being divore'd of the wrangling Qualities, if by a happy marriage they were not united to their matter and among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves too.</p>
                  <p>The daily diſſolution we ſee in things, and their continual haſtning to their laſt period, proceeds meerly from Strifes and Conteſts. The Elements do mutually engage at cuffs, and as it were ſtudiouſly bent on each others ruine, do box it ſtoutly till death do part them. Neither can we mortals boaſt a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Safety, who through Wars and Contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons do ruſh upon our Fate with winged ſpeed. Death would every where be eſteem'd but a Fable and Phantaſm, a very valn and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vial Deity, if men would accord within them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and enter into a ſtrict League of mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Charity. For no life ſo happy or (as if emulous of Heaven) comes nearer the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:53205:80"/>of the Gods above, than where there is a recipocal Harmony of wills and deſires, and (if poſſible) a mixture of Souls. The moſt impregnable Bulworks, nay the Sinews of a Nation, even money it ſelf, cann't ſo forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie a City, as the mutual Kindneſs, and Love of Citizens. No engins whatſoever, nay the tutelar Deities themſelves can't be Taliſmans ſufficient for the defence of that place, which is not bleſſed with the ſacred Genius of Una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimity. For how doth it lie open even to an unarmed man, when fermenting and boiling with inteſtine fends it contends againſt it ſelf, and is its own Enemy! to how great dangers both of Rocks and Waves is that veſſel expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, which amidſt buſſling ſtorms and the ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping Ocean (as it were for the paſtime of the winds) is diſtracted with the contrary vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence of divers pilots! and certainly to no leſs hazards is obnoxious that City, whoſe Inhabitants diſagreeing among themſelves, and being of various tempers, do exchange their Peace and Quiet for bloody brawls and inhumane Slaughters. That, either ſhelves and quick ſands, this, either its ſelf, or its Enemies will overwhelm with ruine. As a diſmal inſtance of this ſad Event, I appeal to that fortified City of <hi>Regium,</hi> ſo beſieg'd on all ſides with ſtrength and Bulworks, that it ſtood
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:53205:81"/>impregnable againſt all invaſion, and bafled the aſſaults even of the God of war: But when once it began to groan under inteſtine Animoſities, with what winged ſpeed did it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lie to ruine, and how ſoon did it drop into duſt and rubbiſh? how many Ghoſts did the civil Wars diſmiſs to the ſhades below! how did they tire the Deſtinies with repeated Funerals! and weary the boat of re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>leſs <hi>Charon?</hi> and at laſt, with what Facility did the beſieg'd, their ſtrength being moſt decay'd by a long League, I ſay, how ſoon did they raze the City, and drew about it their hoſtile plow? and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (O <hi>Rome!</hi>) not an Army of mountains can promiſe thee unſhaken wals, or a ſafe Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitol, ſo long as thou frameſt to thy ſelf <hi>Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jan</hi> horſes, whilſt Private <hi>Catilines</hi> with fire and ſword invade the Senate.</p>
                  <p>There is no ſpeedier way to Spoils and Tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phies, than when (Swords and Souls as it were conſpiring) all men level at the ſame end. Nothing ſooner blocks up the paſſage of an invading Enemy, than twiſted Counſels and breaſts united in one common Harmony. Not numerous <hi>Xerxes,</hi> a General more formi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable than any <hi>Encelladus,</hi> at whoſe ſight the very Sun abſconded and Nature totter'd, whoſe Army ſip't up the Ocean, and whoſe Arrows Heaven; I ſay, this terrible Warriour
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:53205:81"/>could not one jot prevail, either with fire or ſword, againſt united <hi>Greece;</hi> for that all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding Diety, Love, ſoon ſcatter'd his Forces better than the ſtrength of any Engine. What unprofitable darts did that grim aſpect of war ſhoot and level? how was the ſword bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh't in vain? neither could any Arm, or the God of war himſelf do any thing.</p>
                  <p>Let us reflect on our age, and take a ſurvey of this Kingdom! what ſerene dayes have we enjoyed here! how, to the envy of ages and nations, without camp or ſword, hath our <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain</hi> flouriſh't! and I hope will for ever enjoy an undiſturbed peace! we congratulate our Unity, Peace, Laws, Judges, Flamines, Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, Cities, Academies, and whatſoever is ſacred or auguſt in this our <hi>England.</hi> What Elegancies are legible and inſcrib'd on the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick of the body? what charms are conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuous in each part, and what Divinities are ſcattered in every member! how in vain doth the Dotage of the year diſcover its horyneſs in Ice and Froſts, and with what fruitleſs flames do the Stars burn; ſeeing it can eſtabliſh to it ſelf an amicable concord, and harmoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous temper; whereas let but the diſagreeing Principles of things contend and ſquobble, and how ſwiftly do they haſten to their ruine?</p>
                  <p>Thus Cities grow, and great wealth is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved,
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:53205:82"/>and a little increaſed by Concord; but Diſcord diminiſheth the moſt pompous riches, and utterly razeth the moſt opulent Towns. Thoſe things are moſt durable, which are moſt one and united; and all things covet an Eternity, and are ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous of Immortality. Thus ſtones ſtick moſt cloſely in their ſeveral Parts; water crowds into a globe leaſt it ſhould periſh by diviſion; if any thick body be laid upon it, it is advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced upward, and (I know not by what in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct) preſerves it in an abiding ſtate, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard the parts will not be ſeparated from their parts; for all ſeparation is fatal to things that are alike. Particles of water falling on the pavement of a ſmooth table, appear and ſhew themſelves tumid and globular, neither will be demoliſh't into flatneſs by the ſhaken board. But if other portions of the Element be added to them, then one drop hath a mind to, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fires another, and then they are as it were immediately married and mutually incorpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated, aſſiſting each other againſt the hoſtili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the air, and the violence of the ſurface on which they fell, leaſt they ſhould be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroied by them. All which do as it were with a vocal ſtilneſs whiſper and ſuggeſt and as ſo many mute Doctors do proclaim by their filence, what a guard inviolable Concord and
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:53205:82"/>Unity uniterrupted by Strifes and emulous of Eternity hath indulged to Nature.</p>
                  <p>But now, if Nations owe their Cities, (thoſe Souls of Kingdoms) and Scepters to Love and Amity, and are more ſafely begirt with a guard of hearts, than of ſwords or hands, or if theſe ſublunary things in the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of this Deity, ſhould be preſently in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volv'd in a ſudden deſtruction, neither Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture her ſelf, nor the World, no, nor the Deities themſelves could prorogue their Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity: If this is the happyeſt boon and the ſafeſt benefit that Nature ever beſtowed on mankind, I wiſh all things lucky and proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous to all men; and tis the ſum of my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires that this our <hi>Parnaſſus</hi> may eternally flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh with the beauteous harmony of Counſels, Arts and Souls; and above all names, thrice holy be to us that innocent and propitious Genius of Unity and Concord; but as for Strife and Diſcord, let them for ever be condemn'd to the lower Regions, and be a vexation to the Furies amongſt which they were bred! let Envy be baniſht to the infernal ſhades whoſe poyſonous Nature blaſts by infection its neighbours Fame, leaſt it ſhould ſurvive and increaſe its leaneſs. Be gone all ye cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous detractors with your virulent tongues, who are arm'd with the points and ſtings of
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:53205:83"/>Satyrs, or pointed with the ſtings of Satyrs, whoſe weapons are tincttur'd with the blood of Vipers; who never think themſelves more content and quiet, than when they wrangle and brawl with the greateſt diſquietude! let fraternal Animoſities die and vaniſh! let it be no longer proverbial that moſt implacable En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity ariſes from blood! let us not, as if born ſo many <hi>Catilines</hi> againſt our <hi>Rome</hi> promote domeſtick fewds, or civil diſcord, but let all our Studies, Muſes, Souls and deſires conſpire in this one thing, that theſe our manſions may ever enjoy the bleſſing of peace to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of Piety, Concord, Vertue and Unity.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="declamation">
                  <pb n="157" facs="tcp:53205:83"/>
                  <head>DECLAM. IX. <hi>Whether the Senſes can err, or be decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, when converſant about their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per objects?</hi> Affirm'd.</head>
                  <p>HOw is humane Underſtanding inwrapt in darkneſs? how is that Diviner frag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a Rational Soul benighted as it were in the miſts of Error! that off-ſpring of <hi>Jove</hi> that conſtitutes men, nay Dignifies them with the Eſſence almoſt of Gods, I ſay, how is it invelop'd in clouds of Ignorance! the too fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent infirmities and failures of craz'd and diſtempr'd heads, and that variety of danger to which every year, age, and lives of all men are caſually expoſed, are too ample demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations of this truth.</p>
                  <p>Behold!
<note place="margin">A diſcription of an Epicure.</note> here's one born for the Luxury of a banquet! ſee! another. <hi>Sardanapalus,</hi> whoſe very Nature is calulated for a feſtival entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. He Deifies a Kitchin, and adores the ingenuity of a pallatable diſh, and is proſtrate to a table groaning under the varieties of <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſian</hi>
                     <pb n="158" facs="tcp:53205:84"/>delicacies. He looks upon that to be the flower of being, and as it were the Life and Soul of Life, which lies melted and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved in the midſt of Junkets even to the nau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeating of the plenty of loath'd dainties. He never thinks he fares deliciouſly unleſs his riot doth invert the ſeaſon, and he crown his goblet with winter Roſes; unleſs <hi>Falernian</hi> diſſolve the Summer Snow in his cup of Pearl, and a ſtrange Fowl of an unknown sky, or an exotick Fiſh of a forreign ſhore are the conſtant meſſes of his curious meals. He increaſes the thirſty Avarice of his ſilver drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie with golden naps, being laborious even be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond <hi>Cleanthes</hi> for ſelf and money. He fancies to himſelf I know not what kind of Chime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal happineſs to ariſe even from his very poc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets, and had rather be a <hi>Craeſus</hi> or a <hi>Midas,</hi> than a <hi>Saturn</hi> or a <hi>Jove</hi> in their reſpective Heavens.</p>
                  <p>He loves to be ſeen in a crowd or throng, and then thinks he moſt happily ſets up his plumes, when his ſweaty ſingers are hoop'd with a Summer ring.</p>
                  <q>
                     <l>When born on ſix mens ſhoulders (on both ſides</l>
                     <l>The curtains tuck't up, windows open) rides</l>
                     <l>Lolling <hi>Mecaenas</hi> like —</l>
                  </q>
                  <pb n="159" facs="tcp:53205:84"/>
                  <p>Every wiſh aims at Empire, and he is high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſmitten with and dotes on Monarchy. Whilſt his Soul is involv'd in clouds of Error, it is a very ill Judge of things, wherefore he, ambitiouſly breathing after that Fortune, which the higher it is, it is the more unſtable, and through the anger of the Fates ſinks and falls with a greater ruine.</p>
                  <p>So purblind are the minds and underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of men, that it oftentimes embraces fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities for truths, and (whilſt we too ſilly do follow its guidance and conduct) it doth varniſh, and adulterate evil into good; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with we are not only unwarily deceived, but ſometimes enſnared into our own ruine; and can by no means promiſe the raies of the Moon and Stars to be kept inviolable, if a bolder cloud and impudent darkneſs ſhould invade the Sun; neither can it be hop'd that thoſe ſtreams ſhould be clear and chryſtall, which derive a filthineſs from the very Fountain.</p>
                  <p>The Will ſeems to be darkned by the borrowed errours of the Underſtanding; if therefore theſe endowments of Immortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, theſe almoſt Godlike Powers of the Soul, the Mind and Will, have their failures, falſe Images and repreſentations of things, we ſhould much offend in aſcribing ſo great a certainty to outward ſenſes, which we have in
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:53205:85"/>common with brutes. Theſe guards or cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinels are ſo far from being acute anddex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous, that their deceptions equal them, and they are guilty of as many Errors as they have Objects. Thus the Stars to the bleerey'd are as ſo many Giants, and the Moon ſeems leſs than every wheel. I ſhall not inſiſt on phantaſtick Meteors, which having no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtence, are only ſplendid and gawdy appariti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; thus ſweets are bitter to the Feaveriſh Palat. Here is one tickled with the harmony of the Spheres, and there is one offended with the fragrancy of a Roſe. The Errors of the Senſes are ſo frequent and familiar, that it is not worth while to inſiſt any longer upon them.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="declamation">
                  <pb n="161" facs="tcp:53205:85"/>
                  <head>DECLAM. X. <hi>Whether Monarchy be the beſt Form of Government.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>SIlence! what confuſed Noiſe and Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mult is this? How great a concourſe of clamorous People! Can we tell what they ſay, or wherefore they are come to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether? They cannot tell themſelves. Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, Liberty they cry, and they ſay, they are come to chuſe their Governours. Let them ſet their hearts at reſt, and calmly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part; their Governour is not now to be choſen, ſince God and Nature, and Law Natural are before hand with them, who have unanimouſly appointed them a Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment under one Soveraign Governor, whom they call a Monarch: For who brought in other Forms, Ariſtocracy or Democracy; Let them look back into the Originals of Rule and Government, trace the Hiſtory of their Anceſtors, when the world was not ſo mad and tumultuous? Do we find Anarchy in the firſt Ages? Any Field-meetings and tumultuous Inundations of People, which, their banks being broken, furiouſly drive
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:53205:86"/>on and bear all before them? Did God and Nature ſo ill provide for the world, that they left them at any time without Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that men muſt ſhift for themſelves and be their own Providers of ſo great a Bleſſing.</p>
                  <p>'Tis true, if Mankind had grown out of the Earth like Muſhrooms, or ſpawn'd in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the world at one inſtant, if they had been transform'd from Emmets to <hi>Myrmidons,</hi> or like Frogs and Todpoles, (the only <hi>Abori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genes</hi> that I know,) had been conceived by the ſlime of <hi>Nile,</hi> and from thence, peopled the world, they might then have muttered ſomething of chuſing a Governour, if a Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in the State of a Natural Barbarity and ſavage life can attain to ſo much ſound rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and good inſight in Morals as to call for Order and Government, which I much queſtion, ſince civil Education is one of the benefits of Government: as for Experience, there can be none in our caſe.</p>
                  <p>No, <hi>Principio rerum,</hi> ſaith the Hiſtorian, <hi>Gentium Nationumque imperium penes Reges erat.</hi> At the beginning the world knew none but Monarchy. <hi>Omnes antiquae gentes Regibus quondam paruere,</hi> ſaith the Orator. Not only the Eaſt and South <hi>Aſia</hi> and <hi>Aegypt,</hi> but even <hi>Italy, Greece,</hi> and the territories thereof, which in after ages admitted Democracy, or Ariſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cratical
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:53205:86"/>mixtures, ſuch as <hi>Argos, Athens, Sicyon, Lacedemon,</hi> were at firſt governed by Kings, whoſe names are ſtill preſerved in Hiſtory. For ſo it is, if we run back the ſcries of the Generations of the world, as far as the clew will guide us, we ſhall find that Government was firſt founded in Families, which mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplying into Tribes, became Townſhips, then Cities, whence their Dominion growing conſiderable, diſcovered to their Neighbours their way of Government, which was by their Natural Prince.</p>
                  <p>Where then is the Noiſe? the Liberty that they ſo cry up, what would they have when they ſay they are free-born? they do not intend, ſure, to do what they liſt; For if Monarchical Power, as all civil, yea and bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous Nations confeſs, is founded in Pater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Power, then it is clear from God and Natures Law, that no man can ſay, he is free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born from Government, ſince it is his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor, who begat him.</p>
                  <p>Hence the Divine Command, which knew how to expreſs it ſelf, by <hi>honouring</hi> our <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> and <hi>Mother,</hi> ſecures Obedience to their Prince, being literally true in <hi>Adam, Noah, Abraham, Iſrael,</hi> that they were Fathers and Princes of their People.</p>
                  <p>And that the Commonalty may learn what
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:53205:87"/>ſhare they had then in Election of their Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour, the firſt-born, by his Primogeniture, his unqueſtionable Right, ſucceeded.</p>
                  <p>This is the Government, which God and Nature hath appointed; All other Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are Sophiſtical, forced devices of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litique unpolitique men, lame and imperfect and ſpurious Models, ſcarce to be called by the beauteous name of Government, but as they reſemble the feature and lineaments of Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy. I know the unhappy conceptions of the inconſiderable Vulgar, who (for want of Education and better Principles) look upon their ſupreme Governour, as a Nuſance to mankind, a perſon only of an exalted For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, living at his eaſe and ſplendor (which if they were anatomized, we ſhould find they grudge to all, but themſelves) Careleſs in the mean time of the Law, and the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth, with Power to oppreſs, not to Protect.</p>
                  <p>But this is a falſe Character, unreaſonably made up by the Envious obſervers of the fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lures of the perſon, who never counterpoiſe them with the unſpeakable benefits we enjoy under Him. The beholder was in the ſhade and dark ſide of the Piece: Let him ſuffer himſelf to ſtand in the true light, and he ſhall diſcern better Features.</p>
                  <pb n="165" facs="tcp:53205:87"/>
                  <p>Conſider Him, with me, as the Sacred Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of JUSTICE, a Word not to be writ but in Capital Letters, engraven in a Memory of Marble: Conſider Him as the great Soul of the LAW, the Rule and Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard of Juſtice, and like the Soul, (for that alſo is a Monarch and hath its juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction) exerciſing vital acts through all, even the remoteſt parts of his territories, in every Borough, Village, Hamlet, by his inferiour Courts and Officers, without which there is no Life in the Body, no Liberty, no Safety, no Right, nothing that is dear to us ſhall be enjoyed, nothing that is due to us ſhall be recovered; All that I am or have ſhall be at the mercy of another; my eſtate, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther left me by my Anceſtors, or dear gotten by indefatigable induſtry, carried away with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out remorſe; my Cattel driven off my ground, Herbage trod to dirt, Corn fields fired, my Children ſpirited away, Wife raviſhed from my armes, my own perſon dogg'd and way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laid by treacherous miſcreants, and for a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal concluſion of all miſchiefs, barbarouſly murdered; my carcaſs in the mean while bleeding for a Coroner, only my Soul ſcapes away to complain of the murder.</p>
                  <p>So that without the Law, I ſhould not live in a Tub, with the Philoſopher, but in a
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:53205:88"/>Mortar, where every Man may pound me; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that even my fears would daily kill me, as in a diſtreſſed veſſel in a very tempeſtuous Sea, men dye every minute, and their hearts ſink a thouſand times before the veſſel is foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred.</p>
                  <p>How bleſſed a thing is Government, which ſtaves off all theſe injuries from us? and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bids them under ſuch ſevere penalties which none but mad men will incur? How bleſſed a thing is Law, which brings Safety into the world, and Innocence, the Parent of Safety, under whoſe protection I enjoy my uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined Liberty, my houſe is not my priſon but my caſtle, the high-way is my rode, the neighbour meadows are my walks, and the whole land is my market.</p>
                  <p>Theſe things conſidered, it is meer ſtupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity not to think of a Governor with honour, and mention him with reſpect, the Monarch I mean, if Kings prove to be the ancient form, to <hi>Them</hi> we are obliged for the eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhing theſe Laws, and to none before them.</p>
                  <p>Where are the Republicans then, is not our Monarchy a Commonwealth? Ingratitude it ſelf cannot deny it? The other Names of Common-wealth counterdiſtinct to a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, are but a cheat; a deluſion of the people
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:53205:88"/>with an ambiguous word; for a Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth truly ſo called, is really found in the Regal Government, as is evident by the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, its firſt rudiment, where the Laws of the maſter of the houſe provide for the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon good, even for the Servants themſelves, according to their Station. But tis true, as it happens in Families, ſo we often ſee it in Kingdoms, men are weary of their ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Freedomes too, when they cannot mend themſelves.</p>
                  <p>For the eſtabliſhing of Monarchy therefore, let all Patrons of Ariſtocracie and Demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cracy know, there are and ought to be many Governors ſubordinate, yet Soveraignty is ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in one. One, I ſay, to avoid diviſion, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hateful becauſe it obſtructs the common good, proves the bane of Governor and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; Juſt as if you divide the Natural Body, it periſhes; yea one Limb ſevered from the whole, keeps no life after; but endangers the reſt. Not a poor worm divided can ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt, its ſevered pieces may make a ſhew of life and ſtruggle for a while, but they never unite again, an Army divided needs no other foe, it countermines and diſſipates it ſelf.</p>
                  <p>Trace we therefore the Footſteps of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine and Humane Wiſdome, and we ſhall find by way of prevention, one Head in the
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:53205:89"/>Natural Body, and one Head in the Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique, one <hi>Paterfamilias,</hi> one Husband, one Prince, one General, one Pilot. What is the Lion in the Forreſt but the Prince of his ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritories, the Maſter Bee (King or Queen we will not diſpute) but the Monarch of the hive, the Sun in the Firmament, the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, the leader, the <hi>Choragus</hi> of all the Stars. God has made Monarchy to flare in our eyes, in Heaven it ſelf, there is One Chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, and how much more ought there to be on earth, ſeeing in earth, we have many giddy Planets, who will go direct and retrograde and how they pleaſe.</p>
                  <p>May we not add, the Lord of the Univerſe is but <hi>One,</hi> nay, that his perfection lies in that he is but One, two chiefs are as abſurd as two infinites, certainly all Majeſty is ſeated in Unity, Divided Government makes no ſhew, there is Majeſty in the proſpect of a vaſt mountain, and none in a hundred molehils.</p>
                  <p>And what news is it to tell the world, even from that one head of the antiquity of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy, that the Earthly Monarch is conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Heavenly, ordeined to be his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puty, a Vice-Roy to him, reigning in his ſtead? Weak People, God help us, we are not willing our duty ſhould be demonſtrated to us, we would have all obligation to be at pleaſure and
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:53205:89"/>indifferent, but yet tis this Divine Deputation which only exalts and ſets him on his true baſe, ennobles the Governour, not his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or his Nature (for with the poor ruſticks leave, he is a man like us) but his Relation to that Soveraign Power, far above all Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pality, whoſe very adumbrations require our honour, ſubjection being due to his Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</p>
                  <p>And leaſt the Republican ſhould plead igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, let us ſhew him how this Relation is made known, more eſpecially in Succeſſive, the only true Monarchy: Even by that very <hi>Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> when Heaven is pleaſed to commend to us a Prince deſcended of Princes, and that by an Immemorial deſcent, willing to ſignalize a Family and perpetuate the ſtream of Blood Royal from age to age; Beſide Perſonal Majeſty, not <hi>aſſumed,</hi> but <hi>inherent, Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Clemency, Gracious</hi> and <hi>Peaceable</hi> Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, to which we muſt add a Teſtimony from Heaven, <hi>Miraculous</hi> gifts of <hi>Healing</hi> entailed upon the Blood: So is the Lions Prerogative manifeſted by his pace and aſpect, and the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidence of the Bee by his ſize and wing.</p>
                  <p>So that we ought to hear no more of that infidel objection, <hi>That the King is but One, and therefore cannot be greater than his thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of his People:</hi> the anſwer is bold to ſay,
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:53205:90"/>He ſtands for GOD; ſo that though he is One, he is found in the place of millions, and according to true Arithmetick, if we trie nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meration aright, he is of more value then the ſubſequent numbers.</p>
                  <p>Let the King therefore be chief in Gods name, and then view his lovely train of <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, Dukes, Earls, Viſcounts, Marqueſſes, Barons, Knights, Judges, Gentry,</hi> to take no notice of the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> ſtate, How tranſporting is the proſpect, how beautiful and ſtately is the incloſure, a Garden deckt with flowers Imperial, diſtributed in their Beds, where by the variety of their Colours, in field ARgent, Or, Gules, Verl, they delight and diſtract the eye (while we the poor com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons are the humble Graſs-plots of the place) All with the <hi>Heliotrope,</hi> worſhiping the Soveraign, who gives life and ſpirit to us by day, and refreſhes us with his dews by night.</p>
                  <p>What of this have we in a Democracy; Go to the <hi>Roman;</hi> Firſt, a goodly pair of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuls, then two or three hundred Patricians, over them a Cenſor to take their names, yea and eſtates too; a Praetor, a Tribune two or three or more according as they can ſpeed in the ſcuffle of Elections, a Scavenger Aedile &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>We will not anatomize the <hi>Belgie</hi> Eſtates,
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:53205:90"/>nor yet the <hi>Venetian Optimacy,</hi> we hear of the number of their <hi>Clariſſimo's:</hi> All that we ſay is, they have a blot in their Eſcocheon, a great di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minution of Honor on this very account of the plurality of Governors. Tis more honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to be governed by One, more honorable both to Governor, and Subject alſo; the firſt, that a Monarch is more Noble then any, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by this, that He to whom ſingly the whole is committed, is more Honoured than thoſe Many to whom it is jointly entruſted, as clear, as that the Whole is greater than the Part, ſo that is diſpatched. More honourable even for the Subject, the People governed; for there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they get the name of a peaceable, tracta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, wiſe and intelligent people, who, come the worſt that can be imagined (and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever can be imagined, will be objected by turbulent perſons) had rather <hi>ſuffer</hi> ill than <hi>act</hi> it, rather wait upon the will of Heaven, than throw themſelves into hurry and confuſion, Confuſion being a plague not to be found in Hell it ſelf, not to be lookt upon without horror by all who have known or heard of its diſmal acts on the late Engliſh <hi>Pharſalia,</hi> an infatuation greater then any other, which can befal a People, greater then <hi>Lunacie, Mania,</hi> or whatever ſpecies there are of diſtracted wits, in a miſerable, mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cileſs
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:53205:91"/>People. A <hi>Clariſſimo</hi> is an honourable perſon perhaps, in his own precinct, but abroad, he is to ſeek. A perſon loyal to his Prince is honoured whereſoever he comes, all forreign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers do welcome him to their coaſts. For the world hath no notion of that Honour, which men cut out to themſelves, pitiful <hi>glow-worms,</hi> who ſhine by night, <hi>rotten ſticks</hi> that look il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtriouſly, but in a blind corner. So of old the ignoble <hi>Romans</hi> having excluded their King, degraded their Nation, (a juſt puniſhment for all ſuch hotheaded Innovators; whoſe Honour ſpreads no further then their Arms would hew their way) being therefore, no queſtion, aſſaulted by Kings and Princes, <hi>Pyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rhus, Mithridates,</hi> &amp;c. and becauſe they could not brook the ſo proſperous increaſe of ſo contemptible a government.</p>
                  <p>For let me ask them, why, I pray, two Conſuls? <hi>Rome</hi> was not founded by two Conſuls, Cannot the ſame power which foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded it, preſerve it? why muſt authority be bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, piece-meal, which as all other good things, are beſt, Intire: In all Fractures, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing muſt needs fall to the ground, ſome minute parts, at leaſt. <hi>Two heads are better than one</hi> in Counſel, not in Government, we plead not for a head without eyes, Counſel overthrows not Monarchy, but eſtabliſhes it,
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:53205:91"/>though by the way it is obſerved alſo, that Counſel, if too numerous, is inconvenient for reſolution, as multiplicity of Commentators obſcure the text.</p>
                  <p>To proceed, <hi>Two heads</hi> are unnatural, a mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous Government, an <hi>Amphibaena</hi> in Politiques; therefore monſtrous, becauſe they take it to be a Serpent with two heads, diſcharging poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon at both orifices; nor can Two be one po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litique head ſo eaſily, there are difficulties in the Politic as in the Natural Union. For what if <hi>Appius Coecus</hi> thinks himſelf as wiſe as <hi>Volumnius,</hi> &amp;c. who ſhall moderate or reconcile? There wants a third Conſul. Or if one excel the other, then we are reduced to one Conſul, the other is a very <hi>Bibulus.</hi> See what a task you wiſe men of <hi>Rome</hi> have ſet your ſelves! you muſt find Two of the ſame age, and the ſame prudence: (ſooner ſhall the <hi>Egyptians</hi> find a ſucceſſor to their ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mark'd <hi>Apis</hi>) or elſe have One Conſul ſtill, for the Junior, in manners, muſt hearken to the Senior, compliment him ſo far, and the inferior Family give way to the Collegue of the nobleſt Extraction.</p>
                  <p>Oh! <hi>but now they are free from Tyranny and a ſingle Perſon.</hi> Alas! Two are but one degree removed from Tyranny, and two may agree to be Tyrants, (why not?) as well as thirty!
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:53205:92"/>we have heard of thirty Tyrants in Greek ſtory. What remedy have you? <hi>Oh for that trick they ſhall be elected annually, they ſhall hold their Dignity but for a year.</hi> Mark the fears and jealouſies of People with their new deviſe; the Adminiſtration of a Conſulate muſt be annual, leaſt they ſhould deſign to retrieve Monarchy; ſo have I ſeen watch and ward obſerved in a houſe to keep poſſeſſion againſt the true Owner: Lo the difference of Monarchy from other Governments! be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold and love it, for if <hi>Fears</hi> and <hi>Jealouſies</hi> may be created ſometimes under it, other Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments are meerly founded upon them; whilſt Monarchy alone is founded upon Law Natural, Age, Authority, Love, Prudence, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Take the <hi>Venetian</hi> State, behold the <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> jealouſies, not of their Wives, but of their Governors, the grand Duke muſt not budge out of Town without the leave of the Senate, O pitiful grand Duke! O pitiful <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netians!</hi> For if the Duke ſhould once go out of Town, the Ducal Coronet bloſſoms into a Crown: and call you This, Liberty? he lives in Slavery, who lives in perpetual fears, a very <hi>Gyrus</hi> and <hi>Geta,</hi> who always dreads his Maſters coming. Nor let any man tell me this Eſtate hath laſted a great while, What is
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:53205:92"/>inferred from thence? Nothing of Nature or right Reaſon in it, tis a forced Government ſtill, wherefore tis wonderful it hath laſted ſo long, (tis true) becauſe things againſt Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture uſe to have a ſhorter period.</p>
                  <p>Now admit that <hi>annual</hi> Government were not founded in fears and jealouſies, yet ſtill in a Soveraign tis unreaſonable and ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous; unreaſonable, becauſe all Government requires Uſe and Experience, beſides Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to anſwer that infinite diſpatch that is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, but an <hi>annual</hi> Magiſtracy is confined to ſo ſhort a term, that the Governor ſcarce learns how to behave himſelf, till he is ready to lay it down. All the benefit is, that the annual adminiſtration is very convenient for Chronology indeed, but the ſame conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence would be greater, if they were ſtated yet ſhorter: let the Conſuls therefore be cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen to hold a month, or as the <hi>Decemviri</hi> were to rule in turn for a day— 'Tis All Boyes-play, Picture and Pageant, Princes of Revels, and Lords of a May time, rather than Government in earneſt intended.</p>
                  <p>Nor do we intend to ſay that Monarchy is more excellent on the account of its Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but alſo for its intrinſick perfection, the moſt ſufficient and reſponſible to all intents and purpoſes which brought Government at
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:53205:93"/>firſt into the world. I have ſaid tis the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment ſolely intended by Nature, it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be denied but tis the <hi>Standard</hi> of all the reſt; for in Ariſtocracy and Democracy all plurality of votes effect nothing but by virtue of the ſingle Form. They muſt be of <hi>One</hi> head and one mind, as if <hi>One</hi> ſingle perſon, elſe they can determine nothing. Now ſeeing a <hi>nemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne contradicente</hi> is ſeldome ſeen, they muſt be concluded by the <hi>major part,</hi> which major part rightly apprehended, is the ſpurious Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch, an Individual <hi>multiplied,</hi> though but <hi>One</hi> in it ſelf, or rather the <hi>many</hi> playing Mercuries part to the Auditors, while all wiſe men know there is but one <hi>Soſia.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And what can be required at the hands of Government which is not here found? Juſtice, we have it in Monarchy: for Kings and Judges of old were the ſame perſons. Honour we have it in Monarchy; Liberty, yea even Liberty, as I ſhall ſhew, we have it in Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy; Safety from civil diſcords and ſeditions, we find in Monarchy: Safety from Enemies abroad; who muſt go in and out before us but the Monarch? And this the <hi>Antimonarchiſts</hi> could never wipe off; Three <hi>hundred heads</hi> in time of exigency, in time of war, are feign to have recourſe to a <hi>ſingle</hi> perſon; the <hi>Romans</hi> not long after their <hi>Regifugium,</hi> (that they
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:53205:93"/>might ſee that their Rebellion was ſenſeleſs, when they ſtood in need of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which they had lately expelled) were forced to pitch upon a General, whom they called indeed a Dictator, to blind poor people, when none could be more abſolute King than he.</p>
                  <p>Here is the tryal of Government, as of the Pilot in a ſtorm; In a calm we may have Liberty — to fiſh, if we pleaſe, but in a Storm we muſt receive the word of Command. Was it ever heard of in the world, that an Army was led by a Committee, to march up before their Diviſions, and menace death to the oppoſer? O Alas poor ſouls! they muſt in their Rank, obſerve the Right hand Man; and ſo ſeeming Commanders, are, indeed Common Souldiers: as ſoon ſhall ſo many Ganders marching before their Diviſions be terrible to the Foe.</p>
                  <p>Yet this is not All: without Monarchy they cannot ſo much as raiſe an Army, for, the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my being at door; To ſee the ill luck of it, when the Conſul muſters, and the Tribune disbands as faſt, they muſt chuſe a Dictator to make a muſter.</p>
                  <p>You will ſay this is <hi>pro tempore</hi> only; But what will be ſaid, if all new Forms and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels return at laſt to their old Monarchs, as the
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:53205:94"/>River will run in its own <hi>alveus.</hi> I muſt not here recount, what Piques and Stratagems there are or have been laid againſt <hi>Venice,</hi> much leſs will I divine how near our un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy Neighbours are to their Reduction, to de <hi>united,</hi> not againſt, but under their Head: All the world knows, that the <hi>Roman</hi> State, of <hi>Royal</hi> became <hi>Popular,</hi> and at laſt <hi>Imperial.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Here we ſhould be Injurious to the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors, if they be not Reminded, That thoſe who have been zealous in violating Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, have commonly given the world ſad warning by their remarkable <hi>Exit.</hi> Not one of them who aſſaſſined <hi>Caeſar,</hi> which came not to a violent end, and the ſurly ill prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipled Family of <hi>Bruti</hi> ſhew that this is Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens perpetual Method; ſince <hi>Caeſars</hi> aſſaſſinate was ſlain in battel by <hi>Octavius,</hi> as, four hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years before, his Anceſtor was ſlain by <hi>Aruns,</hi> to teach us, that if we liſt not to be ruled by the Publick, the Indignation of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven will commiſſionate a private hand to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der us; where the <hi>Seepter</hi> will not ſway, the <hi>Sword</hi> muſt. And who can forget the Dire, but moſt juſt Fate, of our late <hi>Regicides,</hi> who deſerved to be pitied, but that ſome others do more deſerve it, I mean ſuch as will not take warning from their lamentable period. Never ſhall I wonder, if a dry Gallows
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:53205:94"/>frighteth not a Thief, when Exenteration and Quartering deterre not a Traytor; From ſuch a tender Conſcience Heaven deliver us.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Yea, but to be free from Tyranny and Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Rule of a ſingle Perſon, who often invades Liberty, and Property; violates the Priviledges of the Subject, is not this deſirable? <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder Monarchy we ſuffer in our Eſtates; Taxes, Subſidies drain our purſes, and after too great evacuation, leave them gaſping for life; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as under Democracy the People ſhall be Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and in what Government there is, we all ſhall have a ſhare.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Can this in our caſe be pleaded ſtill, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding what hath been juſt now deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered; I had thought the hints of an Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minious deſerved death ſhould fright us from theſe abortive dangerous Fancies. I anſwer fairly, Give me a <hi>free</hi> Republick with all my heart, where I may be free from Slavery and <hi>Treaſon</hi> too, where I may be free, Body and Soul, from the foul blot of <hi>Rebellion.</hi> The name of Rebel cates into and cankers the fleſh, beſide it ſticks like a curſe to the race and line of the attempter; Inceſt, Blaſphemy, Parricide, Sacriledg, four foul offences; but Rebellion, ſo ſoul it is, involves Three of them.</p>
                  <p>Again, let the Objectors Prudence conſider
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:53205:95"/>not only the Preſent, but ſomething of the Future, Who knows what will be after him? we have ſaid and ſeen with thanks to Heaven, that a baniſhed Prince may return again: In thy Behaviour to the Publick have regard ſay I to thy own Poſterity: thou ſhalt live but thy while; leave thy Children thy own and thy <hi>Princes</hi> bleſſing; thy Deeds and Writings per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps will not ſecure thy Eſtate to thy Heirs, unleſs thou draw up an Act of Oblivion, which ſince thou canſt not do, let thy Heirs have no occaſion for it. They who need it for their babes, muſt, when they dye, pray that the Prince may never be reſtored, that Right may never take place, which beſide the fruitleſneſs of the wiſh, how conducible it is to thoſe, who commend themſelves to another world, Let any ſober man judge.</p>
                  <p>As for <hi>Tyranny,</hi> and <hi>Arbitrary</hi> Power, Who will give us the definition of a Tyrant? 'tis more eaſie to aſperſe, than define. Every charge againſt a Governor will not amount to Tyranny, as neither every indictment of the Subject will come up to Treaſon. He who calls a Prince a Tyrant calls him Monſter, murders, buries, yea ſtakes his body; for None is a Tyrant, but he who in ſpight of all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural or Divine Laws, doth what he pleaſeth; Unleſs you can inſert that <hi>killing</hi> clauſe of fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonious
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:53205:95"/>Indictment, <hi>viz. Having not the fear of God before his eyes,</hi> you are no Subject, but a Viper, and deſerve to be trod on, after you have hiſſed and ſhewn your teeth. In the vaſtneſs of adminiſtration, 'tis a miracle, if there be no failures: In the receipt of a ſum of thouſands, there may be one or two leſs currant peices without the reproach, I hope, of Thievery or Cheat. How many times doth Innocence it ſelf (to ſay nothing of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avoidable Overſight) in a Governour, ſuffer as grievouſly as wilfull Malice? Even <hi>Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curgus,</hi> tis a ſhame to hear it, was affronted, pelted with ſtones, and driven from his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom: Hiſtory rings how juſt he was, and yet how ſavagely uſed. And ſo tis freſh in our memories, how the meekeſt and moſt inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent of all Princes was ſtab'd by the vulgar, by the inſcription of <hi>ultimus Tyrannorum.</hi> Naughty men calumniate ſtrongly for their own ends, cry out upon One to ſet up an hundred Tyrants: Beſides that many admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrations of Government may be preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to be Arbitrary, not becauſe they are ſo, but becauſe they are leſs uſuall, according to ſome emergencies extraordinary. Some wiſe men ſay that in all Supremacy, there muſt be ſome uſe of unconfined and arbitrary Power, which they prove by the confeſſion and
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:53205:96"/>practice of the People, where they arrogate Supremacy; but if This be too high or harſh a ſtring for us, then we ſay, whatever Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny or arbitrary Power ſignifies, tis a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fractary Spirit to cry out upon the beſt Form, for the apprehenſions of thoſe abuſes, which have been found in their own tumults and new Models. <hi>Cade</hi> and <hi>Tyler</hi> of old, as He who made the filthy rime to <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> were raſcally Tyrants. Arbitrary Government by Arms, Rumps, and Committees; moſt men, who either love the Republick or their own Eſtates, do dread the return of ſuch confounded Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publiques. To ſpeak what I think, if we ſearch the wound to the bottome, tis an impatiency of all Government, Divine though it be, in an untutored ſelfiſh people, that makes them ſo free in aſperſing our Governors; ſuch who have been bred to underſtand nothing ſo much as their private intereſt, inſtead of good manners or Religion it ſelf.</p>
                  <p>As to our <hi>Liberty,</hi> we have already ſaid, that juſt Liberty is not invaded, for unjuſt and unnatural, why is it deſired? what Man, who is truly man, dare ſtand by the wild no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the vulgar Liberty? let looſe the Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lons then, and the Mad-men, the Priſons and Bedlam be broke open in the name of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty; And let no man be bound, (That
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:53205:96"/>ſuits finely indeed, <hi>To be bound</hi>) no not to their good Behavior. Let all young men, Apprentices, command their Indentures, and renounce or cancel their oathes of faithful ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice. Let the Tenants deny Service to their Land-Lords, for a Land-Lord is but a linch of Tyranny, and what is Rent, but an exacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Tribute? by Nature we are all as good, one as another, and as free: let us remove therefore all encroachments (to ſpeak out) of the Rich upon the meaner ſort, and let Right be done, that is, let no great One run away with All, and an Hundred have juſt no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing: Let a through reformation and reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be made of our ancient Liberty, and let Eſtates and Fortunes be ſweetly levelled, for Government is a yoke; do our Lords think to make Brutes of us? This is the ſence not only of the <hi>Roman</hi> Slaves, and Imperial Boors, who break out into ſeditions at every opportunity, but of the poorer ſort among our ſelves; See we the neceſſity of Government / for who can out-vote them, who have moſt voices? It is expedient therefore for them to be inſtructed, that Levelling is Confuſion, neither has Nature made all equal, witneſs the difference of Ages, Statures, Beauties, Parts or Gifts of the Mind. Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is as neceſſary as Breathing, tis called a yoke, but an eaſie one, (and ſo we may call our
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:53205:97"/>garments, if we pleaſe, becauſe they are juſt fit to our bodies and keep them from grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of ſhape.) Religion is alſo called a yoke, and I hope, we are not weary of that. Add, that Liberty is a Faculty of operating according to our Station: We illuſtrate it by the Members of the Body, who in their Stations have their Freedoms and their <hi>Priviledges</hi> alſo, but yet exactly keep due order; the Foot may draw on a neat pantofle; the Hand put on a fine perfumed Cordovan; the Foot may walk forward, back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, Stand, Caper, Dance; the Hand may Give, Take, Exerciſe it ſelf to work or play, But neither may the Hand aſſaſſine the Face, or pull out the Eye, nor may one Foot kick againſt the other. No man hath Liberty to forget himſelf; Vulgar people, like little Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, think their Liberty is infringed, when the troth is, they are bleſt with Government; ſo did I reckon, when I was a Child, that I was in Priſon when I was in my good Fathers houſe, becauſe He pleaſed to reſtrain me from ſome licenciouſneſs, which was indulged in other children: Attend, my dear Country-men, if I had enjoyed my Liberty, I had been un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done; I ſee now that my Fathers reſtraint was for my good: Liberty is good, but we muſt not ſurfeit upon it, a convenient Doſe is very proper.</p>
                  <pb n="185" facs="tcp:53205:97"/>
                  <p>This being obſerved, I dare boldly ſay, there is no true Liberty, ſuch as conſiſts with Natural Order, but under Monarchy. We have branched out its Subordinations (as the Natural Body ſhoots it ſelf into Limbs) from the Soveraign to the Peſant; As then it is in the Natural Body, the Foot cannot <hi>Petition</hi> to have the arm lopt off, and ſet it ſelf in its room; ſo neither can the Peſant on pretence of Liberty challenge the Coat of a Gentleman; nor every Gentleman expect a Patent to be a Baron, In other Commonwealths its called Liberty; It is monſtrous deformity or diſlocation of Members, where the Leg grows out of the Armpit and its proud of the prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. But as proud as it is, it is a foul ſpecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle and the true Augurs will tell you ſuch monſtrous Governments ought to be aboliſhed.</p>
                  <p>Taxes and Tallage are the eaſieſt part of the objection, ſince Nature requires it, and all Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion allows it is due, every Profeſſion de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands a Fee, every Office its Salary; Tis on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ruſticks, and want of breeding, who at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taint the Prieſt, the Lawyer, the Phyſician, for a covetous Generation, while they only expect their Dues: Governors are Miniſters atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding continually upon the diſcharge of their Office; And muſt only they be unpaid for their attendance? your Coach-man and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-man muſt be conſidered for their atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance;
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:53205:98"/>Bees have more juſtice, who maintain their Maſter at the charge of the Hive. If God had made the Governors Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal, He, nor They would have expected Subſidy, but ſeeing the Prince partakes of the Common Nature, tis barbarouſly ſad to ſtarve Him, and tends to nought, but the change of Government; as they, who lie before a City in hope to famiſh it, ſeek to maſter it.</p>
                  <p>Now to all experience is it contrary to hope for redreſs from contribution under a Democracy, the <hi>Romans</hi> ceſſed the people to purpoſe, and ſpared not, they knew the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates of each Citizen, and they made uſe of them. It would do one good to conſider how free our Neighbour <hi>Eſcates</hi> are from Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſements and Taxes, or to remember brave <hi>Olivers</hi> ninety thouſand pound, with an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditament of thirty thouſand more to make it up 120000 <hi>lib. per menſem;</hi> Pay your exciſe for ſhame, O ye well wiſhers to Democracy, and mutter not at a round Aſſeſsment, for our bleſſed Democracy brought theſe knacks into <hi>England,</hi> and Let it not be ſaid that theſe Oppreſſions are no preſſures, when laid on us by Ignoble Uſurpers, but only then, are intol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable, when called for by our Natural Prince; when we will mutter and mutter, fume and ſmother, till we break out into a flame, and depopulate our Native Country,
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:53205:98"/>rather than pay a ſix pence <hi>Ship-mony</hi>—Oh how long ſhall we be called an unruly Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, who love our Prince, and yet ſell him for ſix pence? When ſhall we wipe off the reproach, ſo long thrown in our faces, that the King of <hi>England</hi> is a King of <hi>Furies, Rex Caco D— My heart is not hard enough to ſpeak out the word;</hi> Whence comes this foul <hi>Stigma,</hi> upon us? From the Stars? as Mr. <hi>Camden</hi> hath it, or the Temper of our Iſland? or is it a National Corruption drawn from our <hi>Saxon</hi> Anceſtors, (ſince the <hi>Britains</hi> are of better principles) or were we taught it by thoſe Birds of Prey, thoſe Families, (whoſe Gentry I queſtion not) who came in with the Conqueror, with this noble Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, to <hi>get</hi> what they could, and to <hi>part</hi> with as little as may be. Whenceſoever it is, we ſhall never be <hi>Queen</hi> of Iſlands, till we have laid by ſuch low Spirited principles, and ſtudied our good name by more noble, more magnifie Reſolutions.</p>
                  <p>To conclude, the Laſt is the moſt honeſt plea of all, <hi>viz.</hi> that under <hi>Democracy</hi> we ſhall have each of us a <hi>ſhare</hi> in the Government, Every man ſhall take his turn; for Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy ſeems a <hi>Monopoly</hi> of Authority, but we deſire a <hi>Free-Trade,</hi> in ſuch Merchandiſe, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Families will be the better, when the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nopoly
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:53205:99"/>is divided, as <hi>Alexanders</hi> Empire up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his death made ſeveral petty Princes: So it is we would be All Paramount; Tis a very loving propoſition, and it will pleaſe our Wives be ſure: But this is but a dream, a device to poſſeſs peoples heads to fool them into turbulency; For Government is no Frolick, no ridiculous ſport at Queſtions and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, where the Servant takes his turn of a <hi>Mock-King,</hi> and commands all the Houſe; but Government is a moſt ſerious conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to <hi>profit,</hi> not to pleaſe all; implanted in Nature, and Conſcience, and hence is it, that in that very ſportive <hi>way,</hi> where a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant is King, he cannot command his Maſter in all inſtances of Obedience requirable without egregious Impudence.</p>
                  <p>No, no; People are to be governed: Not an Army, or a Family, or any multitude can govern it ſelf, they may wiſh their own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation and welfare, but they underſtand not the means conducing thereto. Every member of the Army agrees in Victory or common Safety deſired; but the Methods, the Intrigues and Stratagems how to expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite the Whole from <hi>this</hi> danger, or make them Maſters of <hi>that</hi> advantage, Theſe are <hi>Arcana,</hi> which the private Souldier doth not comprehend; Some ſhrewd pates there may
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:53205:99"/>be among the Country Buskins, and greater Pretenders within the City-Walls, but he would not deſerve well of his Majeſty, who ſhall adviſe him to ſearch the Coffee-Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies for Privy Counſellors. Let them be wiſe, but with ſubmiſſion and a hearty belief that there are many in <hi>Place,</hi> wiſer than themſelves: Haſt thou Senſe and Sagacity, be thankful; but thou haſt no obligation to be Proud; I will allow thee to be wiſer than the <hi>Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude,</hi> I find it by thy diſcourſe; but if thou art wiſer than the <hi>Many,</hi> confeſs then with me that the Multitude ought not to govern.</p>
                  <p>I count them well imployed that Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly inquire into the reaſons of Divine San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, of whom at preſent I would gladly know, wherefore Heaven was pleaſed to ordein <hi>Succeſſive</hi> Monarchies and not <hi>Elective.</hi> Surely beſide the prevention of factious Field-meetings on the Peoples part, and crafty am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious practices of the competitors ſide: He did not reckon the People under their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended ſtate of Liberty, to be competent Electors of their Princes: the Votes of a Commonalty can do much, yet it is ſtill queſtionable, whether any voting themſelves to be wiſe and prudent, can effectually make them ſuch. So irrational is the claim of chooſing their Soveraign, when they have
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:53205:100"/>neither Power nor Skill to intitle them to it: For if they had power, it would yet be an offence, not to call in wiſer than themſelves to their aſſiſtance: As the <hi>wife,</hi> though ſhe hath unqueſtionable power, to chooſe her Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, tranſgreſſeth the rule, if ſhe hearkeneth not to the advice of her Parents. For how eaſie is the People, how <hi>ductile,</hi> hammered to all dimenſions, and degrees of tenuitie, a cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Sophiſter can lead them with a twin'd thread of Rhetorick, to be <hi>Pompeians</hi> to day, and <hi>Caeſarians</hi> to morrow. So tottering, and ſo unballaſted are their Judgements, that they turn with every tide, and comply with the wantonneſs of the wave, if any wind be ſtirring. Intoxicated with falſe principles, (and ſuch 'tis eaſie to infuſe,) they will meet in great bodies, as if acted by Divine <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct:</hi> So will minute Fiſhes meeting in ſhoals overturn a Navy; and an Army of Graſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers blaſt and burn up all that is goodly in the Land. They ſay they are <hi>Free-born,</hi> but they are kin to him, who would ſell his Birth-right; for Beef and Country Ale will marſhal a Province. You may diſcover their <hi>Character</hi> by their abilities in <hi>Spirituals:</hi> One paultry lying Spirit will found a numerous new Sect, which will ſtand at defiance with Humanity it ſelf: But if ſome men will ſtrive
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:53205:100"/>to forget their moſt amiable duty of Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, or, in ſpite of Conſcience, throw it off, we ſhall hope ſtill, that Monarchy will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petually flow with the largeſt ſtreams of time, that the Engliſh <hi>Roſes</hi> will never be blaſted in theſe our gardens: That the Royal Thiſtle ſhall avenge it ſelf upon all unhallowed fingers, that the <hi>Genius</hi> of the Nation, the <hi>Bent</hi> of our Gentry, the <hi>Sublimity</hi> of our Peers, the <hi>Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,</hi> Principles, and Spirit of our Clergy, I may add, the Flower of <hi>London</hi> its noble City and Lieutenancy, beſide the Dignity of our Iſland, the Fame of our Anceſtors (and what can I ſay more? except I ſhould add the Decree of Heaven, of which I hope theſe are no contemptible arguments) will appear againſt all reſtleſs deſigns of ignoble Repub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks, wherever contrived at Club or Coffee-meeting, and that the publick ſhouts of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> and Dominion of <hi>Wales</hi> upon every oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion ſhall by ringing their Loyal Ejaculati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons make <hi>Holy-day</hi> in the Air, while Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens applauding, and the Earth dancing a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raband, the Mountains ſhall anſwer the voi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Man, Woman and Child with the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful thundring rebound of, <hi>God ſave the</hi> KING.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:53205:101"/>
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>PAge 164. line 12. inconſiderate. p. 169. l. 8. Subſtitutions. p. 170. l. 15. Verd. 172. l. 16. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>le</hi> and p. 174. <hi>Syrus.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>Books ſold by <hi>Obadiah Blagrave</hi> at the <hi>Bear</hi> in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>DR. <hi>Gell</hi> on the New Teſtament, in <hi>Folio.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Phillips</hi> Engliſh Dictionary, explaining all hard Engliſh words, in <hi>Folio.</hi> price 12 <hi>s.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Smiths</hi> Chriſtians Religions Appeal againſt the Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks of this Age, in <hi>Folio,</hi> price 12 <hi>s.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Parthaniſſa,</hi> a Romance, in <hi>Folio.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pharamand,</hi> all twelve parts, in <hi>Folio,</hi> price 1. <hi>l.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Saunders</hi> Phyſiognomy and Chyromancy Metopoſupa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, explaining the moles of the body, of dreams &amp;c. in <hi>Folio.</hi> price 12. <hi>s.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Bromes Britannia</hi> being a large deſcription of <hi>England</hi> with Maps of the Country</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Seldens Mare Clauſum,</hi> concerning the Right and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion of the Sea, in <hi>Folio.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cockers</hi> large Copy Book in <hi>Folio,</hi> price 2. <hi>s.</hi> 6. <hi>d.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Stapletons</hi> tranſlation of <hi>Juvenal,</hi> in <hi>Folio.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Williams</hi> perfect Stateſman, in <hi>Folio.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Satyr againſt Hipocrites in <hi>Quarto.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Compleat Clerk and Scriveners Guide, in <hi>Quarto.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Stubs</hi> directions for Blood letting, in <hi>Quarto.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Biſhop <hi>Sanderſons</hi> Life, with divers Caſes of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Elton</hi> on the ten Commandments, Lords prayer and Creed</item>
               <item>St. <hi>Clement</hi>'s Epiſtles tranſlated out of the Greek.</item>
               <item>A Treatiſe of Taxes and Contributions by Sir <hi>William Pitt.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:53205:101"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
